[
    {
        "question": "Stress is a frequent aspect of the pilot's job. Under which of the following circumstances does it occur?\n1. Stress occurs whenever the pilot must revise his plan of action and does not immediately have a solution\n2. Stress occurs with inexperienced pilots when the situational demands exceed their individual capabilities\n3. Stress occurs if a pilot is convinced that he will not be able to find a solution for the problem he/she faces.",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "Only 1 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct, 2 and 3 are false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a cause of accidents, the human factor",
        "answer": "is cited in approximately 70 - 80 % of aviation accidents",
        "choiceone": "which is cited in current statistics, applies to the flight crew and ATC only",
        "choicetwo": "has increased considerably since 1980 - the percentage of accident in which this\nfactor has been involved has more than tripled since this date",
        "choicethree": "plays a negligible role in commercial aviation accidents. It is much more important\nin general aviation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet aircraft\ncommercial fleet shows that human error is involved in:",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases",
        "choiceone": "about 55% of cases",
        "choicetwo": "about 90% of cases",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "do not affect hypoxia at all",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Henry's Law explains the occurrence of:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness",
        "choiceone": "diffusion",
        "choicetwo": "hyperventilation",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Inhaling carbon monoxide can be extremely dangerous during flying.\nWhich of the following statements is correct?",
        "answer": "Carbon monoxide is odourless and colourless.",
        "choiceone": "Small amounts of carbon monoxide are harmless.",
        "choicetwo": "With increasing altitude the negative effects of carbon monoxide poisoning can be\ncompensated for.",
        "choicethree": "Carbon monoxide increases the oxygen saturation in the blood.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following applies to carbon monoxide poisoning?",
        "answer": "Several days are needed to recuperate from a carbon monoxide poisoning.",
        "choiceone": "A very early symptom of carbon monoxide poisoning is euphoria.",
        "choicetwo": "Inhaling carbon monoxide leads to hyperventilation.",
        "choicethree": "The human body shows no sign of carbon monoxide poisoning.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is oxygen mainly transported in the blood?",
        "answer": "Haemoglobin in the red blood cells.",
        "choiceone": "Blood fat.",
        "choicetwo": "White blood cells.",
        "choicethree": "Plasma.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot increase his tolerance to +Gz ?",
        "answer": "Tightening of the stomach muscles.",
        "choiceone": "Take an upright seat position.",
        "choicetwo": "Tighten shoulder harness.",
        "choicethree": "Relax the muscles and lean upper body forward.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is/are the symptom(s) of hypoxia ?",
        "answer": "Lack of concentration, fatigue, euphoria",
        "choiceone": "Pain in the joints",
        "choicetwo": "Low blood pressure",
        "choicethree": "Excessive rate and depth of breathing combined with pains in the chest area",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which symptom of hypoxia is the most dangerous for conducting safe flight ?",
        "answer": "The degradation of reasoning and perceptive functions.",
        "choiceone": "Lack of adaptation.",
        "choicetwo": "Dizziness.",
        "choicethree": "Lack of accommodation.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Breathing 100% will elevate the pilot's physiological safe altitude to approximately:",
        "answer": "40 000 ft",
        "choiceone": "22 000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "45 000 ft",
        "choicethree": "10 000",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What event can cause a hyperventilation (not required by physical need)?\n1. Pressure breathing.\n2. Anxiety or fear.\n3. Overstress.\n4. Strong pain.\n5. Jogging.",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct, 5 is false",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3,4 and 5 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1and 5 are both false",
        "choicethree": "Only 2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Breathing pure oxygen (without pressure) will be sufficient up to an altitude of:",
        "answer": "40000 FT",
        "choiceone": "80000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "45000 FT",
        "choicethree": "60000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment (> 10 m depth) is\nforbidden because it:",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below\n18 000 FT",
        "choiceone": "will always lead to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights",
        "choicethree": "prevents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms",
        "choiceone": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT",
        "choicethree": "are only relevant when diving",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The function of the Eustachian tube is to equalise the pressure between the:",
        "answer": "middle ear and the external atmosphere",
        "choiceone": "sinuses",
        "choicetwo": "sinuses of the nose and the external atmosphere",
        "choicethree": "nose, throat and the external atmosphere",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Trapped intestinal gases can cause severe pain.\nWhen is this the case?",
        "answer": "More frequent when flying above 18 000 FT in a non-pressurized aircraft.",
        "choiceone": "Only in pressurized aircraft when flying at higher flight levels.",
        "choicetwo": "At lower altitudes.",
        "choicethree": "During descent as well as during climb, when the cabin pressure altitude exceeds\n2 000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear most likely will occur",
        "answer": "when descending rapidly",
        "choiceone": "during a long high altitude flight",
        "choicetwo": "when climbing",
        "choicethree": "in sudden steep turns",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the \"Time of Useful Consciousness\" for a rapid decompression at 25,000 ft ?",
        "answer": "Between 3 and 5 minutes depending on the physical activities of the subjected\npilot",
        "choiceone": "Between 25 seconds and 1 minute 30 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "About 18 seconds",
        "choicethree": "About 30 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The thin walls of capillaries are permeable for:",
        "answer": "gases",
        "choiceone": "protein",
        "choicetwo": "platelets",
        "choicethree": "red blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Haemoglobin is:",
        "answer": "in the red blood cells",
        "choiceone": "dissolved in the plasma",
        "choicetwo": "in the platelets",
        "choicethree": "in the white blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The average pulse of a healthy adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": " 60 to 80 beats/min",
        "choiceone": "110 to 150 beats/min",
        "choicetwo": " 30 to 50 beats/min",
        "choicethree": " 90 to 100 beats/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in blood-pressure are measured by:",
        "answer": "pressoreceptors",
        "choiceone": "arteriols",
        "choicetwo": "pacemakers",
        "choicethree": "adrenal glands",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological effects of accelerations to the human body depend on:\n1. the duration of the G-forces\n2. the onset rate of the G-forces\n3. the magnitude of the G-forces\n4. the direction of the G-forces.",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1and 4 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During sustained positive G-forces the order of symptoms you can expect is:",
        "answer": "grey-out, tunnel vision, black-out and unconsciousness.",
        "choiceone": "grey-out, unconsciousness, black-out and tunnel vision",
        "choicetwo": "unconsciousness, black-out, tunnel vision and grey out.",
        "choicethree": "black-out, grey-out, tunnel vision and unconsciousness.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volume of air exchanged during a normal breathing cycle (tidal volume) is about:",
        "answer": "500 ml of air",
        "choiceone": " 75 ml of air",
        "choicetwo": "350 ml of air",
        "choicethree": "150 ml of air",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:",
        "answer": "the partial oxygen pressure is lower than at sea level.",
        "choiceone": "the composition of the air is different from sea level",
        "choicetwo": "the composition of the blood changes",
        "choicethree": "the percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure\n(i.e. when climbing a high mountain)",
        "choiceone": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure",
        "choicethree": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A passenger complains about a painful inflated belly at 8.000 feet. You advise him to:\n1. unbuckle and massage the belly\n2. stand up and let go the gases out of the intestines\n3. eat less gas forming food and avoid carbonhydrated beverages before flight in the\nfuture\n4. drink a lot of water throughout the flight",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "only 4 is correct",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 not advisable",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which symptom does not belong to the following list:",
        "answer": "leans",
        "choiceone": "bends",
        "choicetwo": "chokes",
        "choicethree": "creeps",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decompression symptoms are caused by:",
        "answer": "dissolved gases from tissues and fluids of the body",
        "choiceone": "release of locked gases from joints",
        "choicetwo": "low carbon dioxide pressure of inhaled air",
        "choicethree": "low oxygen pressure of inhaled air",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decompression sickness can normally be prevented by:\n1. avoiding cabin altitudes above 18 000 FT\n2. maintaining cabin pressure below 8 000FT when flying at high altitudes\n3. performing physical exercises before and during the flight\n4. breathing 100 % oxygen for 30 min prior and during the flight",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "only 3 is correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Following a rapid decompression at 30.000 feet, the time of useful consciousness\nwould be about:",
        "answer": "between 45 seconds and 1 minute 30 seconds",
        "choiceone": "5 to 10 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "10 to 12 minutes",
        "choicethree": "3 to 5 minutes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxic hypoxia may be caused by:\n1. climbing to a high altitude without using additional oxygen\n2. malfunction in the oxygen supply system\n3. loss of cabin pressurization at high altitude\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following gases is fundamentally responsible for decompression\nsickness?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen.",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen.",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide.",
        "choicethree": "Sodium.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is quite normal for aircrew to suffer\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013.. in air conditioned/ pressurized\naircraft",
        "answer": "itchy, dry eyes",
        "choiceone": "blurred vision",
        "choicetwo": "watery eyes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot suffers from hypothermia (e.g. after loss of cabin heating) his/her demand\nfor oxygen will be:",
        "answer": "initially increased",
        "choiceone": "reduced giving a better tolerance to hypoxia at higher altitudes",
        "choicetwo": "raised leading to an increased tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "unaffected",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the functional connection between neurones?",
        "answer": "Synapse.",
        "choiceone": "Occlusion.",
        "choicetwo": "By-pass.",
        "choicethree": "Interconnnection.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time required for complete adaptation is",
        "answer": "for high levels of illumination 10 sec and for full dark adaptation 30 min",
        "choiceone": "for night 10 sec and for day 30 min",
        "choicetwo": "for high levels of illumination 10 minutes and for low levels of illumination 30\nminutes",
        "choicethree": "for day and night: 30 min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the optical image forms in front of the retina; this results in:",
        "answer": "myopia",
        "choiceone": "hypermetropia",
        "choicetwo": "astigmatism",
        "choicethree": "presbyopia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to central vision, which of the following statements are correct ?\n-1: It is due to the functioning of rods\n-2: It enables details, colours and movement to be seen\n-3: Its very active both during the day and at night\n-4: It represents a zone where about 150.000 cones per mm are located to give high resolution capacity",
        "answer": "2,4",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,4",
        "choicethree": "1,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What factors can lead to a deterioration in vision?\n1.  Hypoxia\n2.  Smoking\n3.  Poor diet, lacking Vitamin A\n4.  Exposure to bright lights\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "2 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the factors which affect visual acuity are:",
        "answer": "Hypoxia, age and angular distance from the fovea",
        "choiceone": "Smoking, colour blindness and angular distance from the fovea",
        "choicetwo": "Colour blindness, alcohol and amount of light available",
        "choicethree": "Colour blindness, visibility and angular distance from the fovea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The intensity of a sound is measured in",
        "answer": "decibels",
        "choiceone": "hertz",
        "choicetwo": "curies",
        "choicethree": "cycles per second",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tinnitus is",
        "answer": "ringing in the ears",
        "choiceone": "very insensitive hearing",
        "choicetwo": "very sensitive hearing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Better resistance to tinnitus may occur",
        "answer": "if hearing protection is used in early flying life",
        "choiceone": "if masking devices are used",
        "choicetwo": "if ear drops are used regularly",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which force(s) affect(s) the otoliths in the utriculus and sacculus?",
        "answer": "Gravity and linear acceleration",
        "choiceone": "Gravity alone",
        "choicetwo": "Angular acceleration",
        "choicethree": "Linear acceleration and angular acceleration",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following systems are involved in motion sickness ?\n-1: Hearing\n-2: The vestibular system\n-3: Vision\n-4 The proprioceptive senses \"Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense\")\n-5: The gastrointestinal system",
        "answer": "2,3,4,5",
        "choiceone": "1,2,5",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which problem may occur, when flying in an environment of low contrast (fog, snow,\ndarkness, haze)?\nUnder these conditions it is:",
        "answer": "difficult to estimate the correct speed and size of approaching objects",
        "choiceone": "unlikely that visual illusions occur",
        "choicetwo": "no problem to estimate the correct speed and size of approaching objects",
        "choicethree": "impossible to detect objects",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dizziness and tumbling sensations, when making head movements in a tight turn, are\nsymptoms of",
        "answer": "\"Pilot`s vertigo\"",
        "choiceone": "\"Oculogravic illusion\"",
        "choicetwo": "\"Nystagmus\"",
        "choicethree": "\"Flicker-vertigo\"",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "\"Pilot's vertigo\"",
        "answer": "is the condition of dizziness and/or tumbling sensation caused by contradictory\nimpulses to the central nervous system (CNS)",
        "choiceone": "is the sensation to keep a rotation after completing a turn",
        "choicetwo": "announces the beginning of airsickness",
        "choicethree": "is the sensation of climbing caused by a strong linear acceleration",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can a pilot do to avoid \"Flicker vertigo\" when flying in the clouds?",
        "answer": "Switch strobe-lights off",
        "choiceone": "Dim the cockpit lights to avoid reflections",
        "choicetwo": "Engage the autopilot until breaking the clouds",
        "choicethree": "Fly straight and level and avoid head movements",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual disturbances can be caused by:\n1. hyperventilation\n2. hypoxia\n3. hypertension\n4. fatigue",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot, trying to pick up a fallen object from the cockpit floor during a tight turn,\nexperiences:",
        "answer": "coriolis illusion",
        "choiceone": "barotrauma",
        "choicetwo": "pressure vertigo",
        "choicethree": "autokinetic illusion",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are subjected to an illusion during night flying you should:",
        "answer": "continue on instruments",
        "choiceone": "use your oxygen mask",
        "choicetwo": "dim the cockpit lighting",
        "choicethree": "scan the surroundings",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the major protective measures against illusions is:",
        "answer": "comprehensive briefing and de-briefing",
        "choiceone": "wearing of polaroid sun glasses",
        "choicetwo": "regular eye tests",
        "choicethree": "wearing of good quality sun glasses",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following mechanisms regulate body temperature when exposed to extreme\nhigh environmental temperatures?\n-1: Shivering\n-2: Vaso-constriction of peripheral blood vessels\n-3: Sweating\n-4: Vaso-dilation of peripheral blood vessels",
        "answer": "3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "1",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The body loses water via:\n1. the skin and the lungs\n2. the kidneys\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is not correct and 2 is correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct and 2 is not correct",
        "choicethree": "both are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having a serious cold it is better not to fly, due to the extra risk of:\n1. flatulence\n2. pain in the ear during descent\n3. vertigo\n4. pain in the nasal sinuses",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to reduce the risk of coronary artery disease, exercise should:",
        "answer": "double the resting heart rate for at least 20 minutes, three times a week",
        "choiceone": "double the resting heart rate for at least an hour, five times a week",
        "choicetwo": "triple the resting heart rate for 20 minutes, once a week",
        "choicethree": "be avoided since raising the heart rate shortens the life of the heart",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is most true?",
        "answer": "Regular exercise is beneficial to general health, but the most efficient way to lose\nweight is by reducing calorie consumption",
        "choiceone": "Regular exercise is an impediment to losing weight since it increases the\nmetabolic rate",
        "choicetwo": "Regular exercise is beneficial to general health, and is the only effective way to\nlose weight",
        "choicethree": "Regular exercise and reduction in calorie consumption are both essential in order\nto lose weight",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual acuity during flight at high altitudes can be affected by:\n1. anaemia\n2. smoking in the cockpit\n3. carbon monoxide poisoning\n4. hypoxia",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Trace elements should be obtained through:",
        "answer": "A balanced diet",
        "choiceone": "Vitamin pills",
        "choicetwo": "Eating plenty of meat and vegetables",
        "choicethree": "Dairy products and vegetables",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hepatitis 'A' is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "food or water which has been contaminated.",
        "choiceone": "insect bites.",
        "choicetwo": "droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person.",
        "choicethree": "bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pilots should not take antihistamines because they may cause:\n1. Drowsiness and dizziness\n2. Hypoglycaemia\n3. Hyperventilation\n4. Flatulence\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "only 1",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are the most favourable solutions to manage phases of reduced or low vigilance\n(hypovigilance)?\n1. Keep active open communication between man and machine\n2. Use of amphetamines\n3. Reducing the intensity of the light\n4. Organising periods of rest during the flight",
        "answer": "1,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main factors which bring about reduced or low vigilance (hypovigilance)\n?\n1. The monotony of the task\n2. Tiredness and the need for sleep\n3. A lack of stimulation\n4. Excessive stress",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "2,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot experiences difficulties in the control of his aircraft and consequently omits to\nmonitor the fuel level. This is caused by:",
        "answer": "a lack of attention due to distraction",
        "choiceone": "both a lack of attention and a lack of alertness",
        "choicetwo": "a lack of alertness",
        "choicethree": "This pilot manages his attention well.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the two types of attention ?",
        "answer": "Selective and divided",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first stage in the information process is",
        "answer": "sensory stimulation",
        "choiceone": "perception",
        "choicetwo": "selective attention",
        "choicethree": "the recognition of information",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main limitation of the long-term memory is:",
        "answer": "unless information is accessed from time to time, retrieval of information can be\ndifficult",
        "choiceone": "the data storage time",
        "choicetwo": "the quantity of data which may be stored",
        "choicethree": "if enough information is entered at the same time, saturation may take place",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main limits of short-term memory ?\nIt is:\n-1: very sensitive to interruptions and interference\n-2: difficult to access\n-3: limited in size\n-4: information is lost within approximately 20 seconds unless it is actively or deliberately placed into the long term\nmemory.",
        "answer": "1,3 ,4",
        "choiceone": "2,4",
        "choicetwo": "2 ,3",
        "choicethree": "1,2 ,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Less experienced pilots differ from experienced pilots in the following way:",
        "answer": "inexperienced pilots refer to information more than experts when carrying out the\nsame task",
        "choiceone": "flight planning performance decreases with age, and experience is unable to mask\nthis deficiency",
        "choicetwo": "task for task, an expert's workload is greater than a novice's one",
        "choicethree": "experienced pilots are less routine-minded than young pilots because they know\nthat routine causes mistakes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human errors are frequent and may take several forms:",
        "answer": "an error can be described as the mismatch between the pilots intention and the\nresult of his/her actions",
        "choiceone": "all errors are avoidable through continuous and thorough training",
        "choicetwo": "a violation is an error which is always involuntary",
        "choicethree": "representational errors in which the pilot has properly identified the situation and\nis familiar with the procedure",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why must flight safety considerations consider the human error mechanism?\n-1: It is analysis of an incident or accident which will make it possible to identify what error has\nbeen committed and by whom. It is the process whereby the perpetrator is made responsible\nwhich may lead to elimination of the error.\n-2: If we have a better understanding of the cognitive error mechanism, it will be possible to\nadapt procedures, aircraft interfaces, etc.\n-3: It is error management procedure which enables us to continuously adjust our actions. The\nbetter we understand the underlying mechanism of an error, the better will be our means for\ndetecting and reducing future errors.\n-4: Since error is essentially human, once it has been identified by the use of procedures, a\nperson will be able to anticipate and deal with it automatically in the future.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "2 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors in rule-based control mode are of the\nfollowing type(s):",
        "answer": "errors of technical knowledge",
        "choiceone": "creative errors",
        "choicetwo": "handling errors",
        "choicethree": "routine errors",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An unnoticed way-point error entered in an aircraft data base is an example of:",
        "answer": "Latent failure/error",
        "choiceone": "Pro-active failure/error",
        "choicetwo": "Active failure/error",
        "choicethree": "Re-active failure/error",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To maintain good situational awareness you should:\n(1) believe only in your own interpretation of the data\n(2) gather as much data as possible from every possible source before making inferences\n(3) question whether your hypothesis still fits the situation as events progress and try to make time to review the\nsituation\n(4) consider ways of testing your situational hypothesis to see whether it is correct",
        "answer": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "all answers are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which biases relate to human decision making?\n1. Personal experience tends to alter the perception of the risk of an event occurring\n2. There is a natural tendency to want to confirm our decision even in the face of facts which contradict it\n3. The group to which an individual belongs tends to influence the particular decision\n4. There is natural tendency to select only objective facts for decision-making purposes",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the decision-making process, confirmation bias results in:",
        "answer": "a tendency to look for information which confirms the validity of the decision",
        "choiceone": "a tendency to look for approval by other crew-members, or by the ATC",
        "choicetwo": "choosing familiar solutions, even if they are not the best ones",
        "choicethree": "overestimating the frequency of some events",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In his/her behaviour, the \"ideal professional pilot\" is:",
        "answer": "both \"person\" and \"goal\" oriented",
        "choiceone": "\"goal\" rather than \"person\" oriented",
        "choicetwo": "\"person\" rather than \"goal\" oriented",
        "choicethree": "neither \"person\" nor \"goal\" oriented",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pilots are more easily inclined to take greater risks when:",
        "answer": "they are part of a group of pilots and they feel that they are being observed and\nadmired (e.g. air shows)",
        "choiceone": "making a flight over unfamiliar territory",
        "choicetwo": "they are not constrained by time",
        "choicethree": "making decisions independently of others",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The three types of Authority Gradient Cockpits are:",
        "answer": "Autocratic, Laisser-Faire and Synergistic",
        "choiceone": "Authoritative, Followership and Synergistic",
        "choicetwo": "Autocratic, Followership and Synergistic",
        "choicethree": "Authoritative, Laisser-Faire and Synergistic",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person's attitudes define a set of learned dispositions (likes and dislikes) which:",
        "answer": "influence a person's reaction and response to people, situations, etc.",
        "choiceone": "cannot be modified through training",
        "choicetwo": "is exactly the same as a person's personality",
        "choicethree": "do not depend on a person's past experiences",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following answers is correct?",
        "answer": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is adaptable.",
        "choiceone": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is not adaptable.",
        "choicetwo": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is not adaptable.",
        "choicethree": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is adaptable.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Performance can be affected by fatigue and lack of motivation. This situation can lead to",
        "answer": "under arousal",
        "choiceone": "under response",
        "choicetwo": "over response",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Signs of stress include:",
        "answer": "Perspiration, dry mouth, dilated pupils, fast breathing.",
        "choiceone": "Lowering of the blood pressure.",
        "choicetwo": "Faster, deep inhalation, stabbing pain around the heart.",
        "choicethree": "Rising of the blood pressure, pupils narrowing, stabbing pain around the heart.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In case of in-flight stress, one should:",
        "answer": "use all available resources of the crew",
        "choiceone": "demonstrate aggressiveness to stimulate the crew",
        "choicetwo": "always carry out a breathing exercise",
        "choicethree": "only trust in oneself; being sure to know the own limits",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the effects of excesive stress?",
        "answer": "It increases vigilance for a longer period than stress itself, but may focus attention\ninappropriately",
        "choiceone": "It activates resources stored in memory",
        "choicetwo": "It has very little immediate effect on vigilance and attention",
        "choicethree": "It reduces vigilance and focuses attention",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stress reaction is:",
        "answer": "the non-specific response of the body to demands placed on a person",
        "choiceone": "the specific stimuli causing a human body to respond",
        "choicetwo": "the non-specific stimuli causing a human body to respond",
        "choicethree": "the specific response of the body to demands placed on a person",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The biological reaction to stress is identical regardless of the cause of stress. This\nmechanism occurs in three phases and is referred to, by Selye, as the \"General\nAdaptation Syndrome\".\nThe sequence is:",
        "answer": "alarm phase - resistance phase - exhaustion phase",
        "choiceone": "alarm phase - denial phase - exhaustion phase",
        "choicetwo": "resistance phase - exhaustion phase - recovery phase",
        "choicethree": "exhaustion phase - resistance phase - adaptation phase",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Environmental sources of stress in the cockpit could be:\n1. noise and vibration\n2. acceleration\n3. radiation\n4. extreme temperatures\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct statement",
        "answer": "if is not corrected by the sun and other zeitgebers, the natural body cycle is greater\nthan 24 hours",
        "choiceone": "the natural body cycle is about 24 hours",
        "choicetwo": "if it is not corrected by the sun and other zeitgebers, the natural body cycle is less than\n24 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct statement",
        "answer": "a pilot who is fit will handle a high stress situation better than an unfit pilot",
        "choiceone": "fitness does not affect the ability to handle a high stress situation",
        "choicetwo": "a pilot who is fit may or may not handle a high stress situation better than an unfit pilot",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What seems to be the main role of Orthodox sleep?",
        "answer": "It essentially allows for physical recovery",
        "choiceone": "It includes physical and mental recuperation associate with fatigue",
        "choicetwo": "Via physical recovery, it is characterised by an alternation of dream phases and\nparadoxical phases",
        "choicethree": "Its main role is associated with activities of memory activities and restoration of\nattention capabilities",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main effects of a lack of sleep on performance?",
        "answer": "It increases fatigue, reduces concentration and increases the risk of sensory\nillusions",
        "choiceone": "It reduces concentration and fatigue only with sleep loss greater than 48 hours",
        "choicetwo": "It causes muscular spasms",
        "choicethree": "It increases fatigue and concentration difficulties, but facilitates stress\nmanagement by muscular relaxation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disturbance of the biological clock appears after a:\n1. bad night's sleep\n2. day flight Amsterdam - New York\n3. day flight Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following drawbacks are associated with automation ?\n1. Reduced competence in manually controlling the aircraft\n2. Increased likelihood of slips while programming automatic systems\n3. Difficulties in adapting to the use of a sidestick\n4. General decrease in technical reliability",
        "answer": "1,2",
        "choiceone": "1,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can vertigo be prevented in conditions of good visibility?",
        "answer": "By looking at the horizon",
        "choiceone": "By avoiding blinking",
        "choicetwo": "By looking approximately 5\u00b0 to one side of an object",
        "choicethree": "By closing the eyes momentarily",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Between which components, with reference to the SHELL Concept, covers pilot\nmisinterpretation of the old three-point altimeter?",
        "answer": "Liveware - Hardware",
        "choiceone": "Liveware - Liveware",
        "choicetwo": "Liveware - Software",
        "choicethree": "Liveware - Environment",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:",
        "answer": "L and S",
        "choiceone": "L and E",
        "choicetwo": "L and L",
        "choicethree": "L and H",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1972, a psychologist named Edwards presented a concept of the interface between\nflight crew and other parts of the airspace environment. What is this concept called\nand the names of those elements involved ?",
        "answer": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment, and liveware",
        "choiceone": "The SHELL Concept. Software, harmony, environment, and location",
        "choicetwo": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, economy and liveware",
        "choicethree": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment and location",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The atmosphere contains the following gases:",
        "answer": "78% nitrogen, 21% oxygen, 0,03% carbon dioxide, rest: rare gases",
        "choiceone": "78% helium, 21% oxygen, 0,03% carbon dioxide, rest: rare gases",
        "choicetwo": "78% nitrogen, 21% oxygen, 1% carbon monoxide, rest: rare gases",
        "choicethree": "78% helium, 21% oxygen, 1% carbon monoxide, rest: rare gases",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Below 70,000 ft., what gas makes up the major part of the atmosphere ?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen",
        "choicetwo": "Ozone",
        "choicethree": "Carbon dioxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct ?",
        "answer": "Oxygen diffusion from the blood into the cells depends on the partial oxygen\npressure gradient.",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen is mainly transported in plasma.",
        "choicetwo": "The gradient of diffusion is higher at altitude than it is at sea-level.",
        "choicethree": "Oxygen diffusion from the lungs into the blood does not depend on partial oxygen\npressure.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot increase his tolerance to +Gz ?",
        "answer": "Tightening of the stomach muscles.",
        "choiceone": "Tighten shoulder harness.",
        "choicetwo": "Relax the muscles and lean upper body forward.",
        "choicethree": "Take an upright seat position.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What event can cause a hyperventilation (not required by physical need)?\n1. Pressure breathing.\n2. Anxiety or fear.\n3. Overstress.\n4. Strong pain.\n5. Jogging.",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct, 5 is false",
        "choiceone": "Only 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3,4 and 5 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1and 5 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time between inadequate oxygen supply and incapacitation is called TUC (Time of\nUseful Consciousness). It",
        "answer": "varies individually and depends on cabin pressure altitude",
        "choiceone": "is not dependent on physical or psychological pressure",
        "choicetwo": "is the same amount of time for every person",
        "choicethree": "varies individually and does not depend on altitude",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After a cabin pressure loss in approximately 35 000 FT the TUC (Time of Useful\nConsciousness) will be approximately:",
        "answer": "30 -40 seconds",
        "choiceone": "3-4 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "10-15 seconds",
        "choicethree": "5 minutes or more",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma caused by gas accumulation in the stomach and intestines can lead to:",
        "answer": "pressure pain or flatulence",
        "choiceone": "decompression sickness",
        "choicetwo": "barosinusitis",
        "choicethree": "barotitis",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear",
        "answer": "is more likely, when the pilot is flying with a respiratory infection and during\ndescent",
        "choiceone": "causes severe pain in the sinuses",
        "choicetwo": "is to be expected during rapid decompressions, but an emergency descent\nimmediately following the decompression will eliminate the problem",
        "choicethree": "is only caused by large pressure changes during climb",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the ear could be affected by air pressure changes during climb and/or\ndescent?",
        "answer": "The Eustachian tube and the tympanic membrane (ear drum)",
        "choiceone": "The saccules and utricles",
        "choicetwo": "The cochlea",
        "choicethree": "The semicircular canals",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The type of hypoxia, which occurs at altitude is a explained by:",
        "answer": "Dalton\u00b4s law",
        "choiceone": "Henry\u00b4s law",
        "choicetwo": "Graham\u00b4s law",
        "choicethree": "Boyle Mariotte\u00b4s law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The cabin pressure in airline operation is",
        "answer": "normally between 6 000 to 8 000 feet",
        "choiceone": "normally between 2 000 to 3 000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "always equivalent to sea level",
        "choicethree": "normally between 4 000 to 5 000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning barotrauma are correct?",
        "answer": "It is caused by pressure differentials between gases in hollow cavities of the body\nand the ambient pressure",
        "choiceone": "It is caused by an increase in the partial pressure of oxygen associated with a\ndecrease in altitude",
        "choicetwo": "It is more likely to occur during ascent then during a rapid descent",
        "choicethree": "It is mainly associated with a sink rate which exceeds the ability of the body to\nbalance its internal pressures",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The procedure to be followed in the event of decompression when flying above 10,000\nft must:",
        "answer": "allow for the rapid supply of oxygen in order to prevent hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "allow for a rapid descent independent from sufficient supply of oxygen in order to\nprevent disorders due to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "make it possible to prevent hyperventilation owing to the inhalation of 100 %\noxygen",
        "choicethree": "make it possible to eliminate the risk of fogging due to the sudden pressure\nchanges",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following alternatives, which effects are due to positive acceleration (+ Gz)?\n- 1: Decrease in heart rate\n- 2: Pooling of blood into lower parts of the body\n- 3: Drop in blood pressure above heart-level\n- 4: Downward displacement or deformation of soft or mobile organs",
        "answer": "2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "1",
        "choicethree": "1,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The thin walls of capillaries are permeable for:",
        "answer": "gases",
        "choiceone": "red blood cells",
        "choicetwo": "platelets",
        "choicethree": "protein",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia has:",
        "answer": "not enough functional haemoglobin",
        "choiceone": "not enough platelets",
        "choicetwo": "not enough white blood cells",
        "choicethree": "not enough plasma",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The average pulse of a healthy adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": " 60 to 80 beats/min",
        "choiceone": "110 to 150 beats/min",
        "choicetwo": " 30 to 50 beats/min",
        "choicethree": " 90 to 100 beats/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "At rest the cardiac output (the quantity of blood the heart pumps in one minute) of an\nadult is approximately:",
        "answer": "5 litres/min",
        "choiceone": "75 litres/min",
        "choicetwo": "450 ml/min",
        "choicethree": "45 litres/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in blood-pressure are measured by:",
        "answer": "pressoreceptors",
        "choiceone": "adrenal glands",
        "choicetwo": "arteriols",
        "choicethree": "pacemakers",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following symptoms can indicate hypoxia?\n1. Blue lips and finger nails.\n2. Euphoria.\n3. Flatulence.\n4 .Unconsciousness..",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct.",
        "choiceone": "1, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct.",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During flight all crewmembers have one or more of the following symptoms:\n1. blue lips\n2. mental disturbances\n3. tingling sensations in arms and/or legs\n4. reduction of peripheral vision\nWhich is the possible cause?",
        "answer": "Hypoxia.",
        "choiceone": "Glaucoma.",
        "choicetwo": "Hypothermia.",
        "choicethree": "Hypoglycaemia.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If somebody starts breathing faster and deeper without physiological need",
        "answer": "the blood turns more alkaline",
        "choiceone": "the blood turns more acid",
        "choicetwo": "the blood pressure in the brain will rise significantly",
        "choicethree": "the acid-base balance of the blood will not change",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During hyperventilation:",
        "answer": "acidity level of the blood is reduced",
        "choiceone": "oxygen concentration of the blood is below normal",
        "choicetwo": "alkalinity level of the blood is reduced",
        "choicethree": "nitrogen concentration of the blood is above normal",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following gases is fundamentally responsible for decompression\nsickness?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen.",
        "choiceone": "Sodium.",
        "choicetwo": "Oxygen.",
        "choicethree": "Carbon dioxide.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "By 'long duration acceleration', we mean that it lasts more than:",
        "answer": "1 second",
        "choiceone": "1 minute",
        "choicetwo": "20 seconds",
        "choicethree": "5 minutes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the humidity of air in current in a pressurized cabin, we know that it:\n-1: varies between 40 and 60%\n-2: varies between 5 and 15%\n-3: may cause dehydration effecting the performance of the crew\n-4: has no special effects on crew members",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,4",
        "choicethree": "1,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype and involuntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\ncalled:",
        "answer": "reflex",
        "choiceone": "change of stimulation level",
        "choicetwo": "data processing",
        "choicethree": "control system",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference to instruments\nbecause:",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast",
        "choiceone": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \"greying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain",
        "choicethree": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation",
        "choiceone": "will improve the pilots depth perception",
        "choicetwo": "can cause colour-illusions",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A shining light is fading out (i. e. when flying into fog, dust or haze). What kind of\nillusion could the pilot get?",
        "answer": "The source of light moves away from him",
        "choiceone": "The source of light stands still",
        "choicetwo": "The light source will make the pilot believe, that he is climbing",
        "choicethree": "The source of light is approaching him with increasing speed",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flickering light when reflected from spinning rotor blades",
        "answer": "can cause spatial disorientation and/or nausea",
        "choiceone": "can be avoided when the strobe-lights are switched on",
        "choicetwo": "should be avoided, because it may destroy the optic nerve",
        "choicethree": "has no effect",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Vitamin A and possibly vitamins B and C are chemical factors and essential to good night vision:\n1. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease night vision performance\n2. An excess intake of vitamin A will improve night vision performance significantly\n3. Pilots should be carefully concerned to take a balanced diet containing sufficient vitamin A\n4. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease visual acuity in photopic vision but not in scotopic vision",
        "answer": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 and 4 are false",
        "choiceone": "Only 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are false, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The fovea",
        "answer": "is an area in which cones predominate",
        "choiceone": "is the area responsible for night vision",
        "choicetwo": "is an area in which rods predominate",
        "choicethree": "is sensitive to very low intensities of light",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to perceive colour vision, it is necessary:\n-1: for there to be considerable amount of light (ambient luminosity)\n-2: at night to look at the point to be observed at an angle of 15\u00b0\n-3: to allow the eye a period of time to get used to the light\n-4: to avoid white light",
        "answer": "1",
        "choiceone": "3",
        "choicetwo": "2,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part",
        "choiceone": "crystalline lens",
        "choicetwo": "rods located in its central part",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its peripheral zone",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Accommodation, which enables a clear image to be obtained, is accomplished by\nwhich of the following?",
        "answer": "The crystalline lens",
        "choiceone": "The retina",
        "choicetwo": "The rods",
        "choicethree": "The cones",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual perception of depth at close to medium distance is primarily due to",
        "answer": "binocular vision",
        "choiceone": "the high sensitivity of the retina",
        "choicetwo": "peripheral vision",
        "choicethree": "interactions between cones and rods",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information:",
        "answer": "is limited to the foveal area of the retina",
        "choiceone": "is governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20 degrees of angle",
        "choicetwo": "is almost equally shared by the entire retina",
        "choicethree": "is limited to daytime using the rod cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is:",
        "answer": "long sightedness linked with age",
        "choiceone": "short sightedness",
        "choicetwo": "high intraocular pressure",
        "choicethree": "myopia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which scanning technique should be used when flying at night?",
        "answer": "Look to the side (10 - 15 deg) of the object.",
        "choiceone": "Look directly at the object.",
        "choicetwo": "Blink your eyes.",
        "choicethree": "Look with one eye.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Empty field myopia is caused by:",
        "answer": "lack of distant focal points",
        "choiceone": "atmospheric perspective",
        "choicetwo": "flying over mountainous terrain",
        "choicethree": "ozone at altitude",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is",
        "answer": "normal deterioration of short sight with age",
        "choiceone": "normal deterioration of long sight with age",
        "choicetwo": "a limiting medical condition affecting the eyes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Eustachian tube connects:",
        "answer": "the middle ear and the throat",
        "choiceone": "the middle ear and the inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "the semi circular canals",
        "choicethree": "the auditory duct and the inner ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the vestibular apparatus is responsible for the detection of angular\nacceleration?",
        "answer": "The semicircular canals",
        "choiceone": "The cochlea",
        "choicetwo": "The Eustachian tube",
        "choicethree": "The sacculus and utriculus",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The vestibular apparatus",
        "answer": "reacts to linear/angular acceleration and gravity",
        "choiceone": "reacts to vibrations of the cochlea",
        "choicetwo": "gives the impression of hearing",
        "choicethree": "reacts to pressure changes in the middle ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The impression of an apparent movement of light when stared at for a relatively long\nperiod of time in the dark is called",
        "answer": "\"autokinesis\"",
        "choiceone": "\"oculografic illusion\"",
        "choicetwo": "\"white out\"",
        "choicethree": "\"oculogyral illusion\"",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot approaching a runway which is narrower than normal may feel he is at a greater\nheight than he actually is. To compensate he may fly a",
        "answer": "flatter than normal approach with the tendency to undershoot",
        "choiceone": "higher than normal approach with the tendency to overshoot",
        "choicetwo": "compensatory glide path and stall out",
        "choicethree": "compensatory glide path and land long",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a coordinated level  turn will",
        "answer": "make the body`s pressure receptors feel an increased pressure along the body`s\nvertical axis",
        "choiceone": " first give the impression of climb , then the impression of descent",
        "choicetwo": "make the seat-of-the-pants sense feel a decreased pressure along the body`s\nvertical axis",
        "choicethree": "make the blood being pooled in the head",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "\"Pilot's vertigo\"",
        "answer": "is the condition of dizziness and/or tumbling sensation caused by contradictory\nimpulses to the central nervous system (CNS)",
        "choiceone": "is the sensation to keep a rotation after completing a turn",
        "choicetwo": "announces the beginning of airsickness",
        "choicethree": "is the sensation of climbing caused by a strong linear acceleration",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the correct action to counteract vertigo?",
        "answer": "Believe the instruments",
        "choiceone": "Rely on the information from the semicircular canals, since these will be\ntransmitting correct information",
        "choicetwo": "Concentrate on the vertical speed indicator",
        "choicethree": "Reduce rate of breathing until all symptoms disappear, then breathe again\nnormally",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual disturbances can be caused by:\n1. hyperventilation\n2. hypoxia\n3. hypertension\n4. fatigue",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot is starring at an isolated stationary light for several seconds in the dark\nhe might get the illusion that:",
        "answer": "the light is moving",
        "choiceone": "the size of the light is varying",
        "choicetwo": "the intensity of the light is varying",
        "choicethree": "the colour of the light is varying",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When you stare at a single light against the dark (i.e.. an isolated star) you will find the\nlight appears to move after some time. This phenomenon is called:",
        "answer": "autokinetic phenomenon",
        "choiceone": "leans",
        "choicetwo": "black hole illusion",
        "choicethree": "coriolis illusion",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How may haze effect perception?",
        "answer": "Objects seem to be further away than in reality.",
        "choiceone": "Haze makes the eyes to focus at infinity",
        "choicetwo": "Objects seem to be closer than in reality.",
        "choicethree": "Objects will give better contrast.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 'Black hole' phenomenon occurs during approaches at night and over water,\njungle or desert. When the pilot is lacking visual cues other than those of the\naerodrome there is an illusion of",
        "answer": "being too high and too far away, dropping low and landing short",
        "choiceone": "being too low, flying a steeper approach than normal",
        "choicetwo": "being too close, landing long",
        "choicethree": "climbing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is",
        "choiceone": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity",
        "choicetwo": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"Leans\" or Somatogyral illusion can be caused by:",
        "answer": "Reducing bank following a prolonged turn",
        "choiceone": "A carrier take-off",
        "choicetwo": "Bunting the aircraft",
        "choicethree": "Going into a turn too quickly",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "We can observe the following in relation to a state of hypothermia:",
        "answer": "reasoning problems as soon as body temperature falls below 37\u00b0C",
        "choiceone": "a substantial increase in internal body temperature whereas peripheral\ntemperature at the skin is stable",
        "choicetwo": "widespread pain in the joints",
        "choicethree": "greater capacity for adaptation than in a hot atmosphere",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n1  Hypothermia affects physical and mental abilities.\n2  Man has effective natural protection against intense cold.\n3  Shivering makes it possible to combat the cold to a certain extent, but uses up a lot of energy\n4  Disorders associated with hypothermia appear at a body temperature of less than 35\u00b0C",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "2,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the waste products of the metabolic process in the cell is:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "protein",
        "choicetwo": "fat",
        "choicethree": "sugar",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having a serious cold it is better not to fly, due to the extra risk of:\n1. flatulence\n2. pain in the ear during descent\n3. vertigo\n4. pain in the nasal sinuses",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma is caused by an increase or decrease in the volume of the gases\ncontained in the body's cavities. Which, in practice, are the most frequent locations of\nsuch problems?",
        "answer": "Facial sinuses, middle ear and dental cavities",
        "choiceone": "Facial sinuses, outer ear and stomach",
        "choicetwo": "Inner ear, facial sinuses and stomach",
        "choicethree": "Dental cavities, outer ear and eyes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When assessing an individual's risk of developing coronary artery disease, the following factors may contribute:\n1.obesity\n2.chronic stress\n3.smoking\n4.family history",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "Only 3 is correct, 1, 2 and 4 are false",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 and 4 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss is influenced by",
        "answer": "the duration and intensity of a noise",
        "choiceone": "the duration of a noise but not its intensity",
        "choicetwo": "the intensity of the noise but not its duration",
        "choicethree": "the suddenness of onset of a noise",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To avoid incapacity due to gastro-intestinal problems, it is recommended that a\nsimple, easily digested meal before boarding the aircraft should be accompanied by:",
        "answer": "non-carbonated water",
        "choiceone": "no drinks, as fluids are not important",
        "choicetwo": "wine or beer",
        "choicethree": "carbonated water.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is corrected with",
        "answer": "plus lenses",
        "choiceone": "minus lenses",
        "choicetwo": "pin cushion shaped lenses",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot who smokes will lose some of his capacity to transport oxygen combined with\nhaemoglobin.\nWhich percentage of his total oxygen transportation capacity would he give away\nwhen he smokes one pack of cigarettes a day?",
        "answer": "5 - 8%",
        "choiceone": "12 - 18%",
        "choicetwo": "0.5 - 2%",
        "choicethree": "20 - 25%",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Approximately how long will a blood/alcohol level of 60 mgm/100ml take to return to\nnormal ?",
        "answer": "4 hours",
        "choiceone": "1 hour",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours",
        "choicethree": "20 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motor programmes are:",
        "answer": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed without\ncontinuous conscious control",
        "choiceone": "rules that enable us to deal with preconceived situations",
        "choicetwo": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed only under\ncontinuous conscious control",
        "choicethree": "rules that enable us to deal with novel situations",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main limits of short-term memory ?\nIt is:\n-1: very sensitive to interruptions and interference\n-2: difficult to access\n-3: limited in size\n-4: information is lost within approximately 20 seconds unless it is actively or deliberately placed into the long term\nmemory.",
        "answer": "1,3 ,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2 ,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,4",
        "choicethree": "2 ,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following characteristics apply to short-term memory ?\n- 1: It is limited in time and size\n- 2: It is unlimited in time and limited in size\n- 3: It is stable and insensitive to disturbances\n- 4: It is limited in time and unlimited in size",
        "answer": "1",
        "choiceone": "2,3",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to short-term memory, we can say that:",
        "answer": "it is made up of everyday information for immediate use, and is limited in its\ncapacity for storing and retaining data",
        "choiceone": "it is a stable form of working memory, and thus not very sensitive to any\ndisturbance",
        "choicetwo": "it is made up of everyday information for immediate use, and is limited in terms of\nthe time for which it retains data but not in its storage capacity",
        "choicethree": "it stores mainly procedural knowledge (skills)",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having interrupted the Captain for a sound reason, the co-pilot should:",
        "answer": "Remind him/her of his/.her last action before the interruption",
        "choiceone": "Never interrupt his/her Captain at a critical stage of flight",
        "choicetwo": "Repeat the interruption twice so that the Captain's attention is focussed on the\nnew information",
        "choicethree": "Ensure there is no ATC traffic on the radio that may be causing a possible\ndistraction before continuing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Less experienced pilots differ from experienced pilots in the following way:",
        "answer": "inexperienced pilots refer to information more than experts when carrying out the\nsame task",
        "choiceone": "task for task, an expert's workload is greater than a novice's one",
        "choicetwo": "experienced pilots are less routine-minded than young pilots because they know\nthat routine causes mistakes",
        "choicethree": "flight planning performance decreases with age, and experience is unable to mask\nthis deficiency",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The errors of a motor programme are:",
        "answer": "Action Slip and Environmental Capture (Habituation)",
        "choiceone": "Action Slip and Confirmation Bias",
        "choicetwo": "Confirmation error and Error of Commission",
        "choicethree": "Habituation and Error of Commission",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \"reversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\" are:\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when situations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress",
        "answer": "1. and 3.",
        "choiceone": "2. and 3.",
        "choicetwo": "3.",
        "choicethree": "1. and 2.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following concepts relating to human reliability is true ?",
        "answer": "If equipment is designed in such a way that it can be operated wrongly, then\nsooner or later, it will be.",
        "choiceone": "Response to a particular stressful influence does not vary from one person to\nanother.",
        "choicetwo": "Expectation has no influence on perception.",
        "choicethree": "Performance is totally independent of motivation.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Analysis of accidents involving the human factor in aviation shows that:",
        "answer": "there is hardly ever a single cause responsible",
        "choiceone": "only front-line operators are involved",
        "choicetwo": "failure of the human factor is always connected with technical breakdowns",
        "choicethree": "only pilot training will make it possible to improve the situation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The decision making in emergency situations requires firstly:",
        "answer": "delegation of tasks and crew coordination",
        "choiceone": "speed of reaction",
        "choicetwo": "informing ATC thoroughly about the situation",
        "choicethree": "the whole crew to focus on the problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In terms of decision-making, the intention to become integrated into the team, to be\nrecognised as the leader or to avoid conflicts may lead to:",
        "answer": "the attempt to agree on decisions made by other crew members",
        "choiceone": "a fast and decisive option",
        "choicetwo": "an authoritarian approach thus demonstrating ones own ability to lead",
        "choicethree": "the improvement of internal risk assessment capabilities",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Habits and routine can influence decision-making in a way that:",
        "answer": "shows a tendency to select the most familiar solution first and foremost,\nsometimes to the detriment of achieving the best possible result",
        "choiceone": "one always selects a choice in accordance with the company's usual practices",
        "choicetwo": "habit is the product of experience and should be used as a primary consideration\nin all decisions",
        "choicethree": "professional pilots will never question established procedures",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making can be influenced by the following factors:\n1. people tend to conform to opinions expressed by a majority within the group they belong to\n2. people always keep the future decisions in line with those their superiors have made in the past\n3. people more easily tend to select data which meet their expectations\n4. people rarely base decisions on their personal preferences but rather on rational information\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 3",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 4",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the decision-making process, confirmation bias results in:",
        "answer": "a tendency to look for information which confirms the validity of the decision",
        "choiceone": "overestimating the frequency of some events",
        "choicetwo": "a tendency to look for approval by other crew-members, or by the ATC",
        "choicethree": "choosing familiar solutions, even if they are not the best ones",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following responses is an example of \"habit reversion\" (negative habit\ntransfer):",
        "answer": "A pilot who has flown many hours in an aircraft in which the fuel lever points\nforward for the ON position, may unintentionally turn the fuel lever into the false\nposition, when flying a different aircraft, where the fuel lever has to point aft to be\nin the ON position",
        "choiceone": "Incorrect anticipation of an air traffic controller\u00b4s instructions",
        "choicetwo": "habitually missing an item on the checklist or missing the second item when two\nitems are on the same line",
        "choicethree": "Turning the aircraft to the left when intending to turn it to the right",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An important aspect of Situational Awareness is:",
        "answer": "When a pilot's perception equals reality",
        "choiceone": "When the pilot perceives the instant and immediate situation both inside and\noutside the cockpit",
        "choicetwo": "When the pilot perceives the situation both inside and outside the aircraft",
        "choicethree": "When a pilot is sure that the situation both inside and outside the aircraft is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to overcome an overload of work during the flight, it is necessary to:\n-1: know how to use one's own reserve of resources in order to ease the burden on the crew.\n-2: divide up tasks among the crew.\n-3: ensure that the long-term memory is used as much as possible as short term memory will add to the\nstress.\n-4: drop certain tasks and stick to high-level priorities.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cohesion is a major advantage in times of:",
        "answer": "Difficulty",
        "choiceone": "Success",
        "choicetwo": "Personal advancement",
        "choicethree": "Achievement",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person's attitudes define a set of learned dispositions (likes and dislikes) which:",
        "answer": "influence a person's reaction and response to people, situations, etc.",
        "choiceone": "cannot be modified through training",
        "choicetwo": "do not depend on a person's past experiences",
        "choicethree": "is exactly the same as a person's personality",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Very high ambition and need for achievement",
        "answer": "disturb the climate of cooperation",
        "choiceone": "fulfil the requirements of stress resistance",
        "choicetwo": "always promote teamwork",
        "choicethree": "improves the coping process with personal failures",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements with regard to motivation is correct?",
        "answer": "Excessive motivation in combination with high levels of stress will limit attention\nmanagement capabilities",
        "choiceone": "Low motivation will guarantee adequate attention management capabilities",
        "choicetwo": "Too much motivation may result in hypovigilance and thus in a decrease in\nattention",
        "choicethree": "Motivation will reduce risk",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Concerning the relationship between performance and stress, which of the following\nstatements is correct?",
        "answer": "A moderate level of stress may improve performance.",
        "choiceone": "A well trained pilot is able to eliminate any kind of stress completely when he is\nscheduled to fly.",
        "choicetwo": "Domestic stress will not affect the pilot's performance because he is able to leave\nthis type of stress on the ground.",
        "choicethree": "A student will learn faster and better under severe stress.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot successfully completes a difficult and stressful landing at an aerodrome. The\nnext time a landing is attempted under the same conditions and at the same\naerodrome, is the pilot likely to experience:",
        "answer": "a lower level of stress",
        "choiceone": "the same stress level as the first landing",
        "choicetwo": "the pilot should only attempt a landing at the same aerodrome if the conditions are\nimproved",
        "choicethree": "a higher level of stress",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about acute or chronic fatigue is INCORRECT?",
        "answer": "Acute fatigue generally has psychological roots.",
        "choiceone": "Chronic fatigue may be caused by inadequate recuperation from periods of acute\nfatigue.",
        "choicetwo": "Chronic fatigue may lead to a person being totally apathetic and indifferent to what\ngoes on around them.",
        "choicethree": "Acute fatigue is felt after a period of significant exertion or emotional excitement.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress management programmes usually involve:",
        "answer": "the prevention and/or the removal of stress",
        "choiceone": "the use of psychoactive drugs",
        "choicetwo": "only the prevention of stress",
        "choicethree": "only the removal of stress",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following operations are performed more effectively by people than by automatic systems ?\n1. Qualitative decision-making\n2. Waiting for an infrequent phenomenon\n3. Monitoring to ensure that certain values are not exceeded\n4. Detection of unusual conditions (smell, noise, etc.)",
        "answer": "1,4",
        "choiceone": "3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can vertigo be prevented in conditions of good visibility?",
        "answer": "By looking at the horizon",
        "choiceone": "By closing the eyes momentarily",
        "choicetwo": "By avoiding blinking",
        "choicethree": "By looking approximately 5\u00b0 to one side of an object",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The errors resulting from an illogical indexing system in an operations manual are\nrelated to an interface mismatch between",
        "answer": "Liveware - Software",
        "choiceone": "Liveware - Liveware",
        "choicetwo": "Liveware - Environment",
        "choicethree": "Liveware - Hardware",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An increase in the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood leads to:",
        "answer": "an increased respiratory rate",
        "choiceone": "a decrease of acidity in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "an improving resistance to hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of red blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "At which altitude is it necessary to breathe 100% oxygen plus pressure after a rapid\ndecompression ?",
        "answer": "Approximately 40 000 ft.",
        "choiceone": "Approximately 50 000 ft.",
        "choicetwo": "Approximately 20 000 ft.",
        "choicethree": "Approximately 14 000 ft.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is true concerning carbon monoxide?",
        "answer": "It is to be found in the smoke of cigarettes lifting up a smoker's \"physiological\naltitude\".",
        "choiceone": "It has no physiological effect when mixed with oxygen.",
        "choicetwo": "It is always present in the lungs.",
        "choicethree": "It combines 5 times faster to the haemoglobin than oxygen.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia especially dangerous for pilots flying solo?",
        "answer": "Since the first signs of hypoxia are generally hard to detect.",
        "choiceone": "A solo pilot is more prone to illusions.",
        "choicetwo": "Difficulties in controlling the aircraft.",
        "choicethree": "Hypoxia improves night vision therefore the pilot will have no indication of danger.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by",
        "answer": "a lack of red blood cells in the blood or decreased ability of the haemoglobin to\ntransport oxygen",
        "choiceone": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases",
        "choicetwo": "a lack of nitrogen in ambient air",
        "choicethree": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) is:",
        "answer": "the length of time during which an individual can act with both mental and physical\nefficiency; measured from the moment at which he/she is exposed to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "the time before becoming unconscious at a sudden pressure loss",
        "choicetwo": "the time after pressure loss until decompression sickness sets in",
        "choicethree": "the time between the start of hypoxia and death",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms",
        "choiceone": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "are only relevant when diving",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The function of the Eustachian tube is to equalise the pressure between the:",
        "answer": "middle ear and the external atmosphere",
        "choiceone": "sinuses",
        "choicetwo": "sinuses of the nose and the external atmosphere",
        "choicethree": "nose, throat and the external atmosphere",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma caused by gas accumulation in the stomach and intestines can lead to:",
        "answer": "pressure pain or flatulence",
        "choiceone": "barosinusitis",
        "choicetwo": "barotitis",
        "choicethree": "decompression sickness",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Eustachian tube is the passage way between the",
        "answer": "throat and the middle ear",
        "choiceone": "nose, throat and inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "sinuses and the throat",
        "choicethree": "nose, throat and the external auditory canal",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation causes",
        "answer": "a reduction of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choiceone": "hypochondria",
        "choicetwo": "acidosis",
        "choicethree": "an excess of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety and fear can cause",
        "answer": "hyperventilation",
        "choiceone": "spatial disorientation",
        "choicetwo": "hypoglycaemia",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following laws explains bubbles of nitrogen coming out of solution in\nbody tissues due to a decrease in atmospheric pressure?",
        "answer": "Henry's law",
        "choiceone": "Boyle's law",
        "choicetwo": "Gay Lussac's law",
        "choicethree": "Dalton's law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main function of the red blood cells is",
        "answer": "to transport oxygen",
        "choiceone": "to participate in the process of coagulation of the blood",
        "choicetwo": "to contribute to the immune response of the organism",
        "choicethree": "the cellular defence of the organism",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Altitude-hypoxia, when breathing ambient air, should not usually occur (indifferent\nphase)",
        "answer": "below 3 000 m",
        "choiceone": "up to 5 000 m",
        "choicetwo": "between 3 000 m and 5 000 m",
        "choicethree": "between 5 000 m and 7 000 m",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following alternatives, which effects are due to positive acceleration (+ Gz)?\n- 1: Decrease in heart rate\n- 2: Pooling of blood into lower parts of the body\n- 3: Drop in blood pressure above heart-level\n- 4: Downward displacement or deformation of soft or mobile organs",
        "answer": "2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The thin walls of capillaries are permeable for:",
        "answer": "gases",
        "choiceone": "red blood cells",
        "choicetwo": "platelets",
        "choicethree": "protein",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\nThe blood-pressure which is measured during flight medical checks is the pressure",
        "answer": "in the artery of the upper arm (representing the pressure at heart level)",
        "choiceone": "in the veins of the upper arm",
        "choicetwo": "in the muscles of the upper arm",
        "choicethree": "in all the blood-vessels of the body (representing the pressure in the whole body)",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The blood-pressure depends on:\n1. the work of the heart\n2. the peripheral resistance\n3. the elasticity of the arterial walls\n4. the blood volume and viscosity",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1,3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The pressoreceptors are located in",
        "answer": "the carotid and aortic arterial vessels",
        "choiceone": "the heart",
        "choicetwo": "the lungs",
        "choicethree": "the intestines",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the pressoreceptors signal a lowering of the blood-pressure there are adaptation\nmechanisms which result in:\n1. an increase of respiratory activity\n2. the arteriols to constrict\n3. an increase of cardiac output\n4. the heart rate to rise",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicethree": "1,3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive g will cause the blood-pressure in the brain to:",
        "answer": "decrease",
        "choiceone": "first increase, then decrease",
        "choicetwo": "remain constant",
        "choicethree": "increase",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal rate of breathing of an adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": "16 cycles per minute",
        "choiceone": "72 cycles per minute",
        "choicetwo": "32 cycles per minute",
        "choicethree": "4 cycles per minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The transfer of oxygen from the alveoli to the blood can be described by:",
        "answer": "the law of diffusion",
        "choiceone": "Henry's Law",
        "choicetwo": "Boyle's Law",
        "choicethree": "Dalton's Law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The transfer of carbon dioxide from the blood to the alveoli can be described by:",
        "answer": "the law of diffusion",
        "choiceone": "Henry's Law",
        "choicetwo": "Dalton's Law",
        "choicethree": "Boyles Law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:",
        "answer": "the partial oxygen pressure is lower than at sea level.",
        "choiceone": "the composition of the blood changes",
        "choicetwo": "the composition of the air is different from sea level",
        "choicethree": "the percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Early symptoms of hypoxia could be:\n1. euphoria\n2. decreased rate and depth of breathing\n3. lack of concentration\n4. visual disturbances",
        "answer": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the functions below, which is the most sensitive to hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Night vision.",
        "choiceone": "Speech.",
        "choicetwo": "Motor coordination.",
        "choicethree": "Hearing.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During a night flight at 10,000 feet you notice that your visual acuity has decreased. In\nthis case you can increase your acuity by:",
        "answer": "breathing extra oxygen through the oxygen mask.",
        "choiceone": "closing one eye",
        "choicetwo": "dim the instrument lights",
        "choicethree": "scanning sectors of the field of vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pain in the middle ear during descent may be eased by:",
        "answer": "levelling off and possibly climbing",
        "choiceone": "using an oxygen mask",
        "choicetwo": "blocking the effected ear with the palm of your hand",
        "choicethree": "increasing the rate of descent",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness without having a decompression",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "stress",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The exchange of gases between the alveoli and the blood is due to:",
        "answer": "diffusion",
        "choiceone": "changes in atmospheric pressure",
        "choicetwo": "inspiration",
        "choicethree": "physical exercise",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxic hypoxia may be caused by:\n1. climbing to a high altitude without using additional oxygen\n2. malfunction in the oxygen supply system\n3. loss of cabin pressurization at high altitude\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "By 'long duration acceleration', we mean that it lasts more than:",
        "answer": "1 second",
        "choiceone": "5 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "20 seconds",
        "choicethree": "1 minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ozone in the air of a pressurized cabin can be eliminated by:",
        "answer": "ozone-converters",
        "choiceone": "spraying detergents",
        "choicetwo": "climbing to altitudes above 45,000 ft",
        "choicethree": "avoiding flights along the equator",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do to optimise his/her night vision (scotopic vision)?",
        "answer": "Not smoke before start and during flight and avoid flash-blindness",
        "choiceone": "Select meals with high contents of vitamin B and C",
        "choicetwo": "Wait at least 60 minutes to night-adapt before he takes off",
        "choicethree": "Avoid food containing high amounts of vitamin A",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Generally, the time required for dark adaptation is:",
        "answer": "30 min",
        "choiceone": "1/10 sec",
        "choicetwo": "10 sec",
        "choicethree": "10 min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time required for complete adaptation is",
        "answer": "for high levels of illumination 10 sec and for full dark adaptation 30 min",
        "choiceone": "for high levels of illumination 10 minutes and for low levels of illumination 30\nminutes",
        "choicetwo": "for night 10 sec and for day 30 min",
        "choicethree": "for day and night: 30 min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The requirement of good sunglasses is to",
        "answer": "absorb enough visible light to eliminate glare without decreasing visual acuity",
        "choiceone": "eliminate distortion in aircraft windshields",
        "choicetwo": "increase the time for dark adaptation",
        "choicethree": "fit to the pilots individual taste",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia will effect night vision",
        "answer": "at approximately 5000 FT",
        "choiceone": "and causes hyperventilation",
        "choicetwo": "and causes the autokinetic phenomena",
        "choicethree": "less than day vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the optical image forms in front of the retina; this results in:",
        "answer": "myopia",
        "choiceone": "presbyopia",
        "choicetwo": "astigmatism",
        "choicethree": "hypermetropia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to perceive colour vision, it is necessary:\n-1: for there to be considerable amount of light (ambient luminosity)\n-2: at night to look at the point to be observed at an angle of 15\u00b0\n-3: to allow the eye a period of time to get used to the light\n-4: to avoid white light",
        "answer": "1",
        "choiceone": "3",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3",
        "choicethree": "2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The mechanism of accommodation is caused by:",
        "answer": "the functioning of the ciliary muscle around the lens",
        "choiceone": "the elasticity of the optic nerves",
        "choicetwo": "the functioning of the muscles of the eye",
        "choicethree": "the diameter of the pupil",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time an eye needs to adapt fully to the dark is about:",
        "answer": "25 - 30 minutes",
        "choiceone": "10 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "5 minutes",
        "choicethree": "10 minutes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\na) turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\nb) looking inside the cockpit\nc) wearing sunglasses\nd) using blinds or curtains when installed",
        "answer": "a), b), c) and d) are correct",
        "choiceone": "a), b) and c) are correct, d) is false",
        "choicetwo": "a) and b) are correct, c) and d) are false",
        "choicethree": "c) and d) are correct, a) and b) are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which scanning technique should be used when flying at night?",
        "answer": "Look to the side (10 - 15 deg) of the object.",
        "choiceone": "Look with one eye.",
        "choicetwo": "Look directly at the object.",
        "choicethree": "Blink your eyes.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Night vision:",
        "answer": "requires up to 30 minutes to reach its best performance",
        "choiceone": "is insensitive to short duration light sources",
        "choicetwo": "requires 5 minutes to reach its best performance",
        "choicethree": "is insensitive to lightning flashes in storms",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What illusion may occur if an aircraft is flying into fog, snow or haze?",
        "answer": "Objects seem to be farther away than in reality",
        "choiceone": "Objects will appear closer than they really are",
        "choicetwo": "Objects will appear bigger in size than in reality",
        "choicethree": "Objects seem to move slower than in reality",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?",
        "answer": "The cochlea",
        "choiceone": "The sacculus and utriculus",
        "choicetwo": "The Eustachian tube",
        "choicethree": "The semicircular canals",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result in:",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss",
        "choicetwo": "a ruptured ear drum",
        "choicethree": "presbycusis (effects of aging)",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "By what action could the pressure gradient between the middle and the outer ear be\nbalanced?",
        "answer": "By swallowing.",
        "choiceone": "By coughing.",
        "choicetwo": "By breathing out.",
        "choicethree": "By breathing in.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The proprioceptive senses (seat-of-the-pants sense) are important for motor\ncoordination.\nThey",
        "answer": "are completely unreliable for orientation when flying in IMC",
        "choiceone": "indicate the difference between gravity and G-forces",
        "choicetwo": "allow the pilot to determine the absolute vertical at flight condition",
        "choicethree": "are important senses for flight training in IMC",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a coordinated level  turn will",
        "answer": "make the body`s pressure receptors feel an increased pressure along the body`s\nvertical axis",
        "choiceone": "make the blood being pooled in the head",
        "choicetwo": "make the seat-of-the-pants sense feel a decreased pressure along the body`s\nvertical axis",
        "choicethree": " first give the impression of climb , then the impression of descent",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When accelerating in level flight we could experience the sensation of a",
        "answer": "climb",
        "choiceone": "spin",
        "choicetwo": "descent",
        "choicethree": "turn",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During flight in IMC, the most reliable sense which should be used to overcome\nillusions is the:",
        "answer": "visual sense, interpreting the attitude indicator",
        "choiceone": "visual sense by looking outside",
        "choicetwo": "\"Seat-of-the-pants-Sense\"",
        "choicethree": "vestibular sense",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual disturbances can be caused by:\n1. hyperventilation\n2. hypoxia\n3. hypertension\n4. fatigue",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are subjected to an illusion during night flying you should:",
        "answer": "continue on instruments",
        "choiceone": "scan the surroundings",
        "choicetwo": "dim the cockpit lighting",
        "choicethree": "use your oxygen mask",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the factors which can cause illusions while taxiing are:",
        "answer": "relative movement and cockpit height above the ground.",
        "choiceone": "distance from the edge of the taxiway and cockpit lighting.",
        "choicetwo": "distance from the edge of the taxiway and taxi lighting.",
        "choicethree": "visibility and distance.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Somatogravic illusion gives the pilot a false impression of:",
        "answer": "climbing or descending.",
        "choiceone": "descending and turning to the right.",
        "choicetwo": "climbing and turning to the right.",
        "choicethree": "descending and turning to the left.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the waste products of the metabolic process in the cell is:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "fat",
        "choicetwo": "sugar",
        "choicethree": "protein",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss (NIHL) is caused by:",
        "answer": "damage to the sensitive membrane in the cochlea due to overexposure to noise",
        "choiceone": "pressure differences on both sides of the eardrum",
        "choicetwo": "a blocked Eustachian tube",
        "choicethree": "reduced mobility of the ossicles",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the symptoms of hypoglycaemia are:",
        "answer": "Headache and lack of concentration",
        "choiceone": "Double vision and puffiness around the eyes",
        "choicetwo": "Severe eye and head aches",
        "choicethree": "Difficulty in focussing on near-by objects",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cholera can be transmitted through:",
        "answer": "Food or water which has been contaminated",
        "choiceone": "Droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person",
        "choicetwo": "Bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin",
        "choicethree": "Insect bites",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The consumption of medicines or other substances may have consequences on qualification to fly for the\nfollowing reasons:\n1. The disease requiring a treatment may be cause for disqualification.\n2. Flight conditions may modify the reactions of the body to a treatment.\n3. Drugs may cause adverse side effects impairing flight safety.\n4. The effects of medicine do not necessarily immediately disappear when the treatment is stopped.",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are false, 1 and 2 are correct.",
        "choicetwo": "Only 2 is false.",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cigarette smoking has particular significance to the flyer, because there are long-term\nand short-term harmful effects. From cigarette smoking the pilot can get:",
        "answer": "a mild carbon monoxide poisoning decreasing the pilot\u00b4s tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "a suppressed desire to eat and drink",
        "choicetwo": "a mild carbon monoxide poisoning increasing the pilot\u00b4s tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "a mild carbon dioxide poisoning increasing the pilot's tolerance to hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide, a product of incomplete combustion, is toxic because",
        "answer": "it competes with oxygen in its union with haemoglobin",
        "choiceone": "it prevents the excretion of catabolites in the kidneys",
        "choicetwo": "it disturbs gaseous diffusion at the alveoli capillary membrane",
        "choicethree": "it prevents the absorption of food from the digestive tract",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The so-called Coriolis effect (a conflict in information processing in the brain) in\nspatial disorientation occurs:",
        "answer": "on stimulating several semicircular canals simultaneously",
        "choiceone": "on stimulating the cochlea intensely",
        "choicetwo": "on stimulating the saccule and the utricle of the inner ear",
        "choicethree": "when no semicircular canal is stimulated",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Incapacitation is most dangerous when it is:",
        "answer": "insidious",
        "choiceone": "intense",
        "choicetwo": "obvious",
        "choicethree": "sudden",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In-flight incapacitation of a pilot is most frequently caused by:",
        "answer": "acute gastrointestinal disorders",
        "choiceone": "cardio-vascular disorders",
        "choicetwo": "chronic pulmonary disorders",
        "choicethree": "behavioural disorders",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In an abnormal situation the pilot has an apparently correct explanation for the\nproblem. The chance that he/she now ignores or devalues other relevant information,\nnot fitting into his/her mental picture is:",
        "answer": "not usual",
        "choiceone": "not possible since correct training should have eliminated this problem",
        "choicetwo": "not applicable with old and experienced pilots",
        "choicethree": "very rare",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 'cocktail party effect' is",
        "answer": "the ability to pick up relevant information unintentionally",
        "choiceone": "the tendency to believe information that reinforces our mental model of the world",
        "choicetwo": "the tendency not to perceive relevant information",
        "choicethree": "the ability to drink too much at social gathering",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following tasks are possible to do simultaneously without mutual\ninterference?",
        "answer": "Maintain manual straight and level flight and solve a problem.",
        "choiceone": "Talk and rehearse a frequency in working memory.",
        "choicetwo": "Listen attentively and solve a problem.",
        "choicethree": "Read and listen attentively.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Our mental model of the world is based",
        "answer": "on both our past experiences and the sensory information we receive",
        "choiceone": "on both our past experiences and our motor programmes",
        "choicetwo": "entirely on the sensory information we receive",
        "choicethree": "entirely on past experiences",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The maximum number of unrelated items that can be stored in working memory is:",
        "answer": "about 7 items",
        "choiceone": "unlimited",
        "choicetwo": "about 30 items",
        "choicethree": "very limited - only 3 items",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the short-term-memory, information is stored for approximately",
        "answer": "20 seconds",
        "choiceone": "5 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "1 hour",
        "choicethree": "a couple of days",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Less experienced pilots differ from experienced pilots in the following way:",
        "answer": "inexperienced pilots refer to information more than experts when carrying out the\nsame task",
        "choiceone": "experienced pilots are less routine-minded than young pilots because they know\nthat routine causes mistakes",
        "choicetwo": "flight planning performance decreases with age, and experience is unable to mask\nthis deficiency",
        "choicethree": "task for task, an expert's workload is greater than a novice's one",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Planning:",
        "answer": "allows crew members to anticipate potential risky situations and decide on\npossible responses",
        "choiceone": "in the cockpit typically results in plans that are always easy to modify when things\nare not as anticipated",
        "choicetwo": "is unnecessary in the cockpit, as crew members are so highly trained, they will\nalways know what to do in unusual situations",
        "choicethree": "is dangerous in the cockpit, as it interrupts flight crew creativity",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why must flight safety considerations consider the human error mechanism?\n-1: It is analysis of an incident or accident which will make it possible to identify what error has\nbeen committed and by whom. It is the process whereby the perpetrator is made responsible\nwhich may lead to elimination of the error.\n-2: If we have a better understanding of the cognitive error mechanism, it will be possible to\nadapt procedures, aircraft interfaces, etc.\n-3: It is error management procedure which enables us to continuously adjust our actions. The\nbetter we understand the underlying mechanism of an error, the better will be our means for\ndetecting and reducing future errors.\n-4: Since error is essentially human, once it has been identified by the use of procedures, a\nperson will be able to anticipate and deal with it automatically in the future.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 4",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best fits the definition of an active error?\nActive error is:",
        "answer": "produced by the operator and can be rapidly detected",
        "choiceone": "produced either by a front-line operator or by a remote operator and results in a\nhidden or latent consequence at a specific moment of the action",
        "choicetwo": "rare in front-line actions and difficult to detect owing to the fact that it usually\noccurs in a complex system of uncontrolled and involuntary deviations",
        "choicethree": "essentially results from the application of a bad rule or the poor application of a\ngood rule by aeroplane designers",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the external factors that may contribute to an error, cockpit noise and the\nrestriction of the field of view due to windscreen design correspond to:",
        "answer": "ergonomic factors.",
        "choiceone": "psychobiological factors.",
        "choicetwo": "social factors.",
        "choicethree": "organisational factors.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Once a pilot has developed a certain way of thinking about a problem he will probably",
        "answer": "find it difficult to get out of that way of thinking and difficult to try a different\ninterpretation of the data",
        "choiceone": "find it difficult to stick to his/her interpretation of the data",
        "choicetwo": "find it easy to interpret the data in different ways",
        "choicethree": "find it impossible to get out of that way of thinking, whatever happens",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What strategy should be put in place when faced with an anticipated period of stress?",
        "answer": "A strategy of preparing decisions",
        "choiceone": "A strategy of no commitment",
        "choicetwo": "A Laissez-faire strategy",
        "choicethree": "A non-sequenced strategy",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making is a concept which represents:",
        "answer": "a voluntary and conscious process of selection, from among possible solutions,\nfor a given problem",
        "choiceone": "an automatic process of selection from among the various solutions to a given\nproblem",
        "choicetwo": "a spontaneous act of seeking the most effective solution in a given situation when\nfaced with a defined problem",
        "choicethree": "an automated or automation-like act of applying defined procedures",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the decision-making process, confirmation bias results in:",
        "answer": "a tendency to look for information which confirms the validity of the decision",
        "choiceone": "choosing familiar solutions, even if they are not the best ones",
        "choicetwo": "a tendency to look for approval by other crew-members, or by the ATC",
        "choicethree": "overestimating the frequency of some events",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decisions made by pilots in a cockpit:",
        "answer": "remain valid for a limited time only",
        "choiceone": "are automatic when pilots are experts",
        "choicetwo": "are always irreversible",
        "choicethree": "should always be made as quickly as possible",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner",
        "choiceone": "a synonym for behaviour",
        "choicetwo": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity",
        "choicethree": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual ?\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n4. Past experience",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements with regard to motivation is correct?",
        "answer": "Excessive motivation in combination with high levels of stress will limit attention\nmanagement capabilities",
        "choiceone": "Low motivation will guarantee adequate attention management capabilities",
        "choicetwo": "Motivation will reduce risk",
        "choicethree": "Too much motivation may result in hypovigilance and thus in a decrease in\nattention",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Signs of stress include:",
        "answer": "Perspiration, dry mouth, dilated pupils, fast breathing.",
        "choiceone": "Faster, deep inhalation, stabbing pain around the heart.",
        "choicetwo": "Rising of the blood pressure, pupils narrowing, stabbing pain around the heart.",
        "choicethree": "Lowering of the blood pressure.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Acute stress quickly leads to",
        "answer": "the mobilization of resources required to cope with the stressor",
        "choiceone": "a permanent state of incapacitation",
        "choicetwo": "a decrease in the amount of resources mobilized to face the situation",
        "choicethree": "a state of overactivation beyond the control of willpower",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Environmental sources of stress in the cockpit could be:\n1. noise and vibration\n2. acceleration\n3. radiation\n4. extreme temperatures\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to limit stress when flying, a pilot should:",
        "answer": "maintain his competence by practicing his professional skills and learning from\npast experiences",
        "choiceone": "drop activities outside work so as to focus on his work better",
        "choicetwo": "avoid anticipating events during a flight to manage his workload",
        "choicethree": "forget about bad past experiences",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What seems to be the main role of Orthodox sleep?",
        "answer": "It essentially allows for physical recovery",
        "choiceone": "It includes physical and mental recuperation associate with fatigue",
        "choicetwo": "Its main role is associated with activities of memory activities and restoration of\nattention capabilities",
        "choicethree": "Via physical recovery, it is characterised by an alternation of dream phases and\nparadoxical phases",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the case of changes to circadian rhythms, the readjustment to a new time zone:",
        "answer": "is most rapid when flying westbound",
        "choiceone": "is the same in both westbound and eastbound flights",
        "choicetwo": "is most rapid when flying eastbound",
        "choicethree": "occurs immediately, as circadian rhythms do not change depending on direction of\nflying",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal sleep cycle is approximately every ................minutes",
        "answer": "90",
        "choiceone": "180",
        "choicetwo": "60",
        "choicethree": "120",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A good ratio of activity to sleep is",
        "answer": "two hours activity to one hour of sleep",
        "choiceone": "three hours activity to one hour of sleep",
        "choicetwo": "four hours activity to one hour of sleep",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A high degree of cockpit automation may alter the traditional tasks of the pilots in a\nway, that",
        "answer": "the attention of the cockpit crew will become reduced as a consequence of 'being\nout of the loop'",
        "choiceone": "it is guaranteed that the crew always maintains situational awareness",
        "choicetwo": "the crew can pay more attention to problem-solving in an abnormal situation\nwithout monitoring the automatic systems",
        "choicethree": "Crew Coordination can be neglected on long haul flights without compromising\nsafety",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 1.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a cause of accidents, the human factor",
        "answer": "is cited in approximately 70 - 80 % of aviation accidents",
        "choiceone": "which is cited in current statistics, applies to the flight crew and ATC only",
        "choicetwo": "has increased considerably since 1980 - the percentage of accident in which this\nfactor has been involved has more than tripled since this date",
        "choicethree": "plays a negligible role in commercial aviation accidents. It is much more important\nin general aviation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With reference to the SHELL Model, S represents:",
        "answer": "Software (which includes check lists)",
        "choiceone": "Self-awareness (which includes Safety)",
        "choicetwo": "Symbology (which includes safety)",
        "choicethree": "Security (which includes Safety)",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet",
        "choicethree": "do not affect hypoxia at all",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The barometric pressure has dropped to 1/2 of the pressure at sea level at",
        "answer": "18 000 feet",
        "choiceone": "30 000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "25 000 feet",
        "choicethree": "10 000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The atmospheric pressure at 18,000 feet altitude is half the atmospheric pressure at\nsea level.\nIn accordance with this statement,",
        "answer": "the partial oxygen pressure at that altitude will also drop to 1/2 of the pressure of\noxygen at sea level",
        "choiceone": "the partial oxygen pressure at that altitude will be doubled",
        "choicetwo": "the oxygen percentage of the air at that altitude will drop by one half also",
        "choicethree": "the oxygen saturation of the blood at that altitude will drop by 50 % too",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Henry's Law explains the occurrence of:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation",
        "choicetwo": "diffusion",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Oxygen, combined with haemoglobin in blood is transported by",
        "answer": "red blood cells",
        "choiceone": "white blood cells",
        "choicetwo": "blood plasma",
        "choicethree": "platelets",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choiceone": "the total atmospheric pressure",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood",
        "choicethree": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot increase his tolerance to +Gz ?",
        "answer": "Tightening of the stomach muscles.",
        "choiceone": "Tighten shoulder harness.",
        "choicetwo": "Take an upright seat position.",
        "choicethree": "Relax the muscles and lean upper body forward.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot, climbing in a non-pressurised aircraft and without using supplemental oxygen\nwill pass the \"critical threshold\" at approximately:",
        "answer": "20 000 ft",
        "choiceone": "16 000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "18 000 ft",
        "choicethree": "38 000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) is:",
        "answer": "the length of time during which an individual can act with both mental and physical\nefficiency; measured from the moment at which he/she is exposed to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "the time before becoming unconscious at a sudden pressure loss",
        "choicetwo": "the time between the start of hypoxia and death",
        "choicethree": "the time after pressure loss until decompression sickness sets in",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time between inadequate oxygen supply and incapacitation is called TUC (Time of\nUseful Consciousness). It",
        "answer": "varies individually and depends on cabin pressure altitude",
        "choiceone": "is not dependent on physical or psychological pressure",
        "choicetwo": "is the same amount of time for every person",
        "choicethree": "varies individually and does not depend on altitude",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After a decompression to 43 000 FT the TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) will be\napproximately:",
        "answer": "5-15 seconds",
        "choiceone": "45-60 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "30-45 seconds",
        "choicethree": "60-90 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear most likely will occur",
        "answer": "when descending rapidly",
        "choiceone": "in sudden steep turns",
        "choicetwo": "during a long high altitude flight",
        "choicethree": "when climbing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The risk of a barotrauma of the middle ear is more likely to occur",
        "answer": "with colds and rapid descents",
        "choiceone": "after a decompression",
        "choicetwo": "with colds and fast climbs",
        "choicethree": "with colds and slow ascents",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equalization of pressure take place, when\naltitude is changed?",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube",
        "choiceone": "External auditory canal",
        "choicetwo": "Cochlea",
        "choicethree": "Tympanic membrane",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following laws explains bubbles of nitrogen coming out of solution in\nbody tissues due to a decrease in atmospheric pressure?",
        "answer": "Henry's law",
        "choiceone": "Boyle's law",
        "choicetwo": "Dalton's law",
        "choicethree": "Gay Lussac's law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal rate of breathing when at rest is",
        "answer": "12 to 20 cycles a minute",
        "choiceone": "25 to 30 cycles a minute",
        "choicetwo": "60 to 100 cycles a minute",
        "choicethree": "32 to 40 cycles a minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main function of the red blood cells is",
        "answer": "to transport oxygen",
        "choiceone": "to participate in the process of coagulation of the blood",
        "choicetwo": "the cellular defence of the organism",
        "choicethree": "to contribute to the immune response of the organism",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is due to an excessive rate of breathing and can produce the\nfollowing symptoms:",
        "answer": "dizziness, tingling sensation in the fingers and toes, nausea and blurred vision",
        "choiceone": "reduced heart rate and increase in visual acuity",
        "choicetwo": "a state of overconfidence and reduced heart rate",
        "choicethree": "blue finger-nails and lips",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The procedure to be followed in the event of decompression when flying above 10,000\nft must:",
        "answer": "allow for the rapid supply of oxygen in order to prevent hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "allow for a rapid descent independent from sufficient supply of oxygen in order to\nprevent disorders due to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "make it possible to prevent hyperventilation owing to the inhalation of 100 %\noxygen",
        "choicethree": "make it possible to eliminate the risk of fogging due to the sudden pressure\nchanges",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is decompression sickness?",
        "answer": "A condition resulting from the formation of nitrogen bubbles in bodily tissues and\nfluids after a cabin pressure loss at high altitude",
        "choiceone": "A disorder which is solely encountered below 18,000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "The formation of air bubbles in bodily tissues, with no consequences for people's\ncapabilities",
        "choicethree": "A frequent disorder in commercial aviation due to the pressurisation curve of\nmodern aircraft",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n-1: Scuba diving may be practiced without restriction\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The blood in the pulmonary artery is:",
        "answer": "lacking in oxygen and rich in carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "rich in oxygen and lacking in carbon dioxide",
        "choicetwo": "rich in both oxygen and carbon dioxide",
        "choicethree": "lacking in both oxygen and carbon dioxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia has:",
        "answer": "not enough functional haemoglobin",
        "choiceone": "not enough plasma",
        "choicetwo": "not enough white blood cells",
        "choicethree": "not enough platelets",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The average pulse of a healthy adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": " 60 to 80 beats/min",
        "choiceone": " 90 to 100 beats/min",
        "choicetwo": "110 to 150 beats/min",
        "choicethree": " 30 to 50 beats/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "At rest the cardiac output (the quantity of blood the heart pumps in one minute) of an\nadult is approximately:",
        "answer": "5 litres/min",
        "choiceone": "450 ml/min",
        "choicetwo": "45 litres/min",
        "choicethree": "75 litres/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal arterial blood-pressure of a healthy adult is (systolic/diastolic):",
        "answer": "120/80 mm Hg",
        "choiceone": "180/120 mm Hg",
        "choicetwo": " 80/20 mm Hg",
        "choicethree": "220/180 mm Hg",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\nThe blood-pressure which is measured during flight medical checks is the pressure",
        "answer": "in the artery of the upper arm (representing the pressure at heart level)",
        "choiceone": "in all the blood-vessels of the body (representing the pressure in the whole body)",
        "choicetwo": "in the muscles of the upper arm",
        "choicethree": "in the veins of the upper arm",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The blood-pressure depends on:\n1. the work of the heart\n2. the peripheral resistance\n3. the elasticity of the arterial walls\n4. the blood volume and viscosity",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1,3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in blood-pressure are measured by:",
        "answer": "pressoreceptors",
        "choiceone": "arteriols",
        "choicetwo": "adrenal glands",
        "choicethree": "pacemakers",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volume of air exchanged during a normal breathing cycle (tidal volume) is about:",
        "answer": "500 ml of air",
        "choiceone": " 75 ml of air",
        "choicetwo": "150 ml of air",
        "choicethree": "350 ml of air",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet",
        "choiceone": "25.000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet",
        "choicethree": "15.000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following symptoms can indicate hypoxia?\n1. Blue lips and finger nails.\n2. Euphoria.\n3. Flatulence.\n4 .Unconsciousness..",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct.",
        "choiceone": "1, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the functions below, which is the most sensitive to hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Night vision.",
        "choiceone": "Hearing.",
        "choicetwo": "Speech.",
        "choicethree": "Motor coordination.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing",
        "answer": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness without having a decompression",
        "choiceone": "hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "hyperventilation",
        "choicethree": "stress",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "1. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is not correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are both not correct",
        "choicethree": "1 is not correct, 2 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxic hypoxia may be caused by:\n1. climbing to a high altitude without using additional oxygen\n2. malfunction in the oxygen supply system\n3. loss of cabin pressurization at high altitude\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this physical\nstress?",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.",
        "choicetwo": "By increasing cardiac frequency.",
        "choicethree": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot suffers from hypothermia (e.g. after loss of cabin heating) his/her demand\nfor oxygen will be:",
        "answer": "initially increased",
        "choiceone": "raised leading to an increased tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "unaffected",
        "choicethree": "reduced giving a better tolerance to hypoxia at higher altitudes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n-1: Modern aircraft allow for 50 - 60% relative humidity in the cabin air under any conditions of flight, which is\nsatisfactory for the body\n-2: Thirst is a symptom of dehydration\n-3: Dehydration may lead to clinical manifestations such as dizziness and fatigue\n-4: Drinking excessive quantities of water must be avoided since resistance to periods of low hydration will\notherwise be lost",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Generally, the time required for dark adaptation is:",
        "answer": "30 min",
        "choiceone": "1/10 sec",
        "choicetwo": "10 sec",
        "choicethree": "10 min",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Adaptation is",
        "answer": "the adjustment of the eyes to high or low levels of illumination",
        "choiceone": "the change of the diameter of the pupil",
        "choicetwo": "the reflection of the light at the cornea",
        "choicethree": "the adjustment of the crystalline lens to focus light on the retina",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does not impair the function of the photosensitive cells?",
        "answer": "High speed",
        "choiceone": "Toxic influence (alcohol, nicotine, medication)",
        "choicetwo": "Oxygen deficiency",
        "choicethree": "Acceleration",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The part(s) of the eye responsible for night vision",
        "answer": "are the rods",
        "choiceone": "is the cornea",
        "choicetwo": "are the cones",
        "choicethree": "are rods and cones",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the optical image forms in front of the retina; this results in:",
        "answer": "myopia",
        "choiceone": "hypermetropia",
        "choicetwo": "presbyopia",
        "choicethree": "astigmatism",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information:",
        "answer": "is limited to the foveal area of the retina",
        "choiceone": "is governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20 degrees of angle",
        "choicetwo": "is limited to daytime using the rod cells",
        "choicethree": "is almost equally shared by the entire retina",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Glaucoma is due to:",
        "answer": "Increase in pressure of the liquid within the eye",
        "choiceone": "Drop in pressure of the liquid around the eye",
        "choicetwo": "Damage to the eyeball due to high altitude",
        "choicethree": "Excess light on the eyeball",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by presbycusis?",
        "answer": "Gradual loss of hearing with age.",
        "choiceone": "Gradual onset of long-sightedness with age.",
        "choicetwo": "Total loss of hearing in both ears due to disease.",
        "choicethree": "Total loss of hearing in one ear due to use of a headset in the cockpit.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent empty field myopia at higher altitudes:",
        "answer": "it is recommended that a pilot uses short sharp scans, or periodically focuses on a\ndistant object such as a wingtip or cloud edge",
        "choiceone": "it is recommended that a pilot focuses on an object known to be approximately\none metre away",
        "choicetwo": "one should book an appointment with an opthalmologist as soon as possible",
        "choicethree": "one should concentrate only on instruments",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the cruise, at night, when the workload is low, it is recommended that:",
        "answer": "the lighting in the cockpit be increased in order to prevent low vigilance",
        "choiceone": "the lighting in the cockpit be dimmed in order to prevent low vigilance",
        "choicetwo": "the lighting in the cockpit be dimmed in order to reduce visual fatigue",
        "choicethree": "only those instruments that are vital to flying the aircraft be lit in order to avoid\ndividing one's attention",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What illusion may occur if an aircraft is flying into fog, snow or haze?",
        "answer": "Objects seem to be farther away than in reality",
        "choiceone": "Objects will appear bigger in size than in reality",
        "choicetwo": "Objects will appear closer than they really are",
        "choicethree": "Objects seem to move slower than in reality",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which force(s) affect(s) the otoliths in the utriculus and sacculus?",
        "answer": "Gravity and linear acceleration",
        "choiceone": "Gravity alone",
        "choicetwo": "Angular acceleration",
        "choicethree": "Linear acceleration and angular acceleration",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following systems are involved in motion sickness ?\n-1: Hearing\n-2: The vestibular system\n-3: Vision\n-4 The proprioceptive senses \"Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense\")\n-5: The gastrointestinal system",
        "answer": "2,3,4,5",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,5",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sensory input to the \"Seat-of-the-Pants\" sense is given by",
        "answer": "subcutaneous pressure receptors and muscle activity sensors",
        "choiceone": "blood rushing into legs",
        "choicetwo": "acceleration of the stomach (nausea)",
        "choicethree": "pressure of the heart on the diaphragm",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is used to land on small and narrow runways only. Approaching a larger and\nwider runway can lead to:",
        "answer": "an early or high \"round out\"",
        "choiceone": "a steeper than normal approach dropping low",
        "choicetwo": "a flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"",
        "choicethree": "the risk to land short of the overrun",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The proprioceptive senses (\"Seat of-the-Pants-Sense\")",
        "answer": "give incorrect information, when outside visual reference is lost",
        "choiceone": "can neither be used for motor coordination in IMC and VMC",
        "choicetwo": "is a natural human instinct, always indicating the correct attitude",
        "choicethree": "can be used, if trained, to avoid spatial disorientation in IMC",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the correct action to counteract vertigo?",
        "answer": "Believe the instruments",
        "choiceone": "Rely on the information from the semicircular canals, since these will be\ntransmitting correct information",
        "choicetwo": "Concentrate on the vertical speed indicator",
        "choicethree": "Reduce rate of breathing until all symptoms disappear, then breathe again\nnormally",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You fly VFR from your home base (runway width 27 m), to an international airport\n(runway width 45 m). On reaching your destination there is a risk of performing a:",
        "answer": "high approach with overshoot",
        "choiceone": "low approach with overshoot",
        "choicetwo": "high approach with undershoot",
        "choicethree": "low approach with undershoot",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You fly VFR from your home base (runway width 45 m) to a small airfield (runway\nwidth 27 m). On reaching your destination there is a risk of performing a:",
        "answer": "low approach with undershoot",
        "choiceone": "high approach with undershoot",
        "choicetwo": "low approach with overshoot",
        "choicethree": "high approach with overshoot",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?",
        "answer": "Rely entirely on the indications of the flight instruments.",
        "choiceone": "Rely on the Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense.",
        "choicetwo": "Get adapted to low levels of illumination before flying and use off-center vision all\nthe time.",
        "choicethree": "Tilt your head to the side to get better information from the semicircular canals.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are disorientated during night flying you must:",
        "answer": "rely on your instruments",
        "choiceone": "look outside",
        "choicetwo": "check your rate of breathing - do not breathe too fast",
        "choicethree": "descend",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Autokinesis can give the pilot the impression that:",
        "answer": "a star is another aircraft",
        "choiceone": "the aircraft is climbing",
        "choicetwo": "lights are further away than in fact they are.",
        "choicethree": "lights from ships are stars",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following mechanisms regulate body temperature when exposed to extreme\nhigh environmental temperatures?\n-1: Shivering\n-2: Vaso-constriction of peripheral blood vessels\n-3: Sweating\n-4: Vaso-dilation of peripheral blood vessels",
        "answer": "3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1",
        "choicethree": "2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the waste products of the metabolic process in the cell is:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "fat",
        "choicetwo": "protein",
        "choicethree": "sugar",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss (NIHL) is caused by:",
        "answer": "damage to the sensitive membrane in the cochlea due to overexposure to noise",
        "choiceone": "a blocked Eustachian tube",
        "choicetwo": "reduced mobility of the ossicles",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences on both sides of the eardrum",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n1. not eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. always peel fruit\n3. only eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "2 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hepatitis 'A' is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "food or water which has been contaminated.",
        "choiceone": "bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin.",
        "choicetwo": "insect bites.",
        "choicethree": "droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is corrected with",
        "answer": "plus lenses",
        "choiceone": "minus lenses",
        "choicetwo": "pin cushion shaped lenses",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, even when taken in minor quantities",
        "answer": "can make the brain cells to be more susceptible to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "will have no effect at all",
        "choicetwo": "will stimulate the brain, making the pilot resistant to hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "may improve the mental functions, so that the symptoms of hypoxia are much\nbetter to be identified",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The metabolisation of alcohol",
        "answer": "is a question of time",
        "choiceone": "is accelerated by consuming alcohol with a meal",
        "choicetwo": "can be influenced by easily obtained medication",
        "choicethree": "can be accelerated even more by coffee",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Excessive intake of aspirin can cause:",
        "answer": "Gastric bleeding",
        "choiceone": "Fits",
        "choicetwo": "Memory impairment",
        "choicethree": "Sensory loss",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following tasks are possible to do simultaneously without mutual\ninterference?",
        "answer": "Maintain manual straight and level flight and solve a problem.",
        "choiceone": "Talk and rehearse a frequency in working memory.",
        "choicetwo": "Read and listen attentively.",
        "choicethree": "Listen attentively and solve a problem.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The available cognitive resources of the human brain:",
        "answer": "are limited and make it impossible to perform two attentional tasks at the same\ntime",
        "choiceone": "allow for twin-tasks operation without any loss of effectiveness",
        "choicetwo": "are virtually unlimited",
        "choicethree": "are limited but make it possible to easily perform several tasks at the same time",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is \"divided attention\"?",
        "answer": "The management of several matters of interest dealt with individually one after the\nother",
        "choiceone": "Difficulty of concentrating on a particular objective",
        "choicetwo": "Ease of concentrating on a particular objective",
        "choicethree": "The adverse effect of motivation which leads to one's attention being dispersed",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The acquisition of a motor programme (skill) will mean that:",
        "answer": "the more behaviour is automated, the less it requires conscious attention and thus\nthe more it frees mental resources",
        "choiceone": "the less behaviour is automated, the less it requires attention and the more it frees\nresources",
        "choicetwo": "the more behaviour is automated, the more it requires attention and the more it\nfrees resources",
        "choicethree": "the more behaviour is automated, the more it requires attention and the less it\nfrees resources",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot experiences difficulties in the control of his aircraft and consequently omits to\nmonitor the fuel level. This is caused by:",
        "answer": "a lack of attention due to distraction",
        "choiceone": "both a lack of attention and a lack of alertness",
        "choicetwo": "This pilot manages his attention well.",
        "choicethree": "a lack of alertness",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motivation is an important attribute which contributes to flight safety. Which of the\nfollowing statements is correct with regards to motivation?",
        "answer": "Excessive motivation leads to stress which adversely affects performance",
        "choiceone": "A high degree of motivation lowers the level of vigilance",
        "choicetwo": "Motivation reduces the intensity of sensory illusions",
        "choicethree": "A high degree of motivation makes it possible to make up for insufficient\nknowledge in complete safety",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whilst flying a coordinated turn, most of your activity is",
        "answer": "skill based behaviour",
        "choiceone": "knowledge based behaviour",
        "choicetwo": "coping behaviour",
        "choicethree": "rule based behaviour",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The level of automation helps to conserve resources. On the other hand, it may result\nin:",
        "answer": "routine errors (slips)",
        "choiceone": "decision-making errors",
        "choicetwo": "errors in selecting an appropriate plan of action",
        "choicethree": "mistakes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In problem-solving, what determines the transition from rule-based activities to a\nknowledge-based activity?",
        "answer": "The unsuitability of the known rules for the problem posed",
        "choiceone": "The unsuitability of the automated actions",
        "choicetwo": "Attentional capture",
        "choicethree": "Knowledge of rules which apply to the problem posed",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot\u00b4s attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience",
        "choiceone": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres",
        "choicethree": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In terms of decision-making, the intention to become integrated into the team, to be\nrecognised as the leader or to avoid conflicts may lead to:",
        "answer": "the attempt to agree on decisions made by other crew members",
        "choiceone": "a fast and decisive option",
        "choicetwo": "an authoritarian approach thus demonstrating ones own ability to lead",
        "choicethree": "the improvement of internal risk assessment capabilities",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The relevance of check procedures during flight becomes even more important when:",
        "answer": "flying an unfamiliar type of aircraft and experiencing mental pressure",
        "choiceone": "flying an aircraft which you have flown recently",
        "choicetwo": "conducting a longer flight than you would normally perform",
        "choicethree": "flying an aircraft which you have flown many times before",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following course of action should be taken if gastrointestinal complaints in flight crew occur before to\ntake-off:\n-1: take the standard medicines and advise the doctor on returning from the flight\n-2: assess your own ability to fly, if necessary with the help of a doctor\n-3: if in doubt about fitness to fly - do not fly!\n-4: reduce the cabin temperature, and drink before you are thirsty so as to avoid dehydration",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "1,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having made an important decision, a Commander of an aircraft should:",
        "answer": "Always try to make time to explain the reasons for the decision even if it is after\nlanding",
        "choiceone": "Explain the reasons for the decision only if time permits in the air",
        "choicetwo": "Explain the reasons for the decision only if asked",
        "choicethree": "As the leader of the crew, never need explain the reasons behind the decision",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What optimises crew co-operation ?\n1. Sharing and common task\n2. Confidence in each others capability\n3. Precise definition of functions associated with each crew members role",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "1",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "1,2",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cohesion is a major advantage in times of:",
        "answer": "Difficulty",
        "choiceone": "Achievement",
        "choicetwo": "Success",
        "choicethree": "Personal advancement",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following answers is correct?",
        "answer": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is adaptable.",
        "choiceone": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is adaptable.",
        "choicetwo": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is not adaptable.",
        "choicethree": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is not adaptable.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress",
        "choicetwo": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking\nforward to what may happen",
        "choicethree": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is a stressor?",
        "answer": "An external or internal stimulus which is interpreted by an individual as being\nstressful",
        "choiceone": "All external stimuli are stressors since they modify the internal equilibrium",
        "choicetwo": "A psychological problem developed in a situation of danger",
        "choicethree": "The adaptation response of the individual to his environment",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the effects of excesive stress?",
        "answer": "It increases vigilance for a longer period than stress itself, but may focus attention\ninappropriately",
        "choiceone": "It has very little immediate effect on vigilance and attention",
        "choicetwo": "It reduces vigilance and focuses attention",
        "choicethree": "It activates resources stored in memory",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress is:",
        "answer": "a mechanism by which an individual can respond to situations which he/she may\nhave to face",
        "choiceone": "a response by man to his problems, which automatically leads to a reduction in his\nperformance",
        "choicetwo": "a psychosomatic disease that one can learn to control",
        "choicethree": "a phenomenon which is specific to modern man",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to limit stress when flying, a pilot should:",
        "answer": "maintain his competence by practicing his professional skills and learning from\npast experiences",
        "choiceone": "avoid anticipating events during a flight to manage his workload",
        "choicetwo": "forget about bad past experiences",
        "choicethree": "drop activities outside work so as to focus on his work better",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An accumulation of stress inducing factors",
        "answer": "will produce a higher stress level",
        "choiceone": "will not produce a higher stress level",
        "choicetwo": "may produce a higher stress level",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The two types of fatigue are:",
        "answer": "Chronic short-term and acute",
        "choiceone": "Short-term and oppressive",
        "choicetwo": "Heavy and light",
        "choicethree": "Oppressive and negative",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sleeplessness or the disruption of sleeping patterns\n1. can lead to symptoms of drowsiness, irritability and lack of concentration\n2. will make an individual more prone to make errors",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is not correct, 2 is correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct, 2 is not correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both not correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal sleep cycle is approximately every ................minutes",
        "answer": "90",
        "choiceone": "60",
        "choicetwo": "180",
        "choicethree": "120",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following operations are performed more effectively by automatic systems than by people ?\n1. Waiting for an infrequent phenomenon\n2. Long term controlling of a set value (e.g holding of trajectory)\n3. Monitoring to ensure that certain values are not exceeded (e.g. holding of flight path)\n4. Qualitative decision-making",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN 5.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot becomes skilled when he/she:\n-1: trains or practises regularly\n-2: knows how to manage himself/herself\n-3: possesses all the knowledge associated with his aircraft\n-4: knows how to keep resources in reserve for coping with the unexpected",
        "answer": "1,2,4",
        "choiceone": "2, 3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to withstand g forces is reduced by a number of factors, among these\nfactors are:",
        "answer": "Low blood sugar, obesity and hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "Hypoxia, fatigue and vibrations",
        "choicetwo": "Smoking, obesity and vibrations",
        "choicethree": "Physical fitness, heat and hypotension",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Between which components, with reference to the SHELL Concept, covers pilot\nmisinterpretation of the old three-point altimeter?",
        "answer": "Liveware - Hardware",
        "choiceone": "Liveware - Software",
        "choicetwo": "Liveware - Liveware",
        "choicethree": "Liveware - Environment",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dry air is a mixture of gases. Their volume percentage is about:",
        "answer": "21% oxygen,78% nitrogen, 1% other gases",
        "choiceone": "19% oxygen, 80% nitrogen, 1% other gases",
        "choicetwo": "25% oxygen, 74% nitrogen, 1% other gases",
        "choicethree": "18% oxygen, 80% nitrogen, 2% other gases",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following applies to carbon monoxide poisoning?",
        "answer": "Several days are needed to recuperate from a carbon monoxide poisoning.",
        "choiceone": "A very early symptom of carbon monoxide poisoning is euphoria.",
        "choicetwo": "The human body shows no sign of carbon monoxide poisoning.",
        "choicethree": "Inhaling carbon monoxide leads to hyperventilation.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct ?",
        "answer": "Oxygen diffusion from the blood into the cells depends on the partial oxygen\npressure gradient.",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen diffusion from the lungs into the blood does not depend on partial oxygen\npressure.",
        "choicetwo": "The gradient of diffusion is higher at altitude than it is at sea-level.",
        "choicethree": "Oxygen is mainly transported in plasma.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by",
        "answer": "a lack of red blood cells in the blood or decreased ability of the haemoglobin to\ntransport oxygen",
        "choiceone": "a lack of nitrogen in ambient air",
        "choicetwo": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases",
        "choicethree": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Breathing 100% will elevate the pilot's physiological safe altitude to approximately:",
        "answer": "40 000 ft",
        "choiceone": "22 000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "10 000",
        "choicethree": "45 000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time between inadequate oxygen supply and incapacitation is called TUC (Time of\nUseful Consciousness). It",
        "answer": "varies individually and depends on cabin pressure altitude",
        "choiceone": "varies individually and does not depend on altitude",
        "choicetwo": "is not dependent on physical or psychological pressure",
        "choicethree": "is the same amount of time for every person",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You suffered a rapid decompression without the appearance of any decompression\nsickness symptoms.\nWhat should you do before flying ?",
        "answer": "seek prompt aeromedical advice",
        "choiceone": "seek aeromedical advice only if the symptoms become apparent",
        "choicetwo": "nothing, you may fly immediately",
        "choicethree": "delay your next flight for 6 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The function of the Eustachian tube is to equalise the pressure between the:",
        "answer": "middle ear and the external atmosphere",
        "choiceone": "nose, throat and the external atmosphere",
        "choicetwo": "sinuses",
        "choicethree": "sinuses of the nose and the external atmosphere",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear",
        "answer": "is more likely, when the pilot is flying with a respiratory infection and during\ndescent",
        "choiceone": "is only caused by large pressure changes during climb",
        "choicetwo": "causes severe pain in the sinuses",
        "choicethree": "is to be expected during rapid decompressions, but an emergency descent\nimmediately following the decompression will eliminate the problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear most likely will occur",
        "answer": "when descending rapidly",
        "choiceone": "in sudden steep turns",
        "choicetwo": "during a long high altitude flight",
        "choicethree": "when climbing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following laws explains bubbles of nitrogen coming out of solution in\nbody tissues due to a decrease in atmospheric pressure?",
        "answer": "Henry's law",
        "choiceone": "Dalton's law",
        "choicetwo": "Boyle's law",
        "choicethree": "Gay Lussac's law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Altitude-hypoxia, when breathing ambient air, should not usually occur (indifferent\nphase)",
        "answer": "below 3 000 m",
        "choiceone": "up to 5 000 m",
        "choicetwo": "between 3 000 m and 5 000 m",
        "choicethree": "between 5 000 m and 7 000 m",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "\"The Bends\" as a symptom of decompression sickness consists of:",
        "answer": "pain in the joints",
        "choiceone": "pain in the thorax and a cough",
        "choicetwo": "loss of peripheral vision",
        "choicethree": "CNS-disturbances",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The cabin pressure in airline operation is",
        "answer": "normally between 6 000 to 8 000 feet",
        "choiceone": "normally between 2 000 to 3 000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "always equivalent to sea level",
        "choicethree": "normally between 4 000 to 5 000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is hypoxia ?",
        "answer": "Any condition where the oxygen concentration of the body is below normal limits\nor where the oxygen available to the body cannot be used due to some\npathological condition",
        "choiceone": "A state characterised by an excessive supply of oxygen which may be due to\nmaladjustment of the mask",
        "choicetwo": "The respiratory symptom associated with altitude decompression sickness",
        "choicethree": "The total absence of oxygen in the blood of the body",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the procedure above 10.000 ft altitude when faced with explosive\ndecompression?",
        "answer": "Don an oxygen mask and descend to below 10,000 ft",
        "choiceone": "Descend to below 10,000 ft and signal an emergency",
        "choicetwo": "Check the cabin altitude, don an oxygen mask and maintain level flight",
        "choicethree": "First inform ATC",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You climb from 0 to 50.000 ft and measure the decrease of the pressure per 5.000 ft.\nThe absolute difference in barometric pressure is greatest between:",
        "answer": "0 and 5.000 feet",
        "choiceone": "10.000 and 15.000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "45.000 and 50.000 feet",
        "choicethree": "5.000 and 10.000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Physiological problems due to increasing altitude are caused by:",
        "answer": "decreased atmospheric pressure",
        "choiceone": "disorientation",
        "choicetwo": "accelerations",
        "choicethree": "increased atmospheric pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\nThe blood-pressure which is measured during flight medical checks is the pressure",
        "answer": "in the artery of the upper arm (representing the pressure at heart level)",
        "choiceone": "in all the blood-vessels of the body (representing the pressure in the whole body)",
        "choicetwo": "in the veins of the upper arm",
        "choicethree": "in the muscles of the upper arm",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in blood-pressure are measured by:",
        "answer": "pressoreceptors",
        "choiceone": "adrenal glands",
        "choicetwo": "pacemakers",
        "choicethree": "arteriols",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive g will cause the blood-pressure in the brain to:",
        "answer": "decrease",
        "choiceone": "first increase, then decrease",
        "choicetwo": "increase",
        "choicethree": "remain constant",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During sustained positive G-forces the order of symptoms you can expect is:",
        "answer": "grey-out, tunnel vision, black-out and unconsciousness.",
        "choiceone": "grey-out, unconsciousness, black-out and tunnel vision",
        "choicetwo": "black-out, grey-out, tunnel vision and unconsciousness.",
        "choicethree": "unconsciousness, black-out, tunnel vision and grey out.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal rate of breathing of an adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": "16 cycles per minute",
        "choiceone": "4 cycles per minute",
        "choicetwo": "72 cycles per minute",
        "choicethree": "32 cycles per minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Early symptoms of hypoxia could be:\n1. euphoria\n2. decreased rate and depth of breathing\n3. lack of concentration\n4. visual disturbances",
        "answer": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the most dangerous symptoms of hypoxia concerning flight safety is:",
        "answer": "impaired judgement",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation, causing emotional stress",
        "choicetwo": "cyanosis, reducing then pilots ability to hear",
        "choicethree": "reduced coordination of limb movements, causing the pilot to spin",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You are crossing the Alps in a non-pressurised aircraft at an altitude of 15.000 feet.\nYou do not use the oxygen mask because you feel fine. This is unsafe, because:",
        "answer": "your judgement could be impaired",
        "choiceone": "you will get the bends",
        "choicetwo": "the blood-pressure can get too high",
        "choicethree": "the blood-pressure can get too low",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which measure(s) will help to compensate for hypoxia?\n1. Descend below 10 000 FT.\n2. Breathe 100 % oxygen.\n3. Climb to or above 10 000 FT.\n4. Reduce physical activities.",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false",
        "choicethree": "only 1 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:",
        "answer": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft",
        "choiceone": "relying on the body's built in warning system recognizing any stage of hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "not exceeding a cabin pressure altitude of 20000 ft",
        "choicethree": "swallowing, yawing and applying the Valsalva method",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some hours after a rapid decompression at FL 300 you experience pain in the joints.\nWhich of following answers is correct?",
        "answer": "You should ask for medical advice (flight surgeon) since this is a symptom of\ndecompression sickness.",
        "choiceone": "This phenomenon is treated by breathing 100% nitrogen.",
        "choicetwo": "This symptom indicates decompression sickness and will disappear when you\ntake some exercise.",
        "choicethree": "This phenomenon is treated by physiotherapy.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide poisoning can be treated by:",
        "answer": "increasing the amount of oxygen being physically dissolved in the blood",
        "choiceone": "increasing the amount of nitrogen being physically dissolved in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "breathing into a paper bag",
        "choicethree": "decreasing the amount of oxygen being combined with the hemoglobin in the\nblood",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this physical\nstress?",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Haemoglobin has an affinity for carbon monoxide of ...............times over oxygen",
        "answer": "210 - 250",
        "choiceone": "500 - 1,000",
        "choicetwo": "5 - 10",
        "choicethree": "50 - 75",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The system which controls breathing, digestion, heart rate, etc., over which there is no\nvoluntary control, is:",
        "answer": "the autonomic nervous system",
        "choiceone": "the critical nervous system",
        "choicetwo": "the local nervous system",
        "choicethree": "non-existent, as all these functions are under conscious control",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference to instruments\nbecause:",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast",
        "choiceone": "the danger of a \"greying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain",
        "choicetwo": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia will effect night vision",
        "answer": "at approximately 5000 FT",
        "choiceone": "less than day vision",
        "choicetwo": "and causes the autokinetic phenomena",
        "choicethree": "and causes hyperventilation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying at night the first sense to be affected by a slight degree of hypoxia is the",
        "answer": "vision",
        "choiceone": "sense of balance",
        "choicetwo": "proprioceptive sensitivity",
        "choicethree": "cochlea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct ?\n- 1: The retina has rods in its peripheral zone and cones in its central zone\n- 2: The retina has cones and the crystalline lens has rods\n- 3: The rods allow for night-vision\n- 4: The cones are located on the peripheral zone of the retina",
        "answer": "1,3",
        "choiceone": "4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "1",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rods (scotopic visual cells) allow for:",
        "answer": "good night-vision after adaptation to darkness (30 min)",
        "choiceone": "red vision, both during the day and at night",
        "choicetwo": "precise vision of contours and colours",
        "choicethree": "good, virtually instantaneous night-vision (scotopic vision)",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information:",
        "answer": "is limited to the foveal area of the retina",
        "choiceone": "is limited to daytime using the rod cells",
        "choicetwo": "is almost equally shared by the entire retina",
        "choicethree": "is governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20 degrees of angle",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the lens to change its shape is called:",
        "answer": "accommodation",
        "choiceone": "depth perception",
        "choicetwo": "binocular vision",
        "choicethree": "adaptation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The photosensitive cells being responsible for night vision are called:",
        "answer": "the rods",
        "choiceone": "the cones",
        "choicetwo": "the cones and the rods",
        "choicethree": "the fovea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\na) turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\nb) looking inside the cockpit\nc) wearing sunglasses\nd) using blinds or curtains when installed",
        "answer": "a), b), c) and d) are correct",
        "choiceone": "c) and d) are correct, a) and b) are false",
        "choicetwo": "a) and b) are correct, c) and d) are false",
        "choicethree": "a), b) and c) are correct, d) is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which scanning technique should be used when flying at night?",
        "answer": "Look to the side (10 - 15 deg) of the object.",
        "choiceone": "Look directly at the object.",
        "choicetwo": "Look with one eye.",
        "choicethree": "Blink your eyes.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Night vision is significantly reduced (i.e. a loss of more than 25%) at 15,000 FT in\nwhich stage of hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Compensatory",
        "choiceone": "Indifferent",
        "choicetwo": "Anaemic phase",
        "choicethree": "Clinical manifestation phase",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent empty field myopia at higher altitudes:",
        "answer": "it is recommended that a pilot uses short sharp scans, or periodically focuses on a\ndistant object such as a wingtip or cloud edge",
        "choiceone": "one should concentrate only on instruments",
        "choicetwo": "it is recommended that a pilot focuses on an object known to be approximately\none metre away",
        "choicethree": "one should book an appointment with an opthalmologist as soon as possible",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?",
        "answer": "The cochlea",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals",
        "choicetwo": "The Eustachian tube",
        "choicethree": "The sacculus and utriculus",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The intensity of a sound is measured in",
        "answer": "decibels",
        "choiceone": "cycles per second",
        "choicetwo": "hertz",
        "choicethree": "curies",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Excessive exposure to noise damages:",
        "answer": "the sensitive membrane in the cochlea",
        "choiceone": "the semi circular canals",
        "choicetwo": "the ossicles",
        "choicethree": "the eardrum",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tinnitus is",
        "answer": "ringing in the ears",
        "choiceone": "very sensitive hearing",
        "choicetwo": "very insensitive hearing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Resonance of the body parts can result from:",
        "answer": "vibrations from 1 to 100 Hz",
        "choiceone": "vibrations from 16 Hz to 18 kHz",
        "choicetwo": "angular velocity",
        "choicethree": "acceleration along the longitudinal body axis",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The semicircular canals of the inner ear monitor",
        "answer": "angular accelerations",
        "choiceone": "relative speed and linear accelerations",
        "choicetwo": "gravity",
        "choicethree": "movements with constant speeds",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The vestibular apparatus",
        "answer": "reacts to linear/angular acceleration and gravity",
        "choiceone": "gives the impression of hearing",
        "choicetwo": "reacts to pressure changes in the middle ear",
        "choicethree": "reacts to vibrations of the cochlea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Seat-of-the-Pants Sense involves receptors in the",
        "answer": "muscles, tendons and joints sensitive to the position and movement of body parts",
        "choiceone": "semicircular canals",
        "choicetwo": "utriculus and sacculus",
        "choicethree": "skin only",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dizziness and tumbling sensations, when making head movements in a tight turn, are\nsymptoms of",
        "answer": "\"Pilot`s vertigo\"",
        "choiceone": "\"Nystagmus\"",
        "choicetwo": "\"Oculogravic illusion\"",
        "choicethree": "\"Flicker-vertigo\"",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disorientation is more likely to occur when the pilot is:\n1. flying in IMC\n2. frequently changing between inside and outside references\n3. flying from IMC into VMC\n4. approaching over still water at night",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Coriolis illusion, causing spatial disorientation is the result of:",
        "answer": "simultaneous head movements during aircraft manoeuvres",
        "choiceone": "gazing in the direction of a flashing light",
        "choicetwo": "normal deterioration of the semicircular canals with age",
        "choicethree": "undergoing positive G",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?",
        "answer": "Rely entirely on the indications of the flight instruments.",
        "choiceone": "Tilt your head to the side to get better information from the semicircular canals.",
        "choicetwo": "Get adapted to low levels of illumination before flying and use off-center vision all\nthe time.",
        "choicethree": "Rely on the Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot prevent spatial disorientation in flight?",
        "answer": "Establish and maintain a good instrument cross check.",
        "choiceone": "Rely on the \"seat of the pants\" sense.",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on good situational awareness believing your natural senses.",
        "choicethree": "Always try to catch outside visual cues.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy",
        "choiceone": "mental disorders, and even coma",
        "choicetwo": "profuse sweating",
        "choicethree": "the appearance of intense shivering",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n1  Hypothermia affects physical and mental abilities.\n2  Man has effective natural protection against intense cold.\n3  Shivering makes it possible to combat the cold to a certain extent, but uses up a lot of energy\n4  Disorders associated with hypothermia appear at a body temperature of less than 35\u00b0C",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by metabolism?",
        "answer": "The generation and utilisation of energy by the body's cells and tissues",
        "choiceone": "Transfer of chemical messages",
        "choicetwo": "Exchange of substances between the lung and the blood",
        "choicethree": "Information exchange",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the waste products of the metabolic process in the cell is:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "fat",
        "choicetwo": "protein",
        "choicethree": "sugar",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to reduce the risk of coronary artery disease, exercise should:",
        "answer": "double the resting heart rate for at least 20 minutes, three times a week",
        "choiceone": "be avoided since raising the heart rate shortens the life of the heart",
        "choicetwo": "double the resting heart rate for at least an hour, five times a week",
        "choicethree": "triple the resting heart rate for 20 minutes, once a week",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Astigmatism is caused by:",
        "answer": "A mis-shapened cornea",
        "choiceone": "A lack of empty field",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation",
        "choicethree": "A lack of vitamin A",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the symptoms of hypoglycaemia are:",
        "answer": "Headache and lack of concentration",
        "choiceone": "Severe eye and head aches",
        "choicetwo": "Difficulty in focussing on near-by objects",
        "choicethree": "Double vision and puffiness around the eyes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tetanus is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "Bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin",
        "choiceone": "Food or water which has been contaminated",
        "choicetwo": "Insect bites",
        "choicethree": "Droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hepatitis 'A' is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "food or water which has been contaminated.",
        "choiceone": "bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin.",
        "choicetwo": "droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person.",
        "choicethree": "insect bites.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is corrected with",
        "answer": "plus lenses",
        "choiceone": "minus lenses",
        "choicetwo": "pin cushion shaped lenses",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may",
        "answer": "intensify the effects of the drugs",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs",
        "choicetwo": "increase the rate of alcohol elimination from the blood",
        "choicethree": "show undesired effects only during night flights",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the substances present in the smoke of cigarettes can make it significantly\nmore difficult for the red blood cells to transport oxygen and as a consequence\ncontributes to hypoxia. Which substance are we referring to?",
        "answer": "Carbon monoxide",
        "choiceone": "Carbonic anhydride",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide",
        "choicethree": "Tar",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Caffeine may cause an increase in cardiac rate, restlessness/nervousness, insomnia,\nanxiety and intestinal irritability. Excessive consumption is considered to be in excess\nof:",
        "answer": "250 mg/day",
        "choiceone": "40-65 mg/day",
        "choicetwo": "150 mg/day",
        "choicethree": "3 mg/day",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the two types of attention ?",
        "answer": "Selective and divided",
        "choiceone": "Divided and behavioural",
        "choicetwo": "Intuitive and behavioural",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first stage in the information process is",
        "answer": "sensory stimulation",
        "choiceone": "the recognition of information",
        "choicetwo": "perception",
        "choicethree": "selective attention",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The quality of learning:",
        "answer": "is promoted by feedback on the value of one's own performance",
        "choiceone": "is independent of the level of motivation",
        "choicetwo": "depends on long-term memory capacity",
        "choicethree": "is dependent on age and professional role",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What strategies can be used to combat human error?\n-1: Reducing error-prone mechanisms.\n-2: Improving the way in which error is taken into account in training.\n-3: Sanctions against the initiators of error.\n-4: Improving recovery from errors and its consequences.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Once we have constructed a mental model we tend",
        "answer": "to give undue weight to information that confirms the model",
        "choiceone": "to alter that model unnecessarily frequently",
        "choicetwo": "to give undue weight to information that contradicts the model",
        "choicethree": "to give equal weight to contradicting and confirming information",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements fits best the concept of latent error?\nLatent errors:",
        "answer": "have been present in the system for a certain length of time and are difficult to\nidentify as a result of the time lag between the generation and the occurrence of\nthe error",
        "choiceone": "rapidly may be detected via their immediate consequences on the action in\nprogress",
        "choicetwo": "are rarely made by front-line operators, and are consequently readily identified and\ndetected by the monitoring, detection and warning links",
        "choicethree": "are mainly associated with the behaviour of front-line operators and are only\ndetected after advanced problem-solving",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The level of automation helps to conserve resources. On the other hand, it may result\nin:",
        "answer": "routine errors (slips)",
        "choiceone": "mistakes",
        "choicetwo": "decision-making errors",
        "choicethree": "errors in selecting an appropriate plan of action",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In problem-solving, what determines the transition from rule-based activities to a\nknowledge-based activity?",
        "answer": "The unsuitability of the known rules for the problem posed",
        "choiceone": "Knowledge of rules which apply to the problem posed",
        "choicetwo": "Attentional capture",
        "choicethree": "The unsuitability of the automated actions",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If one error is allowed to effect a whole system, the system is described as:",
        "answer": "Vulnerable",
        "choiceone": "Error-prone",
        "choicetwo": "Corrupted",
        "choicethree": "Error tolerant",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To avoid wrong decisions by the pilot, an aircraft system should at the minimum to",
        "answer": "report its malfunction",
        "choiceone": "correct the deviation",
        "choicetwo": "report the deviation",
        "choicethree": "tolerate the deviation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The assessment of risk in a particular situation will be based on",
        "answer": "subjective perception and evaluation of situational factors",
        "choiceone": "situational factors only",
        "choicetwo": "the emergency checklist only",
        "choicethree": "external factors only",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making can be influenced by the following factors:\n1. people tend to conform to opinions expressed by a majority within the group they belong to\n2. people always keep the future decisions in line with those their superiors have made in the past\n3. people more easily tend to select data which meet their expectations\n4. people rarely base decisions on their personal preferences but rather on rational information\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making is a concept which represents:",
        "answer": "a voluntary and conscious process of selection, from among possible solutions,\nfor a given problem",
        "choiceone": "an automatic process of selection from among the various solutions to a given\nproblem",
        "choicetwo": "an automated or automation-like act of applying defined procedures",
        "choicethree": "a spontaneous act of seeking the most effective solution in a given situation when\nfaced with a defined problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following course of action should be taken if gastrointestinal complaints in flight crew occur before to\ntake-off:\n-1: take the standard medicines and advise the doctor on returning from the flight\n-2: assess your own ability to fly, if necessary with the help of a doctor\n-3: if in doubt about fitness to fly - do not fly!\n-4: reduce the cabin temperature, and drink before you are thirsty so as to avoid dehydration",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Waiting for takeoff on the runway, a pilot is informed by the tower that the tail wind\ncomponent is 12 kt. According to the manual, the limitation is 10 kt max.\nThe pilot makes a decision to take-off anyway, as the runway is long.",
        "answer": "This is a violation.",
        "choiceone": "This is neither an error or a violation - the pilot is using his initiative.",
        "choicetwo": "This is a decision error.",
        "choicethree": "This is an error of reasoning.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What optimises crew co-operation ?\n1. Sharing and common task\n2. Confidence in each others capability\n3. Precise definition of functions associated with each crew members role",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "1",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner",
        "choiceone": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting",
        "choicetwo": "a synonym for behaviour",
        "choicethree": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following answers is correct?",
        "answer": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is adaptable.",
        "choiceone": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is not adaptable.",
        "choicetwo": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is adaptable.",
        "choicethree": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is not adaptable.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regards to stress, as it affects human beings, which of the folowing statements is\ncorrect?",
        "answer": "\u00b4Stress\u00b4is a term used to describe how a person reacts to demands placed upon\nhim/her.",
        "choiceone": "All forms of stress should be avoided.",
        "choicetwo": "Stressors relate purely to a pilot\u00b4s physical condition.",
        "choicethree": "Self imposed obligations will not create stress.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Physiological stressors include:",
        "answer": "Noise, temperature (low or high), humidity, sleep deprivation",
        "choiceone": "Heat, humidity, fatigue, administrative problems",
        "choicetwo": "Temperature, hunger, thirst, divorce",
        "choicethree": "Noise, hunger, conflicts, a death",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning stress are true ?\n1. Adaptation is a new state of equilibrium after having coped with a stressful situation.\n2. An individual's anticipation of the situation and his/her perceived abilities to cope with it will\ndetermine the type and strength of stress.",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both true",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, 2 is true",
        "choicethree": "1 is true, 2 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress in the acute form acts over",
        "answer": "the short term",
        "choiceone": "the long term",
        "choicetwo": "long or short term",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress in the chronic form acts over",
        "answer": "the long term",
        "choiceone": "the short term",
        "choicetwo": "long or short term",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most important of the diurnal body rhythms is",
        "answer": "internal body temperature",
        "choiceone": "body temperature and blood pressure",
        "choicetwo": "blood pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mode Error is associated with:",
        "answer": "Automation",
        "choiceone": "Vertigo",
        "choicetwo": "Hardware",
        "choicethree": "Check lists",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot avoid automation complacency?",
        "answer": "Regard the automatic system as additional crew members that needs to be\ncrosschecked as well",
        "choiceone": "Always try to enhance your aviation related knowledge during low workload\nperiods",
        "choicetwo": "Nothing, because it is system-inherent",
        "choicethree": "Always fly the whole flight manually to remain in man-machine loop",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMAN.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can vertigo be prevented in conditions of good visibility?",
        "answer": "By closing the eyes momentarily",
        "choiceone": "By looking approximately 5\u00b0 to one side of an object",
        "choicetwo": "By looking at the horizon",
        "choicethree": "By avoiding blinking",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who in the Aviation Industry is responsible for flight safety ?",
        "answer": "Everyone involved",
        "choiceone": "Aircrew",
        "choicetwo": "Aircrew and GroundCrew",
        "choicethree": "Management, Aircrew, Groundcrew and ATC",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a cause of accidents, the human factor",
        "answer": "is cited in approximately 70 - 80 % of aviation accidents",
        "choiceone": "plays a negligible role in commercial aviation accidents. It is much more important\nin general aviation",
        "choicetwo": "has increased considerably since 1980 - the percentage of accident in which this\nfactor has been involved has more than tripled since this date",
        "choicethree": "which is cited in current statistics, applies to the flight crew and ATC only",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Thinking on human reliability is changing.",
        "answer": "Human errors are now considered as being inevitable",
        "choiceone": "It is thought that it will be possible to eliminate errors in the near future",
        "choicetwo": "The individual view of safety has gradually replaced the systemic view of safety",
        "choicethree": "Human errors can be avoided. All it takes is to be vigilant and to extend one's\nknowledge",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1972, a psychologist named Edwards presented a concept of the interface between\nflight crew and other parts of the airspace environment. What is this concept called\nand the names of those elements involved ?",
        "answer": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment, and liveware",
        "choiceone": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, economy and liveware",
        "choicetwo": "The SHELL Concept. Software, harmony, environment, and location",
        "choicethree": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment and location",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Man possesses a system for maintaining his internal equilibrium in the face of\nvariations brought about by external stimulations.\nThis internal equilibrium is called:",
        "answer": "Homeostasis",
        "choiceone": "Heterostasis",
        "choicetwo": "Metastasis",
        "choicethree": "Isothermy",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Henry's Law explains the occurrence of:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness",
        "choiceone": "diffusion",
        "choicetwo": "hyperventilation",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Below 70,000 ft., what gas makes up the major part of the atmosphere ?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen",
        "choiceone": "Carbon dioxide",
        "choicetwo": "Ozone",
        "choicethree": "Oxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct ?",
        "answer": "Oxygen diffusion from the blood into the cells depends on the partial oxygen\npressure gradient.",
        "choiceone": "The gradient of diffusion is higher at altitude than it is at sea-level.",
        "choicetwo": "Oxygen is mainly transported in plasma.",
        "choicethree": "Oxygen diffusion from the lungs into the blood does not depend on partial oxygen\npressure.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung",
        "choicetwo": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen",
        "choicethree": "an increased number of red blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most dangerous symptoms of hypoxia at altitude are",
        "answer": "euphoria and impairment of judgement",
        "choiceone": "sensation of heat and blurred vision",
        "choicetwo": "breathlessness and reduced night vision",
        "choicethree": "hyperventilation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decompression sickness symptoms may develop due to",
        "answer": "cabin pressure loss when flying at higher altitudes (above 18000 FT)",
        "choiceone": "fast flights from a high-pressure zone into a low pressure area when flying an\nunpressurised aeroplane",
        "choicetwo": "sudden pressure surges in the cabin at altitudes below 18000 FT",
        "choicethree": "emergency descents after a cabin pressure loss",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What counter-measure can be used against barotrauma of the middle ear?",
        "answer": "Close the mouth, pinch the nose tight and blow out thereby increasing the\npressure in the mouth and throat. At the same time try to swallow or move lower\njaw",
        "choiceone": "Increase rate of descent",
        "choicetwo": "Pilots should apply anti-cold remedies prior every flight to prevent barotrauma in\nthe middle ear",
        "choicethree": "Stop climbing, start descent",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear is usually accompanied by",
        "answer": "a reduction in hearing ability and the feeling of increasing pressure",
        "choiceone": "dizziness",
        "choicetwo": "noises in the ear",
        "choicethree": "pain in the joints",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The risk of a barotrauma of the middle ear is more likely to occur",
        "answer": "with colds and rapid descents",
        "choiceone": "with colds and fast climbs",
        "choicetwo": "with colds and slow ascents",
        "choicethree": "after a decompression",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear is:",
        "answer": "an acute or chronic trauma to the middle ear caused by a difference of pressure on\neither side of the eardrum",
        "choiceone": "a dilatation of the Eustachian tube",
        "choicetwo": "a bacterial infection of the middle ear",
        "choicethree": "an infection of the middle ear caused by rapid decompression",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal rate of breathing when at rest is",
        "answer": "12 to 20 cycles a minute",
        "choiceone": "60 to 100 cycles a minute",
        "choicetwo": "25 to 30 cycles a minute",
        "choicethree": "32 to 40 cycles a minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is due to an excessive rate of breathing and can produce the\nfollowing symptoms:",
        "answer": "dizziness, tingling sensation in the fingers and toes, nausea and blurred vision",
        "choiceone": "reduced heart rate and increase in visual acuity",
        "choicetwo": "a state of overconfidence and reduced heart rate",
        "choicethree": "blue finger-nails and lips",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to get rid of excess nitrogen following scuba diving, subsequent flights\nshould be delayed",
        "answer": "24 hours",
        "choiceone": "36 hours after any scuba diving",
        "choicetwo": "48 hours after a continuous ascent in the water has been made",
        "choicethree": "3 hours after non decompression diving",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The procedure to be followed in the event of decompression when flying above 10,000\nft must:",
        "answer": "allow for the rapid supply of oxygen in order to prevent hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "make it possible to prevent hyperventilation owing to the inhalation of 100 %\noxygen",
        "choicetwo": "allow for a rapid descent independent from sufficient supply of oxygen in order to\nprevent disorders due to hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "make it possible to eliminate the risk of fogging due to the sudden pressure\nchanges",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the procedure above 10.000 ft altitude when faced with explosive\ndecompression?",
        "answer": "Don an oxygen mask and descend to below 10,000 ft",
        "choiceone": "Check the cabin altitude, don an oxygen mask and maintain level flight",
        "choicetwo": "First inform ATC",
        "choicethree": "Descend to below 10,000 ft and signal an emergency",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n-1: Scuba diving may be practiced without restriction\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia has:",
        "answer": "not enough functional haemoglobin",
        "choiceone": "not enough platelets",
        "choicetwo": "not enough white blood cells",
        "choicethree": "not enough plasma",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive g will cause the blood-pressure in the brain to:",
        "answer": "decrease",
        "choiceone": "first increase, then decrease",
        "choicetwo": "remain constant",
        "choicethree": "increase",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The transfer of carbon dioxide from the blood to the alveoli can be described by:",
        "answer": "the law of diffusion",
        "choiceone": "Boyles Law",
        "choicetwo": "Henry's Law",
        "choicethree": "Dalton's Law",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet",
        "choiceone": "20.000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "25.000 feet",
        "choicethree": "15.000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:",
        "answer": "the partial oxygen pressure is lower than at sea level.",
        "choiceone": "the composition of the air is different from sea level",
        "choicetwo": "the percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level",
        "choicethree": "the composition of the blood changes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following symptoms can indicate hypoxia?\n1. Blue lips and finger nails.\n2. Euphoria.\n3. Flatulence.\n4 .Unconsciousness..",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct.",
        "choiceone": "1, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the functions below, which is the most sensitive to hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Night vision.",
        "choiceone": "Hearing.",
        "choicetwo": "Motor coordination.",
        "choicethree": "Speech.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When hyperventilating you should:",
        "answer": "control your rate and depth of breathing",
        "choiceone": "apply the Valsalva method",
        "choicetwo": "use the oxygen mask",
        "choicethree": "descend",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A passenger complains about a painful inflated belly at 8.000 feet. You advise him to:\n1. unbuckle and massage the belly\n2. stand up and let go the gases out of the intestines\n3. eat less gas forming food and avoid carbonhydrated beverages before flight in the\nfuture\n4. drink a lot of water throughout the flight",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "only 4 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 not advisable",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tolerance to decompression sickness is decreased by:\n1. SCUBA diving\n2. Obesity\n3. Age\n4. Body height",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "only 4 is correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What human function is most sensitive to lack of oxygen?",
        "answer": "Night vision.",
        "choiceone": "Touch.",
        "choicetwo": "Hearing.",
        "choicethree": "Motor co-ordination.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "By 'long duration acceleration', we mean that it lasts more than:",
        "answer": "1 second",
        "choiceone": "20 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "5 minutes",
        "choicethree": "1 minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n-1: Modern aircraft allow for 50 - 60% relative humidity in the cabin air under any conditions of flight, which is\nsatisfactory for the body\n-2: Thirst is a symptom of dehydration\n-3: Dehydration may lead to clinical manifestations such as dizziness and fatigue\n-4: Drinking excessive quantities of water must be avoided since resistance to periods of low hydration will\notherwise be lost",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype and involuntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\ncalled:",
        "answer": "reflex",
        "choiceone": "change of stimulation level",
        "choicetwo": "control system",
        "choicethree": "data processing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time required for complete adaptation is",
        "answer": "for high levels of illumination 10 sec and for full dark adaptation 30 min",
        "choiceone": "for day and night: 30 min",
        "choicetwo": "for night 10 sec and for day 30 min",
        "choicethree": "for high levels of illumination 10 minutes and for low levels of illumination 30\nminutes",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Vitamin A and possibly vitamins B and C are chemical factors and essential to good night vision:\n1. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease night vision performance\n2. An excess intake of vitamin A will improve night vision performance significantly\n3. Pilots should be carefully concerned to take a balanced diet containing sufficient vitamin A\n4. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease visual acuity in photopic vision but not in scotopic vision",
        "answer": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 and 4 are false",
        "choiceone": "Only 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are false, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part",
        "choiceone": "crystalline lens",
        "choicetwo": "rods located in its peripheral zone",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its central part",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To optimise one's night-vision performance, it is necessary:\n- 1: to spend some time getting adapted to low levels of illumination\n- 2: to increase the instrument panel lighting by reducing the cockpit lighting\n- 3: not to focus on the point to be observed\n- 4: to avoid blinding sources of light",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "2",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Glaucoma is:",
        "answer": "high intra-ocular pressure",
        "choiceone": "disturbed adaptation",
        "choicetwo": "disturbed colour vision",
        "choicethree": "disturbed night vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by presbycusis?",
        "answer": "Gradual loss of hearing with age.",
        "choiceone": "Total loss of hearing in both ears due to disease.",
        "choicetwo": "Total loss of hearing in one ear due to use of a headset in the cockpit.",
        "choicethree": "Gradual onset of long-sightedness with age.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What factors can lead to a deterioration in vision?\n1.  Hypoxia\n2.  Smoking\n3.  Poor diet, lacking Vitamin A\n4.  Exposure to bright lights\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1, 3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What illusion may occur if an aircraft is flying into fog, snow or haze?",
        "answer": "Objects seem to be farther away than in reality",
        "choiceone": "Objects seem to move slower than in reality",
        "choicetwo": "Objects will appear bigger in size than in reality",
        "choicethree": "Objects will appear closer than they really are",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The group of tiny bones (the hammer, anvil and stirrup) are situated in",
        "answer": "the middle ear",
        "choiceone": "the inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "the outer ear",
        "choicethree": "the maxillary sinus",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbycusis results in:",
        "answer": "reduction in the perception of high tones first",
        "choiceone": "reduction in the perception of low tones first",
        "choicetwo": "reduction in the perception of all tones equally",
        "choicethree": "will not affect a pilot's hearing if he/she is wearing ear-plugs all the time",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tinnitus is",
        "answer": "ringing in the ears",
        "choiceone": "very insensitive hearing",
        "choicetwo": "very sensitive hearing",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Older pilots very often need reading glasses. These are usually",
        "answer": "half eye lenses",
        "choiceone": "one lens for distance viewing and another lens for near viewing",
        "choicetwo": "full form lenses",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The vestibular apparatus",
        "answer": "reacts to linear/angular acceleration and gravity",
        "choiceone": "gives the impression of hearing",
        "choicetwo": "reacts to pressure changes in the middle ear",
        "choicethree": "reacts to vibrations of the cochlea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The inner ear is able to perceive:\n1. angular acceleration\n2. linear acceleration\n3. Noise",
        "answer": "1 and 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2 is correct, 1 and 3 are both false",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Angular accelerations are perceived by:",
        "answer": "the semi circular canals",
        "choiceone": "the otholiths",
        "choicetwo": "the receptors in the skin and the joints",
        "choicethree": "the cochlea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The proprioceptive senses (seat-of-the-pants sense) are important for motor\ncoordination.\nThey",
        "answer": "are completely unreliable for orientation when flying in IMC",
        "choiceone": "indicate the difference between gravity and G-forces",
        "choicetwo": "allow the pilot to determine the absolute vertical at flight condition",
        "choicethree": "are important senses for flight training in IMC",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When accelerating in level flight we could experience the sensation of a",
        "answer": "climb",
        "choiceone": "descent",
        "choicetwo": "spin",
        "choicethree": "turn",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot, trying to pick up a fallen object from the cockpit floor during a tight turn,\nexperiences:",
        "answer": "coriolis illusion",
        "choiceone": "barotrauma",
        "choicetwo": "pressure vertigo",
        "choicethree": "autokinetic illusion",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot prevent spatial disorientation in flight?",
        "answer": "Establish and maintain a good instrument cross check.",
        "choiceone": "Always try to catch outside visual cues.",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on good situational awareness believing your natural senses.",
        "choicethree": "Rely on the \"seat of the pants\" sense.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are disorientated during night flying you must:",
        "answer": "rely on your instruments",
        "choiceone": "check your rate of breathing - do not breathe too fast",
        "choicetwo": "descend",
        "choicethree": "look outside",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Somatogravic illusion gives the pilot a false impression of:",
        "answer": "climbing or descending.",
        "choiceone": "descending and turning to the right.",
        "choicetwo": "climbing and turning to the right.",
        "choicethree": "descending and turning to the left.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following mechanisms regulate body temperature when exposed to extreme\nhigh environmental temperatures?\n-1: Shivering\n-2: Vaso-constriction of peripheral blood vessels\n-3: Sweating\n-4: Vaso-dilation of peripheral blood vessels",
        "answer": "3,4",
        "choiceone": "1",
        "choicetwo": "1,3,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n1  Hypothermia affects physical and mental abilities.\n2  Man has effective natural protection against intense cold.\n3  Shivering makes it possible to combat the cold to a certain extent, but uses up a lot of energy\n4  Disorders associated with hypothermia appear at a body temperature of less than 35\u00b0C",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "2,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The body loses water via:\n1. the skin and the lungs\n2. the kidneys\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choiceone": "both are false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is not correct and 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 is correct and 2 is not correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.",
        "choiceone": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.",
        "choicetwo": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.",
        "choicethree": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When considering the eating-habits of pilots:",
        "answer": "breakfast should bring about 25% of the daily calorie intake",
        "choiceone": "high intake of chocolate is recommended before flight to prevent reactional\nhypoglycemia",
        "choicetwo": "low fibre and low protein/carbohydratediet is ideal",
        "choicethree": "a heavy supper is best",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens",
        "choiceone": "A mis-shapened cornea",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea",
        "choicethree": "Lack of mobility of the cornea",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hepatitis 'A' is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "food or water which has been contaminated.",
        "choiceone": "bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin.",
        "choicetwo": "insect bites.",
        "choicethree": "droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may",
        "answer": "intensify the effects of the drugs",
        "choiceone": "increase the rate of alcohol elimination from the blood",
        "choicetwo": "compensate for side effects of drugs",
        "choicethree": "show undesired effects only during night flights",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding alcohol in the human body?",
        "answer": "Judgement and decision making can be affected even by a small amount of\nalcohol.",
        "choiceone": "When drinking coffee, the human body metabolizes alcohol at a faster rate than\nnormal.",
        "choicetwo": "An increase of altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.",
        "choicethree": "A small amount of alcohol increases visual acuity.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In an abnormal situation the pilot has an apparently correct explanation for the\nproblem. The chance that he/she now ignores or devalues other relevant information,\nnot fitting into his/her mental picture is:",
        "answer": "not usual",
        "choiceone": "very rare",
        "choicetwo": "not applicable with old and experienced pilots",
        "choicethree": "not possible since correct training should have eliminated this problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The available cognitive resources of the human brain:",
        "answer": "are limited and make it impossible to perform two attentional tasks at the same\ntime",
        "choiceone": "are limited but make it possible to easily perform several tasks at the same time",
        "choicetwo": "allow for twin-tasks operation without any loss of effectiveness",
        "choicethree": "are virtually unlimited",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can be described as being proficient, when he/she:",
        "answer": "has automated a large part of the necessary flight deck routine operations in order\nto free his/her cognitive resources",
        "choiceone": "is capable of maintaining a high level of arousal during a great bulk of the flight",
        "choicetwo": "is able to reduce his/her arousal to a low level during the entire flight",
        "choicethree": "knows how to off-load all his/her resources to the automation of tasks",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is \"divided attention\"?",
        "answer": "The management of several matters of interest dealt with individually one after the\nother",
        "choiceone": "The adverse effect of motivation which leads to one's attention being dispersed",
        "choicetwo": "Ease of concentrating on a particular objective",
        "choicethree": "Difficulty of concentrating on a particular objective",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first stage in the information process is",
        "answer": "sensory stimulation",
        "choiceone": "the recognition of information",
        "choicetwo": "selective attention",
        "choicethree": "perception",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Our mental model of the world is based",
        "answer": "on both our past experiences and the sensory information we receive",
        "choiceone": "on both our past experiences and our motor programmes",
        "choicetwo": "entirely on past experiences",
        "choicethree": "entirely on the sensory information we receive",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following provides the basis of all perceptions?",
        "answer": "The intensity of the stimuli.",
        "choiceone": "The aural or visual significance attributed in short term memory.",
        "choicetwo": "The aural or visual significance attributed in long term memory.",
        "choicethree": "The separation of figure and background.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main adverse effect of expectation with regards to perception?",
        "answer": "Expectation often guides the focus of attention towards a particular aspect, while\npossible alternates are neglected",
        "choiceone": "The attention area is enlarged by expectation, however it will therefore lead to\nuncertainties when a pilot is looking for a decision",
        "choicetwo": "Expectations always lead to routine errors",
        "choicethree": "Expectation is a tool that allows capture of all relevant information",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motor programmes are:",
        "answer": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed without\ncontinuous conscious control",
        "choiceone": "rules that enable us to deal with novel situations",
        "choicetwo": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed only under\ncontinuous conscious control",
        "choicethree": "rules that enable us to deal with preconceived situations",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down",
        "choiceone": "to ignore messages for other aircraft",
        "choicetwo": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Less experienced pilots differ from experienced pilots in the following way:",
        "answer": "inexperienced pilots refer to information more than experts when carrying out the\nsame task",
        "choiceone": "experienced pilots are less routine-minded than young pilots because they know\nthat routine causes mistakes",
        "choicetwo": "flight planning performance decreases with age, and experience is unable to mask\nthis deficiency",
        "choicethree": "task for task, an expert's workload is greater than a novice's one",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements summarises the impact that motivation may have\non attention?",
        "answer": "It increases alertness and attention",
        "choiceone": "Motivation has only a small effect on attention, but it facilitates alertness",
        "choicetwo": "It stimulates attention but may lead to phases of low arousal",
        "choicethree": "It only facilitates attention in extreme cases (risk of death)",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What strategies can be used to combat human error?\n-1: Reducing error-prone mechanisms.\n-2: Improving the way in which error is taken into account in training.\n-3: Sanctions against the initiators of error.\n-4: Improving recovery from errors and its consequences.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors are of the following type(s) in skill-based\nbehaviour:",
        "answer": "routine errors",
        "choiceone": "creative errors",
        "choicetwo": "handling errors",
        "choicethree": "knowledge errors",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If one error is allowed to effect a whole system, the system is described as:",
        "answer": "Vulnerable",
        "choiceone": "Corrupted",
        "choicetwo": "Error tolerant",
        "choicethree": "Error-prone",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main characteristics of active errors ?\nThey:\n1. are detectable only with difficulty by first-line operators\n2. have rapid and direct consequences on the action in progress\n3. occur at the human/machine interface\n4. lie dormant and are undetected at first",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2",
        "choicethree": "3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the external factors that may contribute to an error, cockpit noise and the\nrestriction of the field of view due to windscreen design correspond to:",
        "answer": "ergonomic factors.",
        "choiceone": "organisational factors.",
        "choicetwo": "social factors.",
        "choicethree": "psychobiological factors.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Once a pilot has developed a certain way of thinking about a problem he will probably",
        "answer": "find it difficult to get out of that way of thinking and difficult to try a different\ninterpretation of the data",
        "choiceone": "find it impossible to get out of that way of thinking, whatever happens",
        "choicetwo": "find it easy to interpret the data in different ways",
        "choicethree": "find it difficult to stick to his/her interpretation of the data",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Habits and routine can influence decision-making in a way that:",
        "answer": "shows a tendency to select the most familiar solution first and foremost,\nsometimes to the detriment of achieving the best possible result",
        "choiceone": "one always selects a choice in accordance with the company's usual practices",
        "choicetwo": "professional pilots will never question established procedures",
        "choicethree": "habit is the product of experience and should be used as a primary consideration\nin all decisions",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following course of action should be taken if gastrointestinal complaints in flight crew occur before to\ntake-off:\n-1: take the standard medicines and advise the doctor on returning from the flight\n-2: assess your own ability to fly, if necessary with the help of a doctor\n-3: if in doubt about fitness to fly - do not fly!\n-4: reduce the cabin temperature, and drink before you are thirsty so as to avoid dehydration",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult",
        "choicetwo": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality",
        "choicethree": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The unique organisation of characteristics which determine the typical or standard\nbehaviour of an individual is known as:",
        "answer": "personality",
        "choiceone": "heredity",
        "choicetwo": "learning",
        "choicethree": "development",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A copilot has passed an upgrading course to become a captain. Which psychological\nconsequence is most likely?",
        "answer": "His/her self-concept is going to change because of new roles and tasks which\nhave to be incorporated.",
        "choiceone": "His/her self -concept is going to be stabilized because of the higher status as a\ncaptain.",
        "choicetwo": "An upgrading never has psychological consequences.",
        "choicethree": "The increased command authority leads to a higher professionalism.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
        "answer": "Stressors accumulate thus increasing the likelihood of exhaustion.",
        "choiceone": "Stress should always be avoided under any circumstances.",
        "choicetwo": "Stressors are independent from each other.",
        "choicethree": "People are capable of living without stress.",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following physical stimuli may cause stress reactions?\n-1: noise.\n-2: conflict.\n-3: temperature.\n-4: an administrative problem.\n-5: hunger.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1,3,5",
        "choiceone": "3,4,5",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,5",
        "choicethree": "1,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pilot stress reactions:",
        "answer": "differ from pilot to pilot, depending on how a person manages the particular\nstressors",
        "choiceone": "do not change with the environment or different situations but mainly with the\ncharacters themselves",
        "choicetwo": "seem to be the same for most pilots",
        "choicethree": "are related to an internationally recognized list of stressors where the top-ten\nitems should be avoided by every means",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The biological reaction to stress is identical regardless of the cause of stress. This\nmechanism occurs in three phases and is referred to, by Selye, as the \"General\nAdaptation Syndrome\".\nThe sequence is:",
        "answer": "alarm phase - resistance phase - exhaustion phase",
        "choiceone": "exhaustion phase - resistance phase - adaptation phase",
        "choicetwo": "resistance phase - exhaustion phase - recovery phase",
        "choicethree": "alarm phase - denial phase - exhaustion phase",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct statement",
        "answer": "a pilot who is fit will handle a high stress situation better than an unfit pilot",
        "choiceone": "a pilot who is fit may or may not handle a high stress situation better than an unfit pilot",
        "choicetwo": "fitness does not affect the ability to handle a high stress situation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the effect of tiredness on attention ?",
        "answer": "It reduces the ability to manage multiple matters",
        "choiceone": "It increases the ability to manage multiple matters",
        "choicetwo": "It has no specific effects on attention",
        "choicethree": "It leads to one's attention being shared between different centres of interest",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main effects of a lack of sleep on performance?",
        "answer": "It increases fatigue, reduces concentration and increases the risk of sensory\nillusions",
        "choiceone": "It causes muscular spasms",
        "choicetwo": "It reduces concentration and fatigue only with sleep loss greater than 48 hours",
        "choicethree": "It increases fatigue and concentration difficulties, but facilitates stress\nmanagement by muscular relaxation",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To resynchronize a circadian rhythm, it takes more time after:",
        "answer": "eastbound flights",
        "choiceone": "south-north flights",
        "choicetwo": "north-south flights",
        "choicethree": "westbound flights",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sleep pattern is closely associated with:",
        "answer": "Body temperature",
        "choiceone": "Blood pressure",
        "choicetwo": "Glucose level",
        "choicethree": "Heart rate",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mode Error is associated with:",
        "answer": "Automation",
        "choiceone": "Vertigo",
        "choicetwo": "Check lists",
        "choicethree": "Hardware",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A high degree of cockpit automation may alter the traditional tasks of the pilots in a\nway, that",
        "answer": "the attention of the cockpit crew will become reduced as a consequence of 'being\nout of the loop'",
        "choiceone": "the crew can pay more attention to problem-solving in an abnormal situation\nwithout monitoring the automatic systems",
        "choicetwo": "it is guaranteed that the crew always maintains situational awareness",
        "choicethree": "Crew Coordination can be neglected on long haul flights without compromising\nsafety",
        "source": "pdf/Type1/hp\\HUMN (2).pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The changes in atmospheric gas pressure with altitude are:",
        "answer": "non-linear, with a higher rate of change at lower levels",
        "choiceone": "rises with altitude",
        "choicetwo": "decreases in a linear manner with altitude",
        "choicethree": "decreases more slowly at lower altitudes compared with at higher levels",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress in the acute form acts over",
        "answer": "the short term",
        "choiceone": "the long term",
        "choicetwo": "long or short term",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress in the chronic form acts over",
        "answer": "the long term",
        "choiceone": "the short term",
        "choicetwo": "long or short term",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A factor which can produce stress is a",
        "answer": "stressor",
        "choiceone": "receptor",
        "choicetwo": "impeder",
        "choicethree": "Hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An accumulation of stress inducing factors",
        "answer": "will produce a higher stress level",
        "choiceone": "will not produce a higher stress level",
        "choicetwo": "may produce a higher stress level",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Breathing 100% oxygen at 40000 ft is equivalent to breathing ambient air at:",
        "answer": "10 000 ft",
        "choiceone": "8 000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "14 000 ft",
        "choicethree": "18 000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Resistance to various types of stress",
        "answer": "is adversely affected by the presence of other stress factors",
        "choiceone": "is not affected by the presence of other stress factors",
        "choicetwo": "may be not affected by the presence of other stress factors",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what altitude (breathing 100% oxygen without pressure) could symptoms\nof hypoxia be expected?",
        "answer": "Approximately 38 - 40 000 ft.",
        "choiceone": "Approximately 10 - 12 000 ft.",
        "choicetwo": "22 000 ft",
        "choicethree": "Approximately 35 000 ft.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct statement",
        "answer": "a pilot who is fit will handle a high stress situation better than an unfit\npilot",
        "choiceone": "fitness does not affect the ability to handle a high stress situation",
        "choicetwo": "a pilot who is fit may or may not handle a high stress situation better\nthan an unfit pilot",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You can survive at any altitude, provided that",
        "answer": "enough oxygen, pressure and heat is available",
        "choiceone": "21% oxygen is available in the air you breath in",
        "choicetwo": "pressure respiration is guaranteed for that altitude",
        "choicethree": "the temperature in the cabin does not drop below 10\" C",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "At which altitude is it necessary to breathe 100% oxygen plus pressure after a\nrapid decompression ?",
        "answer": "Approximately 40 000 ft.",
        "choiceone": "Approximately 14 000 ft.",
        "choicetwo": "Approximately 20 000 ft.",
        "choicethree": "Approximately 50 000 ft.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot suffers from hypothermia (e.g. after loss of cabin heating) his/her\ndemand for oxygen will be:",
        "answer": "initially increased",
        "choiceone": "unaffected",
        "choicetwo": "reduced giving a better tolerance to hypoxia at higher altitudes",
        "choicethree": "raised leading to an increased tolerance to hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to tolerate pressure",
        "answer": "varies in individuals",
        "choiceone": "is directly related to age",
        "choicetwo": "is directly related in seniority in a crew and flying experience",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The atmosphere contains the following gases:",
        "answer": "78% nitrogen, 21% oxygen, 0,03% carbon dioxide, rest: rare gases",
        "choiceone": "78% nitrogen, 21% oxygen, 1% carbon monoxide, rest: rare gases",
        "choicetwo": "78% helium, 21% oxygen, 1% carbon monoxide, rest: rare gases",
        "choicethree": "78% helium, 21% oxygen, 0,03% carbon dioxide, rest: rare gases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Performance can be affected by fatigue and lack of motivation. This situation\ncan lead to",
        "answer": "under arousal",
        "choiceone": "over response",
        "choicetwo": "under response",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volume percentage of oxygen in the atmosphere is 21% which",
        "answer": "is constant at all altitudes for conventional aircraft",
        "choiceone": "decreases with increasing altitude",
        "choicetwo": "increases with increasing altitude",
        "choicethree": "is dependent on the present air pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The percentage of oxygen in the air at an altitude of approximately\n34 000 ft is:",
        "answer": "21%",
        "choiceone": "5%",
        "choicetwo": "10,5%",
        "choicethree": "42%",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the\nblood, transportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination\nof carbon dioxide from the body",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon\nmonoxide",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of\noxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Inhaling carbon monoxide can be extremely dangerous during flying.\nWhich of the following statements is correct?",
        "answer": "Carbon monoxide is odourless and colourless.",
        "choiceone": "Carbon monoxide increases the oxygen saturation in the blood.",
        "choicetwo": "With increasing altitude the negative effects of carbon monoxide\npoisoning can be compensated for.",
        "choicethree": "Small amounts of carbon monoxide are harmless.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypothermia can cause heat stress. The best way to minimize the condition is\nto",
        "answer": "drink plenty of fluid",
        "choiceone": "rest and sleep as much as possible",
        "choicetwo": "attempt to concentrate carefully and to use check lists",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide poisoning",
        "answer": "is more likely to occur in aeroplanes where the cabin heating is supplied\nby passing cabin air over the exhaust manifold(s)",
        "choiceone": "is more likely to occur in aeroplanes with twin-engines because of high\nengine efficiency",
        "choicetwo": "only occurs in jet-driven aeroplanes",
        "choicethree": "occurs only above 15 degrees OAT",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A good ratio of activity to sleep is",
        "answer": "two hours activity to one hour of sleep",
        "choiceone": "three hours activity to one hour of sleep",
        "choicetwo": "four hours activity to one hour of sleep",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct statement",
        "answer": "the body is freshened during non REM sleep and the brain is freshened\nduring REM sleep",
        "choiceone": "the brain is freshened during non REM sleep and the body is freshened\nduring REM sleep",
        "choicetwo": "the brain and the body are freshened during non REM sleep",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following applies to carbon monoxide poisoning?",
        "answer": "Several days are needed to recuperate from a carbon monoxide\npoisoning.",
        "choiceone": "A very early symptom of carbon monoxide poisoning is euphoria.",
        "choicetwo": "The human body shows no sign of carbon monoxide poisoning.",
        "choicethree": "Inhaling carbon monoxide leads to hyperventilation.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is oxygen mainly transported in the blood?",
        "answer": "Haemoglobin in the red blood cells.",
        "choiceone": "White blood cells.",
        "choicetwo": "Plasma.",
        "choicethree": "Blood fat.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most important of the diurnal body rhythms is",
        "answer": "internal body temperature",
        "choiceone": "blood pressure",
        "choicetwo": "body temperature and blood pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas most readily combines with haemoglobin?",
        "answer": "carbon monoxide",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen",
        "choicetwo": "oxygen",
        "choicethree": "carbon dioxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct statement",
        "answer": "if is not corrected by the sun and other zeitgebers, the natural body\ncycle is greater than 24 hours",
        "choiceone": "if it is not corrected by the sun and other zeitgebers, the natural body\ncycle is less than 24 hours",
        "choicetwo": "the natural body cycle is about 24 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is true concerning carbon monoxide?",
        "answer": "It is to be found in the smoke of cigarettes lifting up a smoker's\n\"physiological altitude\".",
        "choiceone": "It combines 5 times faster to the haemoglobin than oxygen.",
        "choicetwo": "It has no physiological effect when mixed with oxygen.",
        "choicethree": "It is always present in the lungs.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Plus lenses are",
        "answer": "convex",
        "choiceone": "concave",
        "choicetwo": "barrel shaped",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Myopic people need \u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013.. lenses to see clearly at long distance",
        "answer": "concave",
        "choiceone": "convex",
        "choicetwo": "plus",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An increase in the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood leads to:",
        "answer": "an increased respiratory rate",
        "choiceone": "a decrease of acidity in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "a reduction of red blood cells",
        "choicethree": "an improving resistance to hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is",
        "answer": "normal deterioration of short sight with age",
        "choiceone": "normal deterioration of long sight with age",
        "choicetwo": "a limiting medical condition affecting the eyes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the alveoli gas exchange takes place (external respiration). Which gas will\ndiffuse from the blood into the lungs?",
        "answer": "Carbon dioxide.",
        "choiceone": "Ambient air.",
        "choicetwo": "Oxygen.",
        "choicethree": "Carbon monoxide.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is corrected with",
        "answer": "plus lenses",
        "choiceone": "minus lenses",
        "choicetwo": "pin cushion shaped lenses",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbycussis",
        "answer": "is loss of high frequency hearing",
        "choiceone": "is loss of low frequency hearing",
        "choicetwo": "is ringing in the ears",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct ?",
        "answer": "Oxygen diffusion from the blood into the cells depends on the partial\noxygen pressure gradient.",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen is mainly transported in plasma.",
        "choicetwo": "The gradient of diffusion is higher at altitude than it is at sea-level.",
        "choicethree": "Oxygen diffusion from the lungs into the blood does not depend on\npartial oxygen pressure.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tinnitus is",
        "answer": "ringing in the ears",
        "choiceone": "very sensitive hearing",
        "choicetwo": "very insensitive hearing",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot increase his tolerance to +Gz ?",
        "answer": "Tightening of the stomach muscles.",
        "choiceone": "Tighten shoulder harness.",
        "choicetwo": "Take an upright seat position.",
        "choicethree": "Relax the muscles and lean upper body forward.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by:\n1. low partial pressure of oxygen in the atmosphere when flying at high\naltitudes without pressurisation and supplemental oxygen\n2. a decreased saturation of oxygen in the blood due to carbon monoxide\nattached to the haemoglobin\n3. blood pooling in the lower extremities due to inertia (+ Gz)\n4. malfunction of the body cells to metabolize oxygen",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 2, 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Older pilots very often need reading glasses. These are usually",
        "answer": "half eye lenses",
        "choiceone": "full form lenses",
        "choicetwo": "one lens for distance viewing and another lens for near viewing",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot may suffer from hypoxia",
        "answer": "after decompression at high altitude and not using additional oxygen in\ntime",
        "choiceone": "after decompression to 30 000 feet and using 100 % oxygen via an\noxygen mask",
        "choicetwo": "if his rate of climb exceeds 5 000 ft/min",
        "choicethree": "if he/she is flying an unpressurised airplane at an altitude of 15 000 feet\nand breathing 100 % oxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is quite normal for aircrew to suffer\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013\u2013.. in air conditioned/\npressurized aircraft",
        "answer": "itchy, dry eyes",
        "choiceone": "watery eyes",
        "choicetwo": "blurred vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia especially dangerous for pilots flying solo?",
        "answer": "Since the first signs of hypoxia are generally hard to detect.",
        "choiceone": "Difficulties in controlling the aircraft.",
        "choicetwo": "Hypoxia improves night vision therefore the pilot will have no indication\nof danger.",
        "choicethree": "A solo pilot is more prone to illusions.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Persons who suffer from tinnitus often have difficulty in falling asleep. This is\nbecause",
        "answer": "the constant hissing and ringing disturb sleep",
        "choiceone": "of the abnormal brain waves produces",
        "choicetwo": "this type of person is inevitably insomniac",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The symptoms of hypoxia include:",
        "answer": "Visual disturbances, lack of concentration, euphoria.",
        "choiceone": "Nausea and barotitis.",
        "choicetwo": "Dull headache and bends.",
        "choicethree": "Dizziness, hypothermia.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Better resistance to tinnitus may occur",
        "answer": "if hearing protection is used in early flying life",
        "choiceone": "if masking devices are used",
        "choicetwo": "if ear drops are used regularly",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is/are the symptom(s) of hypoxia ?",
        "answer": "Lack of concentration, fatigue, euphoria",
        "choiceone": "Pain in the joints",
        "choicetwo": "Low blood pressure",
        "choicethree": "Excessive rate and depth of breathing combined with pains in the chest\narea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement applies to hypoxia?",
        "answer": "sensitivity and reaction to hypoxia varies from person to person",
        "choiceone": "carbon monoxide increases the tolerance of the brain to oxygen\ndeficiency",
        "choicetwo": "you may become immune to hypoxia when exposed repeatedly to\nhypoxia",
        "choicethree": "it is possible to predict when, how and where hypoxia reaction starts to\nset in",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by",
        "answer": "a lack of red blood cells in the blood or decreased ability of the\nhaemoglobin to transport oxygen",
        "choiceone": "a lack of nitrogen in ambient air",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which symptom of hypoxia is the most dangerous for conducting safe flight ?",
        "answer": "The degradation of reasoning and perceptive functions.",
        "choiceone": "Dizziness.",
        "choicetwo": "Lack of adaptation.",
        "choicethree": "Lack of accommodation.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot, climbing in a non-pressurised aircraft and without using supplemental\noxygen will pass the \"critical threshold\" at approximately:",
        "answer": "20 000 ft",
        "choiceone": "16 000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "18 000 ft",
        "choicethree": "38 000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Breathing 100% will elevate the pilot's physiological safe altitude to\napproximately:",
        "answer": "40 000 ft",
        "choiceone": "10 000",
        "choicetwo": "22 000 ft",
        "choicethree": "45 000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most dangerous symptoms of hypoxia at altitude are",
        "answer": "euphoria and impairment of judgement",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation",
        "choicetwo": "sensation of heat and blurred vision",
        "choicethree": "breathlessness and reduced night vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With hyperventilation, caused by high levels of arousal or overstress:",
        "answer": "an increased amount of carbon dioxide is exhaled causing muscular\nspasms and even unconsciousness",
        "choiceone": "finger nails and lips will turn blue (\"cyanosis\")",
        "choicetwo": "more oxygen will reach the brain",
        "choicethree": "peripheral and scotopic vision will be improved",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following symptoms can mark the onset of hyperventilation?",
        "answer": "Dizzy feeling",
        "choiceone": "Slow heart beat",
        "choicetwo": "Slow rate of breathing",
        "choicethree": "Cyanosis (blueing of lips and finger nails)",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Out of the list of possible measures to counteract hyperventilation, the most\neffective measure is:",
        "answer": "breathe into a plastic or paper bag",
        "choiceone": "hold breath",
        "choicetwo": "avoid strenuous flight manoeuvres",
        "choicethree": "speak soothingly and get the person to breathe slowly",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What event can cause a hyperventilation (not required by physical need)?\n1. Pressure breathing.\n2. Anxiety or fear.\n3. Overstress.\n4. Strong pain.\n5. Jogging.",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct, 5 is false",
        "choiceone": "Only 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,3,4 and 5 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1and 5 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following could a pilot experience when he is hyperventilating?\n1. Dizziness\n2. Muscular spasms\n3. Visual disturbances\n4. Cyanosis",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, all others are correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What could cause hyperventilation ?",
        "answer": "Fear, anxiety and distress",
        "choiceone": "Abuse of alcohol",
        "choicetwo": "Extreme low rate of breathing",
        "choicethree": "Fatigue",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot who is hyperventilating for a prolonged period of time may even\nbecome unconscious.\nHyperventilation is likely to occur, when:",
        "answer": "the pilot is emotionally aroused",
        "choiceone": "there is a low CO-pressure in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "he/she is flying a tight turn",
        "choicethree": "there is an increased blood flow to the brain",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Breathing pure oxygen (without pressure) will be sufficient up to an altitude\nof:",
        "answer": "40000 FT",
        "choiceone": "45000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "60000 FT",
        "choicethree": "80000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) is:",
        "answer": "the length of time during which an individual can act with both mental\nand physical efficiency; measured from the moment at which he/she is\nexposed to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "the time before becoming unconscious at a sudden pressure loss",
        "choicetwo": "the time after pressure loss until decompression sickness sets in",
        "choicethree": "the time between the start of hypoxia and death",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"Effective Performance Time\" or \"Time of Useful Consciousness\" after a\ndecompression at 35 000 ft is:",
        "answer": "between 30 and 60 seconds",
        "choiceone": "approximately 3 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "approximately 5 minutes",
        "choicethree": "less than 20 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time between inadequate oxygen supply and incapacitation is called TUC\n(Time of Useful Consciousness). It",
        "answer": "varies individually and depends on cabin pressure altitude",
        "choiceone": "is the same amount of time for every person",
        "choicetwo": "is not dependent on physical or psychological pressure",
        "choicethree": "varies individually and does not depend on altitude",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After a decompression to 43 000 FT the TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness)\nwill be approximately:",
        "answer": "5-15 seconds",
        "choiceone": "30-45 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "45-60 seconds",
        "choicethree": "60-90 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flights immediately after SCUBA-diving (compressed gas mixtures, bottles)\n(>10 m depth)",
        "answer": "are forbidden",
        "choiceone": "can be performed without any danger",
        "choicetwo": "are allowed, if 38000 FT are not exceeded",
        "choicethree": "should be avoided because hypoxia may develop",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pain in the Joints (\"bends\") is a symptom of:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness",
        "choiceone": "barotrauma",
        "choicetwo": "air-sickness",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After a cabin pressure loss in approximately 35 000 FT the TUC (Time of\nUseful Consciousness) will be approximately:",
        "answer": "30 -40 seconds",
        "choiceone": "10-15 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "3-4 minutes",
        "choicethree": "5 minutes or more",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You suffered a rapid decompression without the appearance of any\ndecompression sickness symptoms.\nWhat should you do before flying ?",
        "answer": "seek prompt aeromedical advice",
        "choiceone": "nothing, you may fly immediately",
        "choicetwo": "delay your next flight for 6 hours",
        "choicethree": "seek aeromedical advice only if the symptoms become apparent",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment (> 10 m\ndepth) is forbidden because it:",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure\naltitudes below 18 000 FT",
        "choiceone": "prevents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when\nclimbing to altitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decompression sickness symptoms may develop due to",
        "answer": "cabin pressure loss when flying at higher altitudes (above 18000 FT)",
        "choiceone": "sudden pressure surges in the cabin at altitudes below 18000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "emergency descents after a cabin pressure loss",
        "choicethree": "fast flights from a high-pressure zone into a low pressure area when\nflying an unpressurised aeroplane",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The function of the Eustachian tube is to equalise the pressure between the:",
        "answer": "middle ear and the external atmosphere",
        "choiceone": "sinuses of the nose and the external atmosphere",
        "choicetwo": "nose, throat and the external atmosphere",
        "choicethree": "sinuses",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disruptions of pressure equalization in air-filled cavities of the head (nose, ear\netc.) are called:",
        "answer": "barotrauma",
        "choiceone": "embolism",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "hyperventilation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma caused by gas accumulation in the stomach and intestines can\nlead to:",
        "answer": "pressure pain or flatulence",
        "choiceone": "barotitis",
        "choicetwo": "decompression sickness",
        "choicethree": "barosinusitis",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What counter-measure can be used against barotrauma of the middle ear?",
        "answer": "Close the mouth, pinch the nose tight and blow out thereby increasing\nthe pressure in the mouth and throat. At the same time try to swallow or\nmove lower jaw",
        "choiceone": "Increase rate of descent",
        "choicetwo": "Stop climbing, start descent",
        "choicethree": "Pilots should apply anti-cold remedies prior every flight to prevent\nbarotrauma in the middle ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the sinuses of the nose",
        "answer": "is caused by differences in pressure between the sinus cavities and the\noutside air pressure",
        "choiceone": "only arises in flying and not in diving",
        "choicetwo": "is an irritation of the sinuses caused by the over-use of nasal sprays",
        "choicethree": "is only caused by colds and their effects",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Even at normal cabin altitudes (i.e. around 8000 ft) you can get severe\nabdominal pain and flatulence after eating gas forming foods or fizzy drinks.\nThe correct counter-measure is:",
        "answer": "descend to a lower altitude",
        "choiceone": "climb to a higher altitude",
        "choicetwo": "perform \"valsalva manoeuvre\"",
        "choicethree": "use supplemental oxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear",
        "answer": "is more likely, when the pilot is flying with a respiratory infection and\nduring descent",
        "choiceone": "is only caused by large pressure changes during climb",
        "choicetwo": "causes severe pain in the sinuses",
        "choicethree": "is to be expected during rapid decompressions, but an emergency\ndescent immediately following the decompression will eliminate the\nproblem",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Trapped intestinal gases can cause severe pain.\nWhen is this the case?",
        "answer": "More frequent when flying above 18 000 FT in a non-pressurized aircraft.",
        "choiceone": "At lower altitudes.",
        "choicetwo": "Only in pressurized aircraft when flying at higher flight levels.",
        "choicethree": "During descent as well as during climb, when the cabin pressure\naltitude exceeds 2 000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which counter-measure can a pilot can use against a barotrauma of the\nmiddle ear?",
        "answer": "Stop descending, climb again and then descend with reduced sink rate",
        "choiceone": "Increase the rate of descent",
        "choicetwo": "Stop chewing and swallowing movements",
        "choicethree": "Use drugs against a cold",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear most likely will occur",
        "answer": "when descending rapidly",
        "choiceone": "during a long high altitude flight",
        "choicetwo": "when climbing",
        "choicethree": "in sudden steep turns",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear is usually accompanied by",
        "answer": "a reduction in hearing ability and the feeling of increasing pressure",
        "choiceone": "dizziness",
        "choicetwo": "noises in the ear",
        "choicethree": "pain in the joints",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The risk of a barotrauma of the middle ear is more likely to occur",
        "answer": "with colds and rapid descents",
        "choiceone": "with colds and fast climbs",
        "choicetwo": "with colds and slow ascents",
        "choicethree": "after a decompression",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Seat-of-the-Pants Sense involves receptors in the",
        "answer": "muscles, tendons and joints sensitive to the position and movement of\nbody parts",
        "choiceone": "semicircular canals",
        "choicetwo": "utriculus and sacculus",
        "choicethree": "skin only",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Equalization of pressure is limited between the middle ear and the ambient,\nwhen:",
        "answer": "the Eustachian tube is blocked",
        "choiceone": "the nose is pinched",
        "choicetwo": "you breath through the mouth",
        "choicethree": "barotrauma exists in the sinuses",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear is:",
        "answer": "an acute or chronic trauma to the middle ear caused by a difference of\npressure on either side of the eardrum",
        "choiceone": "a bacterial infection of the middle ear",
        "choicetwo": "a dilatation of the Eustachian tube",
        "choicethree": "an infection of the middle ear caused by rapid decompression",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The maximum number of unrelated items that can be stored in working\nmemory is:",
        "answer": "about 7 items",
        "choiceone": "very limited - only 3 items",
        "choicetwo": "about 30 items",
        "choicethree": "unlimited",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The proprioceptive senses (seat-of-the-pants sense) are important for motor\ncoordination.\nThey",
        "answer": "are completely unreliable for orientation when flying in IMC",
        "choiceone": "indicate the difference between gravity and G-forces",
        "choicetwo": "allow the pilot to determine the absolute vertical at flight condition",
        "choicethree": "are important senses for flight training in IMC",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The so-called \"Seat-of-the-Pants\" sense is",
        "answer": "not suitable for spatial orientation when outside visual references are\nlost",
        "choiceone": "only to be used by experienced pilots with the permission to fly in IMC",
        "choicetwo": "useful for instrument and contact flight",
        "choicethree": "the only sense a pilot can rely on, when flying in IMC",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sensory input to the \"Seat-of-the-Pants\" sense is given by",
        "answer": "subcutaneous pressure receptors and muscle activity sensors",
        "choiceone": "blood rushing into legs",
        "choicetwo": "acceleration of the stomach (nausea)",
        "choicethree": "pressure of the heart on the diaphragm",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying from Frankfurt to Moscow you will have a lay-over of 4 days. What time\nmeasure is relevant for your circadian rhythm on the third day?",
        "answer": "LT (local time).",
        "choiceone": "MEZ (middle european time).",
        "choicetwo": "ZT (zonal time).",
        "choicethree": "UTC (universal time coordinated).",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Orientation in flight is accomplished by\n1. eyes\n2. utriculus and sacculus\n3. semicircular canals\n4. Seat-of-the-pants-Sense",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "only 1 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct , 1 is false",
        "choicethree": " 2, 3 and 4 are false, only 1 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do to optimise his/her night vision (scotopic vision)?",
        "answer": "Not smoke before start and during flight and avoid flash-blindness",
        "choiceone": "Avoid food containing high amounts of vitamin A",
        "choicetwo": "Wait at least 60 minutes to night-adapt before he takes off",
        "choicethree": "Select meals with high contents of vitamin B and C",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference to\ninstruments because:",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low\ncontrast",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \"greying out\" will make it impossible to determine the\nheight above the terrain",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Signs of stress include:",
        "answer": "Perspiration, dry mouth, dilated pupils, fast breathing.",
        "choiceone": "Lowering of the blood pressure.",
        "choicetwo": "Faster, deep inhalation, stabbing pain around the heart.",
        "choicethree": "Rising of the blood pressure, pupils narrowing, stabbing pain around\nthe heart.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense\"",
        "answer": "can give false inputs to body orientation when visual reference is lost",
        "choiceone": "is a natural human instinct which will always indicate the correct body\nposition in space",
        "choicetwo": "can be used, if trained, to avoid disorientation in space",
        "choicethree": "can be used as a reference for determining attitude when operating in\nvisual and instrument meteorological conditions",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A shining light is fading out (i. e. when flying into fog, dust or haze). What kind\nof illusion could the pilot get?",
        "answer": "The source of light moves away from him",
        "choiceone": "The source of light stands still",
        "choicetwo": "The source of light is approaching him with increasing speed",
        "choicethree": "The light source will make the pilot believe, that he is climbing",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is used to land on small and narrow runways only. Approaching a\nlarger and wider runway can lead to:",
        "answer": "an early or high \"round out\"",
        "choiceone": "a steeper than normal approach dropping low",
        "choicetwo": "a flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"",
        "choicethree": "the risk to land short of the overrun",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The impression of an apparent movement of light when stared at for a\nrelatively long period of time in the dark is called",
        "answer": "\"autokinesis\"",
        "choiceone": "\"white out\"",
        "choicetwo": "\"oculogyral illusion\"",
        "choicethree": "\"oculografic illusion\"",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Generally, the time required for dark adaptation is:",
        "answer": "30 min",
        "choiceone": "10 sec",
        "choicetwo": "1/10 sec",
        "choicethree": "10 min",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which problem may occur, when flying in an environment of low contrast (fog,\nsnow, darkness, haze)?\nUnder these conditions it is:",
        "answer": "difficult to estimate the correct speed and size of approaching objects",
        "choiceone": "impossible to detect objects",
        "choicetwo": "no problem to estimate the correct speed and size of approaching\nobjects",
        "choicethree": "unlikely that visual illusions occur",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot approaching an upsloping runway",
        "answer": "may feel that he is higher than actual. This illusion may cause him to\nland short.",
        "choiceone": "is performing a steeper than normal approach, landing long",
        "choicetwo": "establishes a higher than normal approach speed",
        "choicethree": "establishes a slower than normal approach speed with the risk of\nstalling out",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What illusion may occur if an aircraft is flying into fog, snow or haze?",
        "answer": "Objects seem to be farther away than in reality",
        "choiceone": "Objects will appear closer than they really are",
        "choicetwo": "Objects will appear bigger in size than in reality",
        "choicethree": "Objects seem to move slower than in reality",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Adaptation is",
        "answer": "the adjustment of the eyes to high or low levels of illumination",
        "choiceone": "the change of the diameter of the pupil",
        "choicetwo": "the reflection of the light at the cornea",
        "choicethree": "the adjustment of the crystalline lens to focus light on the retina",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time required for complete adaptation is",
        "answer": "for high levels of illumination 10 sec and for full dark adaptation 30 min",
        "choiceone": "for high levels of illumination 10 minutes and for low levels of\nillumination 30 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "for day and night: 30 min",
        "choicethree": "for night 10 sec and for day 30 min",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The requirement of good sunglasses is to",
        "answer": "absorb enough visible light to eliminate glare without decreasing visual\nacuity",
        "choiceone": "fit to the pilots individual taste",
        "choicetwo": "eliminate distortion in aircraft windshields",
        "choicethree": "increase the time for dark adaptation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Scanning at night should be performed by:",
        "answer": "slight eye movements to the side of the object",
        "choiceone": "scanning with one eye open",
        "choicetwo": "concentrated fixation on an object (image must fall on the fovea)",
        "choicethree": "avoiding food containing Vitamin A",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot accustomed to landing on a wide runway may find, when approaching\nto a narrow runway, that he/she is at a:",
        "answer": "greater height than he actually is with the tendency to land short",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual height with the tendency to overshoot",
        "choicetwo": "greater height and the impression of landing short",
        "choicethree": "lower height and the impression of landing slow",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flickering light when reflected from spinning rotor blades",
        "answer": "can cause spatial disorientation and/or nausea",
        "choiceone": "has no effect",
        "choicetwo": "can be avoided when the strobe-lights are switched on",
        "choicethree": "should be avoided, because it may destroy the optic nerve",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, even when taken in minor quantities",
        "answer": "can make the brain cells to be more susceptible to hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "will stimulate the brain, making the pilot resistant to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "will have no effect at all",
        "choicethree": "may improve the mental functions, so that the symptoms of hypoxia are\nmuch better to be identified",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot approaching a runway which is narrower than normal may feel he is at\na greater height than he actually is. To compensate he may fly a",
        "answer": "flatter than normal approach with the tendency to undershoot",
        "choiceone": "compensatory glide path and land long",
        "choicetwo": "compensatory glide path and stall out",
        "choicethree": "higher than normal approach with the tendency to overshoot",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The proprioceptive senses (\"Seat of-the-Pants-Sense\")",
        "answer": "give incorrect information, when outside visual reference is lost",
        "choiceone": "is a natural human instinct, always indicating the correct attitude",
        "choicetwo": "can be used, if trained, to avoid spatial disorientation in IMC",
        "choicethree": "can neither be used for motor coordination in IMC and VMC",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When assessing an individual's risk of developing coronary artery disease,\nthe following factors may contribute:\n1.obesity\n2.chronic stress\n3.smoking\n4.family history",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 and 4 are false",
        "choicetwo": "Only 3 is correct, 1, 2 and 4 are false",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Resonance of the body parts can result from:",
        "answer": "vibrations from 1 to 100 Hz",
        "choiceone": "vibrations from 16 Hz to 18 kHz",
        "choicetwo": "acceleration along the longitudinal body axis",
        "choicethree": "angular velocity",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia will effect night vision",
        "answer": "at approximately 5000 FT",
        "choiceone": "less than day vision",
        "choicetwo": "and causes the autokinetic phenomena",
        "choicethree": "and causes hyperventilation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress management programmes usually involve:",
        "answer": "the prevention and/or the removal of stress",
        "choiceone": "only the removal of stress",
        "choicetwo": "only the prevention of stress",
        "choicethree": "the use of psychoactive drugs",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The metabolisation of alcohol",
        "answer": "is a question of time",
        "choiceone": "is accelerated by consuming alcohol with a meal",
        "choicetwo": "can be accelerated even more by coffee",
        "choicethree": "can be influenced by easily obtained medication",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does not impair the function of the photosensitive cells?",
        "answer": "High speed",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen deficiency",
        "choicetwo": "Acceleration",
        "choicethree": "Toxic influence (alcohol, nicotine, medication)",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The fovea is",
        "answer": "the area of best day vision and no night vision at all",
        "choiceone": "the area of the blind spot (optic disc)",
        "choicetwo": "where the optic nerves come together with the pupil",
        "choicethree": "the area of best day vision and best night vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to completely resynchronise with local time after zone crossing,\ncircadian rhythms require",
        "answer": "less time when flying from east to west",
        "choiceone": "more time when flying from east to west",
        "choicetwo": "about one day per 2.5 hours of time shift",
        "choicethree": "about one week per 2.5 hours of time shift",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina of the eye",
        "answer": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the\nphotoreceptors essential for vision",
        "choiceone": "filters the UV-light",
        "choicetwo": "is the muscle, changing the size of the crystalline lens",
        "choicethree": "only regulates the light that falls into the eye",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Eustachian tube is the passage way between the",
        "answer": "throat and the middle ear",
        "choiceone": "nose, throat and inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "nose, throat and the external auditory canal",
        "choicethree": "sinuses and the throat",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which force(s) affect(s) the otoliths in the utriculus and sacculus?",
        "answer": "Gravity and linear acceleration",
        "choiceone": "Gravity alone",
        "choicetwo": "Linear acceleration and angular acceleration",
        "choicethree": "Angular acceleration",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The semicircular canals of the inner ear monitor",
        "answer": "angular accelerations",
        "choiceone": "movements with constant speeds",
        "choicetwo": "relative speed and linear accelerations",
        "choicethree": "gravity",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the ear could be affected by air pressure changes during climb\nand/or descent?",
        "answer": "The Eustachian tube and the tympanic membrane (ear drum)",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals",
        "choicetwo": "The cochlea",
        "choicethree": "The saccules and utricles",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?",
        "answer": "The cochlea",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the vestibular apparatus is affected by changes in gravity and\nlinear acceleration?",
        "answer": "The sacculus and utriculus",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals",
        "choicetwo": "The cochlea",
        "choicethree": "The eustachian tube",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the vestibular apparatus is responsible for the detection of\nangular acceleration?",
        "answer": "The semicircular canals",
        "choiceone": "The cochlea",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The vestibular apparatus",
        "answer": "reacts to linear/angular acceleration and gravity",
        "choiceone": "gives the impression of hearing",
        "choicetwo": "reacts to pressure changes in the middle ear",
        "choicethree": "reacts to vibrations of the cochlea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the audible range to human hearing?",
        "answer": "Between 20 Hz and 20 KHz",
        "choiceone": "Between 20 MHz and 20 000MHz",
        "choicetwo": "Between 20 KHz and 20 KHz",
        "choicethree": "Between 20 Hz and 20 MHz",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following components belong to the middle ear?",
        "answer": "Ossicles",
        "choiceone": "Otoliths",
        "choicetwo": "Endolymph",
        "choicethree": "Semicircular canals",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equalization of pressure take place,\nwhen altitude is changed?",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Concerning the effects of drugs and pilot\u00b4s performance",
        "answer": "the primary and the side effects have to be considered",
        "choiceone": "the side effects only have to be considered",
        "choicetwo": "medication has no influence on pilot\u00b4s performance",
        "choicethree": "only the primary effect has to be considered; side effects are negligible",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is understood by air-sickness?",
        "answer": "A sensory conflict within the vestibular system accompanied by nausea\nand vomiting",
        "choiceone": "An illness caused by evaporation of gases in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "An illness caused by reduced air pressure",
        "choicethree": "An illness caused by an infection of the middle ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a coordinated level  turn will",
        "answer": "make the body`s pressure receptors feel an increased pressure along\nthe body`s vertical axis",
        "choiceone": " first give the impression of climb , then the impression of descent",
        "choicetwo": "make the blood being pooled in the head",
        "choicethree": "make the seat-of-the-pants sense feel a decreased pressure along the\nbody`s vertical axis",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level\nturn?",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot overcome vertigo, encountered during a real or simulated\ninstrument flight?\n1. Establish and maintain an effective instrument cross-check.\n2. Always believe the instruments; never trust your sense of feeling.\n3. Ignore arising illusions.\n4. Move the head sidewards and back and forth to \"shake-off\" illusions.",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false",
        "choicetwo": "Only 4 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dizziness and tumbling sensations, when making head movements in a tight\nturn, are symptoms of",
        "answer": "\"Pilot`s vertigo\"",
        "choiceone": "\"Nystagmus\"",
        "choicetwo": "\"Flicker-vertigo\"",
        "choicethree": "\"Oculogravic illusion\"",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "\"Pilot's vertigo\"",
        "answer": "is the condition of dizziness and/or tumbling sensation caused by\ncontradictory impulses to the central nervous system (CNS)",
        "choiceone": "is the sensation to keep a rotation after completing a turn",
        "choicetwo": "is the sensation of climbing caused by a strong linear acceleration",
        "choicethree": "announces the beginning of airsickness",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can a pilot do to avoid \"Flicker vertigo\" when flying in the clouds?",
        "answer": "Switch strobe-lights off",
        "choiceone": "Dim the cockpit lights to avoid reflections",
        "choicetwo": "Engage the autopilot until breaking the clouds",
        "choicethree": "Fly straight and level and avoid head movements",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What do you do, when you are affected by \"pilot`s vertigo\"?\n1. Establish and maintain an effective instrument cross-check.\n2. Believe the instruments.\n3. Ignore illusions.\n4. Minimize head movements.",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false",
        "choicethree": "Only 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the correct action to counteract vertigo?",
        "answer": "Believe the instruments",
        "choiceone": "Reduce rate of breathing until all symptoms disappear, then breathe\nagain normally",
        "choicetwo": "Concentrate on the vertical speed indicator",
        "choicethree": "Rely on the information from the semicircular canals, since these will be\ntransmitting correct information",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The risk of spatial disorientation increases when:",
        "answer": "there is contradictory information between the instruments and the\nvestibular organs",
        "choiceone": "the pilot is buckled tightly to his/her seat and cannot sense the attitude\nchanges of the aircraft by the Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense",
        "choicetwo": "the pilot is performing an effective instrument cross-check and is\nignoring illusions",
        "choicethree": "information from the vestibular organ in the inner ear are ignored",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which flight-manoeuvre will most likely induce vertigo? Turning the head\nwhile",
        "answer": "banking",
        "choiceone": "climbing",
        "choicetwo": "descending",
        "choicethree": "flying straight and level",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual reference, what illusion could the pilot get, when he is\nstopping the rotation to recover from a spin? He will get the illusion of",
        "answer": "spinning into the opposite direction",
        "choiceone": "spinning into the same direction",
        "choicetwo": "straight and level flight",
        "choicethree": "climbing and turning into the original direction of the spin",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When accelerating forward the otoliths in the utriculus/sacculus will",
        "answer": "give the illusion of climbing (body tilting backwards, nose of the a/c\ngoing up)",
        "choiceone": "give the illusion of banking",
        "choicetwo": "give the illusion of straight and level flight",
        "choicethree": "give the illusion of descending (body tilting downwards, or forwards,\nnose of the aircraft going down)",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot, accelerating or decelerating in level flight may experience:",
        "answer": "the illusion of climbing or descending",
        "choiceone": "the feeling of rotation",
        "choicetwo": "the illusion to turning",
        "choicethree": "the impression of stationary objects moving to the right or left",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In his/her behaviour, the \"ideal professional pilot\" is:",
        "answer": "both \"person\" and \"goal\" oriented",
        "choiceone": "\"person\" rather than \"goal\" oriented",
        "choicetwo": "neither \"person\" nor \"goal\" oriented",
        "choicethree": "\"goal\" rather than \"person\" oriented",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following symptoms may a pilot experience when subjected to\nhypoxia?\n1. Fatigue.\n2. Euphoria.\n3. Lack of concentration.\n4. Pain in the joints.\n5. Pain in the inner ear",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "4 and 5 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "Only 5 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pilots should not take antihistamines because they may cause:\n1. Drowsiness and dizziness\n2. Hypoglycaemia\n3. Hyperventilation\n4. Flatulence\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "only 1",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The consumption of medicines or other substances may have consequences\non qualification to fly for the following reasons:\n1. The disease requiring a treatment may be cause for disqualification.\n2. Flight conditions may modify the reactions of the body to a treatment.\n3. Drugs may cause adverse side effects impairing flight safety.\n4. The effects of medicine do not necessarily immediately disappear when the\ntreatment is stopped.",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "3 and 4 are false, 1 and 2 are correct.",
        "choicethree": "Only 2 is false.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Vitamin A and possibly vitamins B and C are chemical factors and essential to\ngood night vision:\n1. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease night vision performance\n2. An excess intake of vitamin A will improve night vision performance\nsignificantly\n3. Pilots should be carefully concerned to take a balanced diet containing\nsufficient vitamin A\n4. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease visual acuity in photopic vision but not\nin scotopic vision",
        "answer": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 and 4 are false",
        "choiceone": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "Only 4 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are false, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cigarette smoking has particular significance to the flyer, because there are\nlong-term and short-term harmful effects. From cigarette smoking the pilot\ncan get:",
        "answer": "a mild carbon monoxide poisoning decreasing the pilot\u00b4s tolerance to\nhypoxia",
        "choiceone": "a mild carbon dioxide poisoning increasing the pilot's tolerance to\nhypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "a mild carbon monoxide poisoning increasing the pilot\u00b4s tolerance to\nhypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot who smokes will lose some of his capacity to transport oxygen\ncombined with haemoglobin.\nWhich percentage of his total oxygen transportation capacity would he give\naway when he smokes one pack of cigarettes a day?\n5 - 8%",
        "answer": "20 - 25%",
        "choiceone": "0.5 - 2%",
        "choicetwo": "12 - 18%",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying at pressure altitude of 10 000 ft, a pilot, being a moderate to heavy\nsmoker, has an oxygen content in the blood equal to an altitude",
        "answer": "of 15000 FT when breathing 100% oxygen",
        "choiceone": "above 10 000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "of 10 000 FT",
        "choicethree": "lower than 10 000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following applies when alcohol has been consumed?",
        "answer": "",
        "choiceone": "",
        "choicetwo": "",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may",
        "answer": "intensify the effects of the drugs",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs",
        "choicetwo": "show undesired effects only during night flights",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of alcohol elimination from the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The type of hypoxia, which occurs at altitude is a explained by:",
        "answer": "Dalton\u00b4s law",
        "choiceone": "Boyle Mariotte\u00b4s law",
        "choicetwo": "Henry\u00b4s law",
        "choicethree": "Graham\u00b4s law",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide, a product of incomplete combustion, is toxic because",
        "answer": "it competes with oxygen in its union with haemoglobin",
        "choiceone": "it prevents the absorption of food from the digestive tract",
        "choicetwo": "it prevents the excretion of catabolites in the kidneys",
        "choicethree": "it disturbs gaseous diffusion at the alveoli capillary membrane",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation causes",
        "answer": "a reduction of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choiceone": "an excess of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "acidosis",
        "choicethree": "hypochondria",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety and fear can cause",
        "answer": "hyperventilation",
        "choiceone": "hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "spatial disorientation",
        "choicethree": "hypoglycaemia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the first effects to be noticed on gradual exposure to high positive\nradial accelerations is",
        "answer": "grey-out",
        "choiceone": "loss of consciousness",
        "choicetwo": "black-out",
        "choicethree": "red-vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first stage in the information process is",
        "answer": "sensory stimulation",
        "choiceone": "perception",
        "choicetwo": "selective attention",
        "choicethree": "the recognition of information",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent vertigo in flight we should",
        "answer": "not move the head suddenly while we are turning",
        "choiceone": "look towards the sides when we make a turn",
        "choicetwo": "breath deeply but control the respiratory frequency",
        "choicethree": "keep breathing normally",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying at night the first sense to be affected by a slight degree of\nhypoxia is the",
        "answer": "vision",
        "choiceone": "cochlea",
        "choicetwo": "sense of balance",
        "choicethree": "proprioceptive sensitivity",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The carcinogen (a substance with the ability to produce modifications in cells\nwhich develop a cancer) in cigarettes is",
        "answer": "tar",
        "choiceone": "nicotine",
        "choicetwo": "carbon monoxide",
        "choicethree": "lead",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the substances present in the smoke of cigarettes can make it\nsignificantly more difficult for the red blood cells to transport oxygen and as a\nconsequence contributes to hypoxia. Which substance are we referring to?",
        "answer": "Carbon monoxide",
        "choiceone": "Carbonic anhydride",
        "choicetwo": "Tar",
        "choicethree": "Carbon dioxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The group of tiny bones (the hammer, anvil and stirrup) are situated in",
        "answer": "the middle ear",
        "choiceone": "the inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "the outer ear",
        "choicethree": "the maxillary sinus",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The semicircular canals form part of the",
        "answer": "inner ear",
        "choiceone": "middle ear",
        "choicetwo": "ear drum",
        "choicethree": "external ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is inadvisable to fly when suffering from a cold. The reason for this is:",
        "answer": "pain and damage to the eardrum can result, particularly during fast\ndescents",
        "choiceone": "gentle descents at high altitude can result in damage to the ear drum",
        "choicetwo": "swollen tissue in the inner ear will prevent the air from ventilating\nthrough the tympanic membrane",
        "choicethree": "swollen tissue in the Eustachian tube will cause permanent hearing loss",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The so-called Coriolis effect (a conflict in information processing in the brain)\nin spatial disorientation occurs:",
        "answer": "on stimulating several semicircular canals simultaneously",
        "choiceone": "on stimulating the saccule and the utricle of the inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "on stimulating the cochlea intensely",
        "choicethree": "when no semicircular canal is stimulated",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When stopping the rotation of a spin we have the sensation",
        "answer": "that we are starting a spin in the opposite direction",
        "choiceone": "of turning in the same direction",
        "choicetwo": "of the sharp dipping of the nose of the aircraft",
        "choicethree": "of the immediate stabilization of the aircraft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When accelerating in level flight we could experience the sensation of a",
        "answer": "climb",
        "choiceone": "descent",
        "choicetwo": "turn",
        "choicethree": "spin",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result in:",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbycusis results in:",
        "answer": "reduction in the perception of high tones first",
        "choiceone": "reduction in the perception of low tones first",
        "choicetwo": "reduction in the perception of all tones equally",
        "choicethree": "will not affect a pilot's hearing if he/she is wearing ear-plugs all the time",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The human ear is capable of perceiving vibrations between the frequencies",
        "answer": "16 - 20000 Hz",
        "choiceone": "0 - 16 Hz",
        "choicetwo": "20000 - 40000 Hz",
        "choicethree": "30 - 15000 dB",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The intensity of a sound is measured in",
        "answer": "decibels",
        "choiceone": "hertz",
        "choicetwo": "cycles per second",
        "choicethree": "curies",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ozone-layer is situated in the",
        "answer": "stratosphere",
        "choiceone": "troposphere",
        "choicetwo": "thermosphere",
        "choicethree": "ionosphere",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The barometric pressure has dropped to 1/2 of the pressure at sea level at",
        "answer": "18 000 feet",
        "choiceone": "10 000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "25 000 feet",
        "choicethree": "30 000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following laws explains bubbles of nitrogen coming out of\nsolution in body tissues due to a decrease in atmospheric pressure?",
        "answer": "Henry's law",
        "choiceone": "Boyle's law",
        "choicetwo": "Dalton's law",
        "choicethree": "Gay Lussac's law",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal rate of breathing when at rest is",
        "answer": "12 to 20 cycles a minute",
        "choiceone": "25 to 30 cycles a minute",
        "choicetwo": "32 to 40 cycles a minute",
        "choicethree": "60 to 100 cycles a minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main function of the red blood cells is",
        "answer": "to transport oxygen",
        "choiceone": "to participate in the process of coagulation of the blood",
        "choicetwo": "the cellular defence of the organism",
        "choicethree": "to contribute to the immune response of the organism",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Altitude-hypoxia, when breathing ambient air, should not usually occur\n(indifferent phase)",
        "answer": "below 3 000 m",
        "choiceone": "up to 5 000 m",
        "choicetwo": "between 3 000 m and 5 000 m",
        "choicethree": "between 5 000 m and 7 000 m",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "\"The Bends\" as a symptom of decompression sickness consists of:",
        "answer": "pain in the joints",
        "choiceone": "pain in the thorax and a cough",
        "choicetwo": "CNS-disturbances",
        "choicethree": "loss of peripheral vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The primary symptom of Decompression sickness/illness is:",
        "answer": "the Bends",
        "choiceone": "the Chokes",
        "choicetwo": "red coloured cheeks and lips",
        "choicethree": "neurological damages to the CNS",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The part(s) of the eye responsible for night vision",
        "answer": "are the rods",
        "choiceone": "are the cones",
        "choicetwo": "are rods and cones",
        "choicethree": "is the cornea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The fovea",
        "answer": "is an area in which cones predominate",
        "choiceone": "is sensitive to very low intensities of light",
        "choicetwo": "is an area in which rods predominate",
        "choicethree": "is the area responsible for night vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the optical image forms in front of the retina; this results in:",
        "answer": "myopia",
        "choiceone": "hypermetropia",
        "choicetwo": "presbyopia",
        "choicethree": "astigmatism",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Within communication, what element suggests that a message has been\nreceived and understood ?",
        "answer": "Feedback.",
        "choiceone": "Coding.",
        "choicetwo": "Synchronization.",
        "choicethree": "Encoding.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The process of responding to a sender by confirming the reception of a\nmessage is called",
        "answer": "feedback",
        "choiceone": "redundancy",
        "choicetwo": "synchronization",
        "choicethree": "transference",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During paradoxical sleep",
        "answer": "rapid eye movements can be observed",
        "choiceone": "physical restoration and recuperation takes place",
        "choicetwo": "respiration is very regular",
        "choicethree": "the rhythm of the heart is very regular",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motor programmes are:",
        "answer": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed without\ncontinuous conscious control",
        "choiceone": "rules that enable us to deal with novel situations",
        "choicetwo": "rules that enable us to deal with preconceived situations",
        "choicethree": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed only\nunder continuous conscious control",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The relationship between arousal and flying performance is",
        "answer": "approximately the form of an inverted U",
        "choiceone": "approximately linear increasing",
        "choicetwo": "approximately exponential",
        "choicethree": "approximately sinusoidal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a complex task high levels of arousal",
        "answer": "narrow the span of attention",
        "choiceone": "improve performance",
        "choicetwo": "lead to better decision-making",
        "choicethree": "reduce failures",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the short-term-memory, information is stored for approximately",
        "answer": "20 seconds",
        "choiceone": "5 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "1 hour",
        "choicethree": "a couple of days",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 'cocktail party effect' is",
        "answer": "the ability to pick up relevant information unintentionally",
        "choiceone": "the ability to drink too much at social gathering",
        "choicetwo": "the tendency to believe information that reinforces our mental model of\nthe world",
        "choicethree": "the tendency not to perceive relevant information",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Once we have constructed a mental model we tend",
        "answer": "to give undue weight to information that confirms the model",
        "choiceone": "to give undue weight to information that contradicts the model",
        "choicetwo": "to give equal weight to contradicting and confirming information",
        "choicethree": "to alter that model unnecessarily frequently",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Very high ambition and need for achievement",
        "answer": "disturb the climate of cooperation",
        "choiceone": "fulfil the requirements of stress resistance",
        "choicetwo": "always promote teamwork",
        "choicethree": "improves the coping process with personal failures",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Our mental model of the world is based",
        "answer": "on both our past experiences and the sensory information we receive",
        "choiceone": "entirely on the sensory information we receive",
        "choicetwo": "entirely on past experiences",
        "choicethree": "on both our past experiences and our motor programmes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following tasks are possible to do simultaneously without\nmutual interference?",
        "answer": "Maintain manual straight and level flight and solve a problem.",
        "choiceone": "Listen attentively and solve a problem.",
        "choicetwo": "Talk and rehearse a frequency in working memory.",
        "choicethree": "Read and listen attentively.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A copilot has passed an upgrading course to become a captain. Which\npsychological consequence is most likely?",
        "answer": "His/her self-concept is going to change because of new roles and tasks\nwhich have to be incorporated.",
        "choiceone": "His/her self -concept is going to be stabilized because of the higher\nstatus as a captain.",
        "choicetwo": "The increased command authority leads to a higher professionalism.",
        "choicethree": "An upgrading never has psychological consequences.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cognitive and physical rehearsal of actions during training:",
        "answer": "is most important for the acquisition of complex perceptual motor skills",
        "choiceone": "is most important for self-control",
        "choicetwo": "leads to an increased error rate",
        "choicethree": "is more effective than practical training",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot avoid automation complacency?",
        "answer": "Regard the automatic system as additional crew members that needs to\nbe crosschecked as well",
        "choiceone": "Always try to enhance your aviation related knowledge during low\nworkload periods",
        "choicetwo": "Always fly the whole flight manually to remain in man-machine loop",
        "choicethree": "Nothing, because it is system-inherent",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can the process of learning be enhanced?",
        "answer": "By reinforcing successful performance",
        "choiceone": "By increasing the psychological pressure on the student",
        "choicetwo": "By punishing the learner for unsuccessful trials",
        "choicethree": "By reinforcing errors",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mental rehearsal is helpful to improve flying skills",
        "answer": "at all levels of flying proficiency",
        "choiceone": "only for student pilots",
        "choicetwo": "only for instructor pilots",
        "choicethree": "only at a certain level of flying experience",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by the term 'complacency'?",
        "answer": "Unjustified self-confidence",
        "choiceone": "To question possible solutions",
        "choicetwo": "An agreement between captain and co-pilot due to Crew Resources\nManagement",
        "choicethree": "Physiological effects on pilots because of fear of flying",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "'Environmental capture' is a term used to describe which of the following\nstatements?\n1.The tendency for a skill to be executed in an environment in which it is\nfrequently exercised\n2.The tendency for a skill acquired in one aircraft type to be executed in a new\naircraft type, even if it is inappropriate to do so\n3. The tendency for people to behave in different ways in different social\nsituations\n4. The gaining of environmental skills",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "4 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A high degree of cockpit automation may alter the traditional tasks of the\npilots in a way, that",
        "answer": "the attention of the cockpit crew will become reduced as a consequence\nof 'being out of the loop'",
        "choiceone": "it is guaranteed that the crew always maintains situational awareness",
        "choicetwo": "Crew Coordination can be neglected on long haul flights without\ncompromising safety",
        "choicethree": "the crew can pay more attention to problem-solving in an abnormal\nsituation without monitoring the automatic systems",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is desirable to standardize as many patterns of behaviour (operating\nprocedures) as possible in commercial aviation mainly because",
        "answer": "such behaviour reduces errors even under adverse circumstances",
        "choiceone": "this lowers the ability requirement in pilot selection",
        "choicetwo": "this reduces the amount of training required",
        "choicethree": "it makes the flight deck easier to design",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot is facing a problem during flight he should",
        "answer": "take as much time as he needs and is available to make up his mind",
        "choiceone": "always make up his mind quickly to give himself as much spare time as\npossible",
        "choicetwo": "avoid making up his mind until the very last minute",
        "choicethree": "make up his mind before consulting other crew members",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The decision making in emergency situations requires firstly:",
        "answer": "delegation of tasks and crew coordination",
        "choiceone": "speed of reaction",
        "choicetwo": "informing ATC thoroughly about the situation",
        "choicethree": "the whole crew to focus on the problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The assessment of risk in a particular situation will be based on",
        "answer": "subjective perception and evaluation of situational factors",
        "choiceone": "external factors only",
        "choicetwo": "the emergency checklist only",
        "choicethree": "situational factors only",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Once a pilot has developed a certain way of thinking about a problem he will\nprobably",
        "answer": "find it difficult to get out of that way of thinking and difficult to try a\ndifferent interpretation of the data",
        "choiceone": "find it difficult to stick to his/her interpretation of the data",
        "choicetwo": "find it easy to interpret the data in different ways",
        "choicethree": "find it impossible to get out of that way of thinking, whatever happens",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To maintain good situational awareness you should:\n(1) believe only in your own interpretation of the data\n(2) gather as much data as possible from every possible source before\nmaking inferences\n(3) question whether your hypothesis still fits the situation as events progress\nand try to make time to review the situation\n(4) consider ways of testing your situational hypothesis to see whether it is\ncorrect",
        "answer": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "all answers are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Doing a general briefing in the pre-flight phase the captain should emphasize",
        "answer": "particular requirements in the field of crew coordination and\nco-operation",
        "choiceone": "complete delegation of all duties",
        "choicetwo": "departure on schedule",
        "choicethree": "avoidance inadequate handling of flight controls",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the pre-flight phase in the cockpit the captain notices that his copilot\non the one hand is rather inexperienced and insecure but on the other hand\nhighly motivated. Which kind of leadership behaviouris is most appropriate?",
        "answer": "The captain lets the copilot fly and observes his behaviour without any\ncomments",
        "choiceone": "The captain flies the first leg by himself and explains each action to the\ncopilot in order to keep him informed about his decisions",
        "choicetwo": "The captain lets the copilot fly and gives him detailed instructions what\nto do",
        "choicethree": "The captain lets the copilot fly and encourages him to ask for support",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A leader who demonstrates a democratic and co-operative style will deal with\nconflict by:",
        "answer": "trying to clarify the reasons and causes of the conflict with all persons\ninvolved",
        "choiceone": "trying to reconcile all persons involved in the conflict and tries to\nre-establish a pleasant and friendly atmosphere within the team",
        "choicetwo": "keeping a neutral position and does not participate in arguing",
        "choicethree": "deciding what to do and pushes his own opinion through",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Informal roles within a crew",
        "answer": "evolve as a result of the interactions that take place among crew\nmembers",
        "choiceone": "are explicitly set out by the crew",
        "choicetwo": "will always impair the captain's influence",
        "choicethree": "characterize inefficient crews",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which behaviour is most likely to promote a constructive solution of\ninterpersonal conflicts?",
        "answer": "Active listening.",
        "choiceone": "Responding with counter-arguments.",
        "choicetwo": "Staying to the own point of view.",
        "choicethree": "Giving up the own point of view.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The team spirit of a cockpit-crew most likely depends on",
        "answer": "both pilots respecting each other and striving for the same goals",
        "choiceone": "both pilots wearing the same uniform",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots flying together very often for a long period",
        "choicethree": "both pilots having the same political and ideological attitude",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the cruising phase of a short-haul flight the captain starts to smoke a\ncigarette in the cockpit. The flying copilot asks him to stop smoking because\nhe is a non-smoker. The captain tells him: 'This is your problem', and\ncontinues smoking. What should the copilot do?",
        "answer": "He should not further discuss this issue but should come back to this\nconflict during the debriefing",
        "choiceone": "He should learn to accept the captain smoking cigarettes in the cockpit",
        "choicetwo": "He should repeat his worries about smoking in the cockpit and should\nargue with the captain about this problem until the conflict is solved",
        "choicethree": "He should bring a cabin crew member in to arbitrate",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How would you describe the leadership style of a captain who primarily is\ninterested in a friendly atmosphere within his crew, who is always\nconstructive and encouraging, who usually compromises in interpersonal\nconflicts, who trusts in the capabilities of his crew-members, and who leaves\nthe crew freedom for own decisions?",
        "answer": "Low task-orientation and high relationship-orientation",
        "choiceone": "High task-orientation and low relationship-orientation",
        "choicetwo": "High task-orientation and high relationship-orientation",
        "choicethree": "Low task-orientation and low relationship-orientation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If the co-pilot continuously feels unfairly treated by the Captain, he/she\nshould:",
        "answer": "point out the problem, concentrate on his/her duties and clarify the\nmatter at a more appropriate time",
        "choiceone": "freeze the communication and thus avoid immediate confrontation",
        "choicetwo": "speak up and point out the possible consequences if the unfair\nbehaviour pesists",
        "choicethree": "internally retire and think positive",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely\nto hamper the communication process.",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents\nor accidents.",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be\naddressed until the end of the flight.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Metacommunication is defined as",
        "answer": "those tools, other than the actual words, which compliment those words\nin order to communicate",
        "choiceone": "balancing the own ideas and interests with those of the receiver",
        "choicetwo": "having an assessment conversation",
        "choicethree": "active listening",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mark the two most important attributes for a positive leadership style:\n1. dominant behaviour\n2. excellent role-behaviour\n3. mastery of communication skills\n4. \"Laissez-faire\" behaviour",
        "answer": "2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nonverbal communication",
        "answer": "supports verbal communication",
        "choiceone": "is of no meaning in the cockpit",
        "choicetwo": "is always used intentionally",
        "choicethree": "should be avoided by all means in the cockpit",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How do you understand the statement 'one cannot not communicate'?",
        "answer": "Being silent as well as inactive are nonverbal behaviour patterns which\nexpress a meaning.",
        "choiceone": "No meaningful communication can occur unless it is by verbal means.",
        "choicetwo": "You cannot influence your own communication.",
        "choicethree": "Communication is always possible.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Discussing private matters in the cockpit",
        "answer": "can improve team spirit",
        "choiceone": "should be avoided by all means in the cockpit",
        "choicetwo": "is appropriate in any phase of flight",
        "choicethree": "decreases the captains role of leadership",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss is influenced by",
        "answer": "the duration and intensity of a noise",
        "choiceone": "the duration of a noise but not its intensity",
        "choicetwo": "the suddenness of onset of a noise",
        "choicethree": "the intensity of the noise but not its duration",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to reduce the risk of coronary artery disease, exercise should:",
        "answer": "double the resting heart rate for at least 20 minutes, three times a week",
        "choiceone": "be avoided since raising the heart rate shortens the life of the heart",
        "choicetwo": "double the resting heart rate for at least an hour, five times a week",
        "choicethree": "triple the resting heart rate for 20 minutes, once a week",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is most true?",
        "answer": "Regular exercise is beneficial to general health, but the most efficient\nway to lose weight is by reducing calorie consumption",
        "choiceone": "Regular exercise is an impediment to losing weight since it increases\nthe metabolic rate",
        "choicetwo": "Regular exercise is beneficial to general health, and is the only effective\nway to lose weight",
        "choicethree": "Regular exercise and reduction in calorie consumption are both\nessential in order to lose weight",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchronise to\nthis new time zone at a rate of about",
        "answer": "1 - 1.5 hours a day",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day",
        "choicethree": "4 - 4.5 hours a day",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The duration of a period of sleep is governed primarily by",
        "answer": "the point within your circadian rhythm at which you try to sleep",
        "choiceone": "the duration of your previous sleep",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of time you have been awake",
        "choicethree": "the number of points you have in your 'credit/deficit' system",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A selective attentional mechanism is required",
        "answer": "because of the limited capacity of the central decision maker and\nworking memory",
        "choiceone": "because the capacity of the long term memory is limited",
        "choicetwo": "because of the limitations of the sense organs",
        "choicethree": "because of limitations in our store of motor programmes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory:",
        "answer": "is sensitive to interruptions which may erase all or some of its contents",
        "choiceone": "is unlimited in size",
        "choicetwo": "is unlimited in duration",
        "choicethree": "varies considerably in size between an expert pilot and a novice pilot",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motivation is an important attribute which contributes to flight safety. Which\nof the following statements is correct with regards to motivation?",
        "answer": "Excessive motivation leads to stress which adversely affects\nperformance",
        "choiceone": "Motivation reduces the intensity of sensory illusions",
        "choicetwo": "A high degree of motivation makes it possible to make up for insufficient\nknowledge in complete safety",
        "choicethree": "A high degree of motivation lowers the level of vigilance",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding decision making?",
        "answer": "Deciding means choosing between alternatives.",
        "choiceone": "Deciding means being able to come up with original solutions.",
        "choicetwo": "Deciding means imposing one's point of view.",
        "choicethree": "Deciding means applying an automatic procedure.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human errors are frequent and may take several forms:",
        "answer": "an error can be described as the mismatch between the pilots intention\nand the result of his/her actions",
        "choiceone": "all errors are avoidable through continuous and thorough training",
        "choicetwo": "a violation is an error which is always involuntary",
        "choicethree": "representational errors in which the pilot has properly identified the\nsituation and is familiar with the procedure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The quality of learning:",
        "answer": "is promoted by feedback on the value of one's own performance",
        "choiceone": "depends on long-term memory capacity",
        "choicetwo": "is independent of the level of motivation",
        "choicethree": "is dependent on age and professional role",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a cause of accidents, the human factor",
        "answer": "is cited in approximately 70 - 80 % of aviation accidents",
        "choiceone": "has increased considerably since 1980 - the percentage of accident in\nwhich this factor has been involved has more than tripled since this date",
        "choicetwo": "which is cited in current statistics, applies to the flight crew and ATC\nonly",
        "choicethree": "plays a negligible role in commercial aviation accidents. It is much more\nimportant in general aviation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Less experienced pilots differ from experienced pilots in the following way:",
        "answer": "inexperienced pilots refer to information more than experts when\ncarrying out the same task",
        "choiceone": "experienced pilots are less routine-minded than young pilots because\nthey know that routine causes mistakes",
        "choicetwo": "task for task, an expert's workload is greater than a novice's one",
        "choicethree": "flight planning performance decreases with age, and experience is\nunable to mask this deficiency",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Analysis of accidents involving the human factor in aviation shows that:",
        "answer": "there is hardly ever a single cause responsible",
        "choiceone": "only front-line operators are involved",
        "choicetwo": "only pilot training will make it possible to improve the situation",
        "choicethree": "failure of the human factor is always connected with technical\nbreakdowns",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Thinking on human reliability is changing.",
        "answer": "Human errors are now considered as being inevitable",
        "choiceone": "Human errors can be avoided. All it takes is to be vigilant and to extend\none's knowledge",
        "choicetwo": "The individual view of safety has gradually replaced the systemic view of\nsafety",
        "choicethree": "It is thought that it will be possible to eliminate errors in the near future",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning communication is valid?",
        "answer": "Professional communication means: using a restricted and specific\nlanguage, tailored to minimize misunderstandings.",
        "choiceone": "Professional communication means to exchange information as little as\npossible.",
        "choicetwo": "Word order is of little importance to its success. Only the words uttered\nare important.",
        "choicethree": "Communication must take priority over any other flight activity under all\ncircumstances",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
        "answer": "Stressors accumulate thus increasing the likelihood of exhaustion.",
        "choiceone": "Stressors are independent from each other.",
        "choicetwo": "Stress should always be avoided under any circumstances.",
        "choicethree": "People are capable of living without stress.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In case of in-flight stress, one should:",
        "answer": "use all available resources of the crew",
        "choiceone": "only trust in oneself; being sure to know the own limits",
        "choicetwo": "demonstrate aggressiveness to stimulate the crew",
        "choicethree": "always carry out a breathing exercise",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n-1: manifestation of aggressiveness.\n-2: a willingness to improve communication.\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The cognitive effects of stress may include:\n-1: excessive haste.\n-2: an improvement in memory.\n-3: a complete block: action is impossible.\n-4: a risk of focusing on a particular aspect.\n-5: ease of decision-making.\n-6: an increase in the rate of mistakes.\nThe combination which brings together all correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1,3,4,6",
        "choiceone": "1,2,5",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,5,6",
        "choicethree": "3,4,5",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the effect of stress on performance ?\n-1: It always reduces performance.\n-2: Optimum performance is obtained with optimum arousal.\n-3: Excessive stress weakens performance.\n-4: Insufficient stress weakens performance.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "1,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the characteristics of the alarm phase of the stress reactions?\n-1: increased arousal level as a result of adrenaline secretion.\n-2: an increase in heart rate, respiration and release of glucose.\n-3: a decrease in stress resistance.\n-4: activation of the digestive system.\n-5: secretion of cortisol to mobilize attention.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "2,4,5",
        "choicethree": "1,3,5",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the three phases of General Adaptation Syndrome ?",
        "answer": "Alarm, resistance, exhaustion.",
        "choiceone": "Alert, resistance, performance.",
        "choicetwo": "alarm, resistance, performance,",
        "choicethree": "alert, resistance, exhaustion",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress occurs:\n-1: only in a situation of imminent danger.\n-2: only when faced with real, existing and actual situation.\n-3: sometimes via imagination, the anticipation of a situation or its outcome.\n-4: because of the similarity with a formerly experienced stressful situation\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cognitive evaluation which leads to stress is based on:",
        "answer": "the evaluation of the situation and the evaluation of capabilities to cope\nwith it",
        "choiceone": "the evaluation of the situation and the state of fatigue of the individual",
        "choicetwo": "the evaluation of the capabilities of the individual and the time available",
        "choicethree": "the capabilities of the individual and the solutions provided by the\nenvironment",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following physical stimuli may cause stress reactions?\n-1: noise.\n-2: conflict.\n-3: temperature.\n-4: an administrative problem.\n-5: hunger.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1,3,5",
        "choiceone": "1,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "3,4,5",
        "choicethree": "2,3,5",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Acute stress quickly leads to",
        "answer": "the mobilization of resources required to cope with the stressor",
        "choiceone": "a decrease in the amount of resources mobilized to face the situation",
        "choicetwo": "a permanent state of incapacitation",
        "choicethree": "a state of overactivation beyond the control of willpower",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress may be defined as:",
        "answer": "a normal phenomenon which enables an individual to adapt to\nencountered situations",
        "choiceone": "a poorly controlled emotion which leads to a reduction in capabilities",
        "choicetwo": "a psychological phenomenon which only affects fragile personalities",
        "choicethree": "a human reaction which one must manage to eliminate",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is a stressor?",
        "answer": "An external or internal stimulus which is interpreted by an individual as\nbeing stressful",
        "choiceone": "All external stimuli are stressors since they modify the internal\nequilibrium",
        "choicetwo": "A psychological problem developed in a situation of danger",
        "choicethree": "The adaptation response of the individual to his environment",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What may trigger stress in humans?",
        "answer": "The subjective interpretation an individual gives to a situation\nexperienced",
        "choiceone": "Only objective stimulation from environmental factors",
        "choicetwo": "Only strong stimulation of the sensory organs: a flash of light, noise and\nthe smell of smoke",
        "choicethree": "Always the reaction to upsetting emotions caused either by\nphysiological or psychological conditions",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the average influence of age on pilot performance, it may be\nsaid that age:",
        "answer": "has little impact since normally the pilot is able to compensate for it by\nhis/her flight experience",
        "choiceone": "sharply reduces performance without, however, affecting cognitive\ncapabilities",
        "choicetwo": "has a major impact owing to the impairment of memory",
        "choicethree": "increases in impact as speed of thought and memory deteriorate",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following statements, which apply to coordinated cooperation?\n-1: It allows for synergy in the actions between the captain and the co-pilot.\n-2: It represents the simultaneous execution of a single action by the various\nmembers of the crew.\n-3: Communication here results in synchronised actions and the natural and\neasy distribution of responsibilities.\n-4: Communication is centred around the outside world.\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements?",
        "answer": "1 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Coaction is a mode of coordination which recommends:",
        "answer": "working in parallel to achieve one common objective",
        "choiceone": "working parallel to achieve individual objectives",
        "choicetwo": "sustained cooperation on actions and the formulation of commitments\nconcerning flight situations",
        "choicethree": "the application of procedural knowledge in the conduct of specific\nactions",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to make communication effective, it is necessary to:\n-1: avoid the synchronization of verbal and non-verbal channels.\n-2: send information in line with the receiver's decoding abilities.\n-3: always concentrate on the informational aspects of the message only.\n-4: avoid increasing the number of communication channels, in order to\nsimplify communication.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "only 2 is correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements regarding interpersonal interactions are\ncorrect?\n-1 If the sender perceives that the receiver is incompetent, he/she will\nincrease the length of the message\n-2 If the receiver is of non-native tongue, the sender will reinforce what he is\nsaying by using more complicated words so as to optimize understanding\n-3 If the sender considers the receiver incompetent, he/she tends to simplify\nthe content of the sentences\n-4 It is much safer to fly with a crew who know each other well because\ncommunication will always be excellent.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "3 only is correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Professional languages have certain characteristics, for example:\n-1: They use a limited vocabulary .\n-2: They are rich and adapted to the context, which sometimes lead to\nambiguities.\n-3: Their grammar is rather complicated and complex.\n-4: Context provides meaning and therefore reduces the risk of ambiguities.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "only 4 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to communication in a cockpit, we can say that:",
        "answer": "communication uses up resources, thus limiting the resources allocated\nto work in progress",
        "choiceone": "communication is always sufficiently automated to enable an activity\nwith a high workload element to be carried out at the same time",
        "choicetwo": "communication is only effective if messages are kept short and\nsufficiently precise to limit their number",
        "choicethree": "all the characteristics of communication, namely output, duration,\nprecision, clarity, etc. are stable and are not much affected by changes\nin workload",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the communication qualities of a good briefing?\nA good briefing must:\n-1: contain as much information and be as comprehensive as possible.\n-2: be of a standard type so that it can be reused for another flight of the same\ntype.\n-3: be short and precise.\n-4: be understandable to the other crew member(s).\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning check list is correct?",
        "answer": "The most important items should be placed at the beginning of a check\nlist since attention is usually focused here",
        "choiceone": "The most important items must be placed at the end of check list,\nallowing them to be kept near at hand so that they are quickly available\nfor any supplementary check",
        "choicetwo": "The most important items must be placed in the middle of check list so\nthat they come to be examined once attention is focused but before\nconcentration starts to wane",
        "choicethree": "All the items of a check list are equally important; their sequence is of\nno importance",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct with regard to the design of a\ncheck list?\n-1: The longer a check list, the more it must be subdivided into logical parts.\n-2: The trickiest points must be placed in the middle of the check list.\n-3: Check lists must be designed in such a way that they can be lumped\ntogether with other tasks.\n-4: Whenever possible, a panel scan sequence should be applied.\n-5: Use should be made of upper case/\"bold\"/italics/colour with care to\nemphasize critical items or points.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1, 4 and 5 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 5 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 5 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The use of check lists should be carried out in such a way that:",
        "answer": "their execution should not be done simultaneously with other actions",
        "choiceone": "their execution may be done simultaneously with other actions",
        "choicetwo": "their execution should be combined with other important tasks",
        "choicethree": "they should only be carried out when time is available",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors in rule-based control mode are of\nthe following type(s):",
        "answer": "errors of technical knowledge",
        "choiceone": "routine errors",
        "choicetwo": "handling errors",
        "choicethree": "creative errors",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors are of the following type(s) in\nskill-based behaviour:",
        "answer": "routine errors",
        "choiceone": "knowledge errors",
        "choicetwo": "handling errors",
        "choicethree": "creative errors",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to overcome an overload of work during the flight, it is necessary to:\n-1: know how to use one's own reserve of resources in order to ease the\nburden on the crew.\n-2: divide up tasks among the crew.\n-3: ensure that the long-term memory is used as much as possible as short\nterm memory will add to the stress.\n-4: drop certain tasks and stick to high-level priorities.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The available cognitive resources of the human brain:",
        "answer": "are limited and make it impossible to perform two attentional tasks at\nthe same time",
        "choiceone": "are limited but make it possible to easily perform several tasks at the\nsame time",
        "choicetwo": "are virtually unlimited",
        "choicethree": "allow for twin-tasks operation without any loss of effectiveness",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The acquisition of a skill comprises three stages (Anderson model):",
        "answer": "cognitive, associative and automatic",
        "choiceone": "cognitive, associative and knowledge",
        "choicetwo": "associative, autonomous and expert",
        "choicethree": "automatic, cognitive and knowledge",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can be described as being proficient, when he/she:",
        "answer": "has automated a large part of the necessary flight deck routine\noperations in order to free his/her cognitive resources",
        "choiceone": "is able to reduce his/her arousal to a low level during the entire flight",
        "choicetwo": "knows how to off-load all his/her resources to the automation of tasks",
        "choicethree": "is capable of maintaining a high level of arousal during a great bulk of\nthe flight",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is\ncorrect?",
        "answer": "All pilots should master it because the aeronautical world needs one\ncommon language.",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for\neffective management of any flight's communication.",
        "choicetwo": "It is necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official\nlanguages of the ICAO.",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the\nofficial aeronautical language of the destination country.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best fits the definition of an active error?\nActive error is:",
        "answer": "produced by the operator and can be rapidly detected",
        "choiceone": "produced either by a front-line operator or by a remote operator and\nresults in a hidden or latent consequence at a specific moment of the\naction",
        "choicetwo": "essentially results from the application of a bad rule or the poor\napplication of a good rule by aeroplane designers",
        "choicethree": "rare in front-line actions and difficult to detect owing to the fact that it\nusually occurs in a complex system of uncontrolled and involuntary\ndeviations",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main consequences of latent errors? They:\n-1: remain undetected in the system for a certain length of time.\n-2: may only manifest themselves under certain conditions.\n-3: are quickly detectable by the front-line operator whose mental schemas on\nthe instantaneous situation filter out formal errors.\n-4: lull pilots into a false sense of security\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "1,2 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements fits best the concept of latent error?\nLatent errors:",
        "answer": "have been present in the system for a certain length of time and are\ndifficult to identify as a result of the time lag between the generation and\nthe occurrence of the error",
        "choiceone": "are rarely made by front-line operators, and are consequently readily\nidentified and detected by the monitoring, detection and warning links",
        "choicetwo": "are mainly associated with the behaviour of front-line operators and are\nonly detected after advanced problem-solving",
        "choicethree": "rapidly may be detected via their immediate consequences on the action\nin progress",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To avoid wrong decisions by the pilot, an aircraft system should at the\nminimum to",
        "answer": "report its malfunction",
        "choiceone": "report the deviation",
        "choicetwo": "correct the deviation",
        "choicethree": "tolerate the deviation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can a system be said to be tolerant to error?\nWhen:",
        "answer": "the consequences of an error will not seriously jeopardise safety",
        "choiceone": "its safety system is too permeable to error",
        "choicetwo": "its safety system has taken account of all statistically probable errors",
        "choicethree": "latent errors do not entail serious consequences for safety",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why must flight safety considerations consider the human error mechanism?\n-1: It is analysis of an incident or accident which will make it possible to\nidentify what error has been committed and by whom. It is the process\nwhereby the perpetrator is made responsible which may lead to elimination of\nthe error.\n-2: If we have a better understanding of the cognitive error mechanism, it will\nbe possible to adapt procedures, aircraft interfaces, etc.\n-3: It is error management procedure which enables us to continuously adjust\nour actions. The better we understand the underlying mechanism of an error,\nthe better will be our means for detecting and reducing future errors.\n-4: Since error is essentially human, once it has been identified by the use of\nprocedures, a person will be able to anticipate and deal with it automatically\nin the future.\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
        "answer": "2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 4",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What strategies can be used to combat human error?\n-1: Reducing error-prone mechanisms.\n-2: Improving the way in which error is taken into account in training.\n-3: Sanctions against the initiators of error.\n-4: Improving recovery from errors and its consequences.\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Concerning the relationship between performance and stress, which of the\nfollowing statements is correct?",
        "answer": "A moderate level of stress may improve performance.",
        "choiceone": "A student will learn faster and better under severe stress.",
        "choicetwo": "Domestic stress will not affect the pilot's performance because he is\nable to leave this type of stress on the ground.",
        "choicethree": "A well trained pilot is able to eliminate any kind of stress completely\nwhen he is scheduled to fly.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress is a frequent aspect of the pilot's job. Under which of the following\ncircumstances does it occur?\n1. Stress occurs whenever the pilot must revise his plan of action and does\nnot immediately have a solution\n2. Stress occurs with inexperienced pilots when the situational demands\nexceed their individual capabilities\n3. Stress occurs if a pilot is convinced that he will not be able to find a\nsolution for the problem he/she faces.",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "Only 1 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 is correct, 2 and 3 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Divided attention is the ability:\n1. to execute several mental activities at almost the same time (i.e. when\nswitching attention from outside the aircraft to the airspeed indicator on the\ninstrument panel)\n2. to monitor the progress of a motor programme (i.e. flying or taxiing the\nairplane) on a relatively subconscious level, while making a radio call at the\nsame time (requiring a rather conscious level)\n3 .to select information and check if it is relevant to the task in hand. At the\nsame time no other operation can be performed.\n4. to delegate tasks to the copilot while concentrating on the procedures",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 and 4 are false",
        "choicethree": "Only 3 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is:",
        "answer": "a physical condition caused by a lack of oxygen to meet the needs of the\nbody tissues, leading to mental and muscular disturbances, causing\nimpaired thinking, poor judgement and slow reactions",
        "choiceone": "a condition of lacking oxygen in the brain causing the circulatory system\nto compensate by decreasing the heart rate.",
        "choicetwo": "often produced during steep turns when pilots turn their heads in a\ndirection opposite to the direction in which the aircraft is turning",
        "choicethree": "a physical condition caused by a lack of oxygen saturation in the blood\nwhile hyperventilating.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is due to an excessive rate of breathing and can produce the\nfollowing symptoms:",
        "answer": "dizziness, tingling sensation in the fingers and toes, nausea and blurred\nvision",
        "choiceone": "reduced heart rate and increase in visual acuity",
        "choicetwo": "a state of overconfidence and reduced heart rate",
        "choicethree": "blue finger-nails and lips",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to get rid of excess nitrogen following scuba diving, subsequent\nflights should be delayed",
        "answer": "24 hours",
        "choiceone": "3 hours after non decompression diving",
        "choicetwo": "36 hours after any scuba diving",
        "choicethree": "48 hours after a continuous ascent in the water has been made",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During flight in IMC, the most reliable sense which should be used to\novercome illusions is the:",
        "answer": "visual sense, interpreting the attitude indicator",
        "choiceone": "\"Seat-of-the-pants-Sense\"",
        "choicetwo": "vestibular sense",
        "choicethree": "visual sense by looking outside",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Spatial disorientation will be most likely to occur during flight:",
        "answer": "if the brain receives conflicting information and the pilot does not\nbelieve the instruments",
        "choiceone": "when flying in and out of clouds and the pilot maintains good instrument\ncross check",
        "choicetwo": "when flying in light rain below the ceiling",
        "choicethree": "when flying in bright sunlight above a cloud layer",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The chemical substance responsible for addiction to tobacco is",
        "answer": "nicotine",
        "choiceone": "carbon monoxide",
        "choicetwo": "tar",
        "choicethree": "the combination of nicotine, tar and carbon monoxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is inadvisable to fly when suffering from a cold. The reason for this is:",
        "answer": "the tissue around the nasal end of the Eustachian tube is likely to be\nswollen thus causing difficulty in equalising the pressure within the\nmiddle ear and the nasal/throat area. Pain and damage to the eardrum\ncan result, particularly during fast descents",
        "choiceone": "although the change in air pressure during a climb at lower altitudes is\nvery small, it increases rapidly at high altitudes. If the tissue in the\nEustachian tube of the ear is swollen, gentle descents at high altitude\nwould result in damage to the ear drum",
        "choicetwo": "swollen tissue in the inner ear will increase the rate of metabolic\nproduction resulting in hyperventilation",
        "choicethree": "because it will seriously affect peripheral vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A large number of medical preparations can be bought without a doctor\u00b4s\nprescription. In relation to using these preparations, which of the following is\ncorrect:",
        "answer": "A pilot using any of these preparations should get professional advice\nfrom an aviation medical specialist if he intends to fly and self-medicate\nat the same time",
        "choiceone": "They have no side effects which would give problems to a pilot during\nflight",
        "choicetwo": "The side effects of these types of preparations are sufficiently negligible\nas to be ignored by pilots",
        "choicethree": "They will cause a condition of over-arousal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total pressure of a mixture of gases is equal to the sum of the partial\npressures of the gases in the mixture. This is:",
        "answer": "Dalton\u00b4s law",
        "choiceone": "Graham\u00b4s law",
        "choicetwo": "Henry`s law",
        "choicethree": "Boyle Mariotte\u00b4s law",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The cabin pressure in airline operation is",
        "answer": "normally between 6 000 to 8 000 feet",
        "choiceone": "normally between 2 000 to 3 000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "normally between 4 000 to 5 000 feet",
        "choicethree": "always equivalent to sea level",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human behaviour is determined by:",
        "answer": "biological characteristics, social environment and cultural influences",
        "choiceone": "biological characteristics only",
        "choicetwo": "the social environment only",
        "choicethree": "cultural influences only",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pilots are more easily inclined to take greater risks when:",
        "answer": "they are part of a group of pilots and they feel that they are being\nobserved and admired (e.g. air shows)",
        "choiceone": "making decisions independently of others",
        "choicetwo": "they are not constrained by time",
        "choicethree": "making a flight over unfamiliar territory",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot\u00b4s attitude to take and to evaluate risks by\nassessing the situation and making decisions based upon knowledge,\nskill and experience",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use\nto manually operate the aircraft controls",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The relevance of check procedures during flight becomes even more\nimportant when:",
        "answer": "flying an unfamiliar type of aircraft and experiencing mental pressure",
        "choiceone": "flying an aircraft which you have flown recently",
        "choicetwo": "conducting a longer flight than you would normally perform",
        "choicethree": "flying an aircraft which you have flown many times before",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following responses is an example of \"habit reversion\" (negative\nhabit transfer):",
        "answer": "A pilot who has flown many hours in an aircraft in which the fuel lever\npoints forward for the ON position, may unintentionally turn the fuel\nlever into the false position, when flying a different aircraft, where the\nfuel lever has to point aft to be in the ON position",
        "choiceone": "Turning the aircraft to the left when intending to turn it to the right",
        "choicetwo": "Incorrect anticipation of an air traffic controller\u00b4s instructions",
        "choicethree": "habitually missing an item on the checklist or missing the second item\nwhen two items are on the same line",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Although the anticipation of possible events is a good attitude for pilots to\nacquire, it can sometimes lead to hazardous situations. With this statement in\nmind, select the response below which could lead to such a hazard:",
        "answer": "mishearing the contents of a reply from an air traffic controller when a\nnon-standard procedure was given but a standard procedure was\nanticipated",
        "choiceone": "anticipating that the weather may deteriorate",
        "choicetwo": "anticipating that the flight will take longer time than planned",
        "choicethree": "anticipating the sequence of items on a check list.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regards to stress, as it affects human beings, which of the folowing\nstatements is correct?",
        "answer": "\u00b4Stress\u00b4is a term used to describe how a person reacts to demands\nplaced upon him/her.",
        "choiceone": "All forms of stress should be avoided.",
        "choicetwo": "Stressors relate purely to a pilot\u00b4s physical condition.",
        "choicethree": "Self imposed obligations will not create stress.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If during flight a pilot is in a mental condition of \"optimum arousal\" he/she will\nbe:",
        "answer": "prepared best to cope with a difficult task",
        "choiceone": "unprepared to handle a difficult situation",
        "choicetwo": "approaching a condition of complacency or fatigue",
        "choicethree": "in a confused mental state",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide is always present in the exhaust gases of engines. If a pilot\nis exposed to carbon monoxide, which of the following responses is correct?",
        "answer": "A short exposure to relatively high concentrations of carbon monoxide\ncan seriously affect a pilot\u00b4s ability to operate an aircraft.",
        "choiceone": "Carbon monoxide is easily recognised by odour and taste.",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon monoxide can only affect pilots if they are exposed to it for a\nlong period of time.",
        "choicethree": "When exposed to carbon monoxide for a long period of time, the body\nwill adapt to it and no adverse physical effects are experienced",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The trend in aeroplane hull-loss rate over the last three decades seems to be\nrelated to:",
        "answer": "the crew",
        "choiceone": "the manufacturer",
        "choicetwo": "the number of engines",
        "choicethree": "the year of manufacture",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pilot stress reactions:",
        "answer": "differ from pilot to pilot, depending on how a person manages the\nparticular stressors",
        "choiceone": "seem to be the same for most pilots",
        "choicetwo": "are related to an internationally recognized list of stressors where the\ntop-ten items should be avoided by every means",
        "choicethree": "do not change with the environment or different situations but mainly\nwith the characters themselves",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What aircraft equipment marked a substantial decrease in hull loss rates in\nthe eighties?",
        "answer": "GPWS",
        "choiceone": "DME",
        "choicetwo": "SSR",
        "choicethree": "TCAS",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Incapacitation is most dangerous when it is:",
        "answer": "insidious",
        "choiceone": "obvious",
        "choicetwo": "sudden",
        "choicethree": "intense",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One negative aspect of the highly automated cockpit results in:",
        "answer": "complacency among the crewmembers",
        "choiceone": "pilots disregarding the automatic equipment",
        "choicetwo": "constantly high crew overload with regard to the monitoring tasks",
        "choicethree": "less experienced crews because of more transparent system details",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following human error rates can be described and pretty good\nrealistic and pretty good, after methodical training",
        "answer": "1 in 1000 times",
        "choiceone": "1 in 100 times",
        "choicetwo": "1 in 10000 times",
        "choicethree": "1 in 100000 times",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Between which components, with reference to the SHELL Concept, covers\npilot misinterpretation of the old three-point altimeter?",
        "answer": "Liveware - Hardware",
        "choiceone": "Liveware - Software",
        "choicetwo": "Liveware - Environment",
        "choicethree": "Liveware - Liveware",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The errors resulting from an illogical indexing system in an operations\nmanual are related to an interface mismatch between",
        "answer": "Liveware - Software",
        "choiceone": "Liveware - Hardware",
        "choicetwo": "Liveware - Environment",
        "choicethree": "Liveware - Liveware",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following provides the basis of all perceptions?",
        "answer": "The intensity of the stimuli.",
        "choiceone": "The aural or visual significance attributed in short term memory.",
        "choicetwo": "The aural or visual significance attributed in long term memory.",
        "choicethree": "The separation of figure and background.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The effect of experience and repetition on performance:",
        "answer": "can both be beneficial and negative",
        "choiceone": "is always negative",
        "choicetwo": "is never negative",
        "choicethree": "is always beneficial",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \"reversion to an earlier behaviour\npattern\" are:\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when situations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress",
        "answer": "1. and 3.",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.",
        "choicetwo": "3.",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most dangerous characteristic ofperception is, that it",
        "answer": "is frequently extremely resistant to correction",
        "choiceone": "will mainly occur under conditions of relaxation",
        "choicetwo": "will only occur under conditions of stress",
        "choicethree": "can easily be changed",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fixation or tunnel vision is primarily to be expected when:",
        "answer": "stress is high",
        "choiceone": "stress is medium",
        "choicetwo": "stress and motivation are medium",
        "choicethree": "stress and motivation are low",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following concepts relating to human reliability is true ?",
        "answer": "If equipment is designed in such a way that it can be operated wrongly,\nthen sooner or later, it will be.",
        "choiceone": "Response to a particular stressful influence does not vary from one\nperson to another.",
        "choicetwo": "Expectation has no influence on perception.",
        "choicethree": "Performance is totally independent of motivation.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following operations are performed more effectively by people\nthan by automatic systems ?\n1. Qualitative decision-making\n2. Waiting for an infrequent phenomenon\n3. Monitoring to ensure that certain values are not exceeded\n4. Detection of unusual conditions (smell, noise, etc.)",
        "answer": "1,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following operations are performed more effectively by\nautomatic systems than by people ?\n1. Waiting for an infrequent phenomenon\n2. Long term controlling of a set value (e.g holding of trajectory)\n3. Monitoring to ensure that certain values are not exceeded (e.g. holding of\nflight path)\n4. Qualitative decision-making",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "2,4",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a result of automation in cockpits,",
        "answer": "communication and coordination call for an even greater effort on the\npart of the crew members",
        "choiceone": "it is easier for the captain to monitor the work of the first officer and vice\nversa",
        "choicetwo": "the need for communication between crew members has been\ndecreased",
        "choicethree": "communication and coordination have clearly improved in man-man and\nman-machine relations",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following drawbacks are associated with automation ?\n1. Reduced competence in manually controlling the aircraft\n2. Increased likelihood of slips while programming automatic systems\n3. Difficulties in adapting to the use of a sidestick\n4. General decrease in technical reliability",
        "answer": "1,2",
        "choiceone": "1,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are the most favourable solutions to manage phases of\nreduced or low vigilance (hypovigilance)?\n1. Keep active open communication between man and machine\n2. Use of amphetamines\n3. Reducing the intensity of the light\n4. Organising periods of rest during the flight",
        "answer": "1,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are main signs indicating the loss of vigilance ?\n1. Decrease in sensory perception\n2. Increase in selective attention\n3. Sensation of muscular heaviness\n4. Decrease in complacency\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements ?",
        "answer": "1 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is \"divided attention\"?",
        "answer": "The management of several matters of interest dealt with individually\none after the other",
        "choiceone": "Ease of concentrating on a particular objective",
        "choicetwo": "Difficulty of concentrating on a particular objective",
        "choicethree": "The adverse effect of motivation which leads to one's attention being\ndispersed",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning hypovigilance is correct ?\nHypovigilance:",
        "answer": "may occur at any time in the flight",
        "choiceone": "usually occurs a number of minutes after a stressful take-off",
        "choicetwo": "tends to occur at the end of the mission as a result of a relaxation in the\ncrew's' attention",
        "choicethree": "only affects certain personality types",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main factors which bring about reduced or low vigilance\n(hypovigilance) ?\n1. The monotony of the task\n2. Tiredness and the need for sleep\n3. A lack of stimulation\n4. Excessive stress",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "2,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements with regard to motivation is correct?",
        "answer": "Excessive motivation in combination with high levels of stress will limit\nattention management capabilities",
        "choiceone": "Too much motivation may result in hypovigilance and thus in a decrease\nin attention",
        "choicetwo": "Motivation will reduce risk",
        "choicethree": "Low motivation will guarantee adequate attention management\ncapabilities",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements summarises the impact that motivation\nmay have on attention?",
        "answer": "It increases alertness and attention",
        "choiceone": "It only facilitates attention in extreme cases (risk of death)",
        "choicetwo": "Motivation has only a small effect on attention, but it facilitates alertness",
        "choicethree": "It stimulates attention but may lead to phases of low arousal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the effects of excesive stress?",
        "answer": "It increases vigilance for a longer period than stress itself, but may\nfocus attention inappropriately",
        "choiceone": "It reduces vigilance and focuses attention",
        "choicetwo": "It activates resources stored in memory",
        "choicethree": "It has very little immediate effect on vigilance and attention",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The level of automation helps to conserve resources. On the other hand, it\nmay result in:",
        "answer": "routine errors (slips)",
        "choiceone": "mistakes",
        "choicetwo": "decision-making errors",
        "choicethree": "errors in selecting an appropriate plan of action",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main adverse effect of expectation with regards to perception?",
        "answer": "Expectation often guides the focus of attention towards a particular\naspect, while possible alternates are neglected",
        "choiceone": "Expectations always lead to routine errors",
        "choicetwo": "Expectation is a tool that allows capture of all relevant information",
        "choicethree": "The attention area is enlarged by expectation, however it will therefore\nlead to uncertainties when a pilot is looking for a decision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The acquisition of a motor programme (skill) will mean that:",
        "answer": "the more behaviour is automated, the less it requires conscious\nattention and thus the more it frees mental resources",
        "choiceone": "the more behaviour is automated, the more it requires attention and the\nmore it frees resources",
        "choicetwo": "the more behaviour is automated, the more it requires attention and the\nless it frees resources",
        "choicethree": "the less behaviour is automated, the less it requires attention and the\nmore it frees resources",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Concerning circadian rhythm disruption (jet lag), adjustment to destination\ntime:\n1. Takes longer when travelling west rather than travelling east\n2. Takes longer when travelling east rather than travelling west\n3. Varies little between individuals\n4. Varies substantially among individuals\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements ?",
        "answer": "2 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What seems to be the main role of Orthodox sleep?",
        "answer": "It essentially allows for physical recovery",
        "choiceone": "It includes physical and mental recuperation associate with fatigue",
        "choicetwo": "Its main role is associated with activities of memory activities and\nrestoration of attention capabilities",
        "choicethree": "Via physical recovery, it is characterised by an alternation of dream\nphases and paradoxical phases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main effects of a lack of sleep on performance?",
        "answer": "It increases fatigue, reduces concentration and increases the risk of\nsensory illusions",
        "choiceone": "It increases fatigue and concentration difficulties, but facilitates stress\nmanagement by muscular relaxation",
        "choicetwo": "It causes muscular spasms",
        "choicethree": "It reduces concentration and fatigue only with sleep loss greater than 48\nhours",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the effect of tiredness on attention ?",
        "answer": "It reduces the ability to manage multiple matters",
        "choiceone": "It increases the ability to manage multiple matters",
        "choicetwo": "It leads to one's attention being shared between different centres of\ninterest",
        "choicethree": "It has no specific effects on attention",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning tiredness is correct ?",
        "answer": "Tiredness is a subjective sensation which may result in hypovigilance",
        "choiceone": "Tiredness is always the result of an intellectual overload",
        "choicetwo": "Tiredness is the consequence of poor performance",
        "choicethree": "Tiredness always effect people of the same age in a similar way",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving conflict?\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n3. Abandoning facts so as to move the conversation to a more emotional level\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences",
        "answer": "1,2,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What elements establish synergy within the crew ?",
        "answer": "Synergy must be built up from the start of the mission (briefing) and be\nmaintained until it comes to an end (debriefing)",
        "choiceone": "Synergy establishes itself automatically within the crew, right through\nfrom briefing to debriefing",
        "choicetwo": "Synergy is independent of the natural individual characteristics of the\ngroup members (communication, mutual confidence, sharing of tasks,\netc.)",
        "choicethree": "It is only the captain's status which allows the establishment of synergy\nwithin the crew",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterise a synergetic cockpit?\n1. Decisions are taken by the captain, but prepared by the crew\n2. There is little delegating of tasks\n3. Communications are few in number but precise and geared purely to the\nflight\n4. Fluid, consensual boundaries exist with regard to leadership-style",
        "answer": "1,4",
        "choiceone": "1,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterise a self-centered cockpit ?",
        "answer": "Without taking note of what the other members are doing, each one\ndoes his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is\naware of what is being done or what is going on",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a\nsynergetic cockpit",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the\ncaptain takes charge of a situation",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member\nbolsters the crew's synergy",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What may become the main risk of a \"laissez-faire\" cockpit ?",
        "answer": "Inversion of authority",
        "choiceone": "Increased captain's authority",
        "choicetwo": "Appearance of aggressiveness",
        "choicethree": "Disengagement of the co-pilot",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is characterized by a \"laissez-faire\" cockpit ?",
        "answer": "A passive approach by the captain allows decisions, choices and\nactions by other crew members",
        "choiceone": "Each member carries out actions and makes choices informing the other\nmembers about them",
        "choicetwo": "The captain's authority rules all the actions or decisions associated with\nthe situation",
        "choicethree": "The high level of independence granted to each member by the captain\nquickly leads to tension between the various crew members",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the most frequent results of an self-centred captain on the flight\ndeck ?",
        "answer": "In a two-pilot flight deck, the co-pilot is ignored and may react by\ndisengaging, showing delayed responses or aggression",
        "choiceone": "High group performance despite the strained relations",
        "choicetwo": "A major risk of authority inversion if the co-pilot is unassertive",
        "choicethree": "Performance is very poor as self-centred behaviour leads to an increase\nof cooperation and efficiency",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following describes an autocratic cockpit?",
        "answer": "The captain's excessive authority considerably reduces\ncommunications and consequently the synergy and cohesion of the\ncrew",
        "choiceone": "Despite the overly strong authority of the captain, everything functions\ncorrectly owing to his natural leadership",
        "choicetwo": "Each of the members chooses what job to do without telling the others\nand in the belief that everyone is aware of what he is doing",
        "choicethree": "The atmosphere is relaxed thanks to a captain who leaves complete\nfreedom to the various members of the crew",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What optimises crew co-operation ?\n1. Sharing and common task\n2. Confidence in each others capability\n3. Precise definition of functions associated with each crew members role",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "1",
        "choicetwo": "1,2",
        "choicethree": "2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What distinguishes status from role ?",
        "answer": "While role defines- via behaviour- the functions that must be performed\nby individuals, status defines the hierarchical position and its\nrecognition by the group",
        "choiceone": "While role defines the enjoyment of a hierarchical position and its\nrecognition by the group, status defines - via behaviour- the functions\nthat must be performed by individuals",
        "choicetwo": "Unlike status, role is fixed and is not modified either by the situation in\nflight or by the interactions of a new crew",
        "choicethree": "Unlike status, role is fixed and is modified either by the situation in flight\nor by the interactions of a new crew",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with\nreference to an object or a situation",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the\nactions associated with them",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual ?\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n4. Past experience",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is synergy in a crew ?",
        "answer": "The coordinated action of all members towards a common objective, in\nwhich collective performance is proving to be more than the sum of the\nindividual performances",
        "choiceone": "A behavioural expedient associated with the desynchronisation of the\ncoordinated actions",
        "choicetwo": "The coordinated action of unrelated individual performances in\nachieving a non-standard task",
        "choicethree": "The uncoordinated action of the crewmembers towards a common\nobjective",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning conflicts is correct ?",
        "answer": "Conflict management involves the participation of all involved parties in\nfinding an acceptable collective solution",
        "choiceone": "Whatever the cause of the conflict, its resolution must necessarily\ninvolve an additional party if it is to be effective",
        "choicetwo": "Conflicts are negative in themselves and can only lead to a general\ndetachment of involved parties",
        "choicethree": "The emergence of a conflict always results from calling into question the\ngeneral abilities of one of the involved parties",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is most likely to be overlooked should a pilot make a\nrushed decision ?",
        "answer": "analysis of the current actual situation and instead applying a decision\nprepared beforehand",
        "choiceone": "the skills of air traffic controllers",
        "choicetwo": "the need to take account of every possible result or outcome",
        "choicethree": "the captain's superior knowledge, justified by his/her status",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In terms of decision-making, the intention to become integrated into the team,\nto be recognised as the leader or to avoid conflicts may lead to:",
        "answer": "the attempt to agree on decisions made by other crew members",
        "choiceone": "an authoritarian approach thus demonstrating ones own ability to lead",
        "choicetwo": "the improvement of internal risk assessment capabilities",
        "choicethree": "a fast and decisive option",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What strategy should be put in place when faced with an anticipated period of\nstress?",
        "answer": "A strategy of preparing decisions",
        "choiceone": "A non-sequenced strategy",
        "choicetwo": "A Laissez-faire strategy",
        "choicethree": "A strategy of no commitment",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which biases relate to human decision making?\n1. Personal experience tends to alter the perception of the risk of an event\noccurring\n2. There is a natural tendency to want to confirm our decision even in the face\nof facts which contradict it\n3. The group to which an individual belongs tends to influence the particular\ndecision\n4. There is natural tendency to select only objective facts for decision-making\npurposes",
        "answer": "1,2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Habits and routine can influence decision-making in a way that:",
        "answer": "shows a tendency to select the most familiar solution first and foremost,\nsometimes to the detriment of achieving the best possible result",
        "choiceone": "habit is the product of experience and should be used as a primary\nconsideration in all decisions",
        "choicetwo": "professional pilots will never question established procedures",
        "choicethree": "one always selects a choice in accordance with the company's usual\npractices",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making can be influenced by the following factors:\n1. people tend to conform to opinions expressed by a majority within the\ngroup they belong to\n2. people always keep the future decisions in line with those their superiors\nhave made in the past\n3. people more easily tend to select data which meet their expectations\n4. people rarely base decisions on their personal preferences but rather on\nrational information\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 3",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making is a concept which represents:",
        "answer": "a voluntary and conscious process of selection, from among possible\nsolutions, for a given problem",
        "choiceone": "an automated or automation-like act of applying defined procedures",
        "choicetwo": "an automatic process of selection from among the various solutions to a\ngiven problem",
        "choicethree": "a spontaneous act of seeking the most effective solution in a given\nsituation when faced with a defined problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In decision-making, the selection of a solution depends:\n1. on objective and subjective criteria\n2. on the objective to be achieved\n3. on the risks associated with each solution\n4. on the personality of the decision-maker",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,3",
        "choicethree": "4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decision-making results in:",
        "answer": "a choice between different options to achieve a goal",
        "choiceone": "a choice always based on the experience of the PIC",
        "choicetwo": "a totally objective choice between options to achieve a goal proposed by\nthe Piot in Command",
        "choicethree": "a subjective choice between options to achieve a goal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In problem-solving, what determines the transition from rule-based activities\nto a knowledge-based activity?",
        "answer": "The unsuitability of the known rules for the problem posed",
        "choiceone": "Attentional capture",
        "choicetwo": "Knowledge of rules which apply to the problem posed",
        "choicethree": "The unsuitability of the automated actions",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main characteristics of active errors ?\nThey:\n1. are detectable only with difficulty by first-line operators\n2. have rapid and direct consequences on the action in progress\n3. occur at the human/machine interface\n4. lie dormant and are undetected at first",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The maintenance of man's internal equilibrium is called:",
        "answer": "Homeostasis",
        "choiceone": "Heterostasis",
        "choicetwo": "Homeothermy",
        "choicethree": "Poikilothermy",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main limitation of the long-term memory is:",
        "answer": "unless information is accessed from time to time, retrieval of\ninformation can be difficult",
        "choiceone": "the quantity of data which may be stored",
        "choicetwo": "if enough information is entered at the same time, saturation may take\nplace",
        "choicethree": "the data storage time",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the main limits of short-term memory ?\nIt is:\n-1: very sensitive to interruptions and interference\n-2: difficult to access\n-3: limited in size\n-4: information is lost within approximately 20 seconds unless it is actively or\ndeliberately placed into the long term memory.",
        "answer": "1,3 ,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2 ,3",
        "choicetwo": "2 ,3",
        "choicethree": "2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Action plans (SOP's) in a cockpit must:",
        "answer": "be shared by the members of the crew and updated at each modification\nin order to maintain maximum synergy",
        "choiceone": "be tailored to the individual pilot's needs in order to facilitate the normal\noperation of the aircraft",
        "choicetwo": "only be tailored to the type of aircraft, regardless of current MCC\nprocedures",
        "choicethree": "only follow the manufacturers proposals and not reflect individual\noperators cockpit philosophies",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Workload essentially depends on:",
        "answer": "the current situation, the pilot's expertise and the ergonomics of the\nsystem",
        "choiceone": "the pilot's experience and the ergonomics of the system",
        "choicetwo": "the pilot's knowledge",
        "choicethree": "the task and the day's parameters (weather report, aircraft load, type of\nflight, etc)",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot becomes skilled when he/she:\n-1: trains or practises regularly\n-2: knows how to manage himself/herself\n-3: possesses all the knowledge associated with his aircraft\n-4: knows how to keep resources in reserve for coping with the unexpected",
        "answer": "1,2,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Man possesses a system for maintaining his internal equilibrium in the face of\nvariations brought about by external stimulations.\nThis internal equilibrium is called:",
        "answer": "Homeostasis",
        "choiceone": "Heterostasis",
        "choicetwo": "Isothermy",
        "choicethree": "Metastasis",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress is:",
        "answer": "a mechanism by which an individual can respond to situations which\nhe/she may have to face",
        "choiceone": "a psychosomatic disease that one can learn to control",
        "choicetwo": "a response by man to his problems, which automatically leads to a\nreduction in his performance",
        "choicethree": "a phenomenon which is specific to modern man",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The individual's perception of stress depends on:",
        "answer": "the subjective evaluation of the situation and one's abilities to cope with\nit",
        "choiceone": "the objective evaluation of the situation and one's abilities to cope with\nit",
        "choicetwo": "the pilot's increasing level of arousal",
        "choicethree": "the conditions of the current situation only",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Physiological stressors include:",
        "answer": "Noise, temperature (low or high), humidity, sleep deprivation",
        "choiceone": "Noise, hunger, conflicts, a death",
        "choicetwo": "Heat, humidity, fatigue, administrative problems",
        "choicethree": "Temperature, hunger, thirst, divorce",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "General Adaptation Syndrome is characterised by the following phases:\n-1: alarm\n-2: alert phase\n-3: resistance phase\n-4: exhaustion phase\n-5: vigilance phase",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,4,5",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4,5",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following course of action should be taken if gastrointestinal complaints\nin flight crew occur before to take-off:\n-1: take the standard medicines and advise the doctor on returning from the\nflight\n-2: assess your own ability to fly, if necessary with the help of a doctor\n-3: if in doubt about fitness to fly - do not fly!\n-4: reduce the cabin temperature, and drink before you are thirsty so as to\navoid dehydration",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,3",
        "choicetwo": "1,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following systems are involved in motion sickness ?\n-1: Hearing\n-2: The vestibular system\n-3: Vision\n-4 The proprioceptive senses \"Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense\")\n-5: The gastrointestinal system",
        "answer": "2,3,4,5",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,2,5",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the absence of external reference points, the sensation that the vehicle in\nwhich you sitting is moving when it is in fact the vehicle directly alongside\nwhich is moving is called:",
        "answer": "illusion of relative movement",
        "choiceone": "autokinetic illusion",
        "choicetwo": "cognitive illusion",
        "choicethree": "somato-gravic illusion",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following illusions are brought about by conflicts between the\nvisual system and the vestibular system ?\n-1: Illusions concerning the attitude of the aircraft\n-2: Autokinetic illusion (fixed point viewed as moving)\n-3: Illusions when estimating the size and distance of objects\n-4: Illusions of rotation",
        "answer": "1,4",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2",
        "choicethree": "3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The vestibular system is composed of\n-1: two ventricles\n-2: a saccule\n-3: a utricle\n-4: three semicircular channels",
        "answer": "2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "1,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct ?\n- 1: The retina has rods in its peripheral zone and cones in its central zone\n- 2: The retina has cones and the crystalline lens has rods\n- 3: The rods allow for night-vision\n- 4: The cones are located on the peripheral zone of the retina",
        "answer": "1,3",
        "choiceone": "1",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to perceive colour vision, it is necessary:\n-1: for there to be considerable amount of light (ambient luminosity)\n-2: at night to look at the point to be observed at an angle of 15\u00b0\n-3: to allow the eye a period of time to get used to the light\n-4: to avoid white light",
        "answer": "1",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,4",
        "choicethree": "3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part",
        "choiceone": "rods located in its central part",
        "choicetwo": "crystalline lens",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its peripheral zone",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Accommodation, which enables a clear image to be obtained, is\naccomplished by which of the following?",
        "answer": "The crystalline lens",
        "choiceone": "The rods",
        "choicetwo": "The cones",
        "choicethree": "The retina",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In civil air transport, linear accelerations (Gx):\n- 1: do not exist\n- 2: have slight physiological consequences\n- 3: may, in the case of pull-out, lead to loss of consciousness\n- 4: may cause sensory illusions on the pitch axis",
        "answer": "2,4",
        "choiceone": "1",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the humidity of air in current in a pressurized cabin, we know\nthat it:\n-1: varies between 40 and 60%\n-2: varies between 5 and 15%\n-3: may cause dehydration effecting the performance of the crew\n-4: has no special effects on crew members",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following occurs in man if the internal body temperature increases to\n39\u00b0C:",
        "answer": "impairment of physical and mental performance",
        "choiceone": "apathy",
        "choicetwo": "considerable dehydration",
        "choicethree": "nothing significant happens at this temperature. The first clinical signs\nonly start to appear at 39\u00b0C",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following mechanisms regulate body temperature when exposed\nto extreme high environmental temperatures?\n-1: Shivering\n-2: Vaso-constriction of peripheral blood vessels\n-3: Sweating\n-4: Vaso-dilation of peripheral blood vessels",
        "answer": "3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3",
        "choicethree": "1",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls\nbelow 35\u00b0C:",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "We can observe the following in relation to a state of hypothermia:",
        "answer": "reasoning problems as soon as body temperature falls below 37\u00b0C",
        "choiceone": "a substantial increase in internal body temperature whereas peripheral\ntemperature at the skin is stable",
        "choicetwo": "widespread pain in the joints",
        "choicethree": "greater capacity for adaptation than in a hot atmosphere",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning barotrauma are correct?",
        "answer": "It is caused by pressure differentials between gases in hollow cavities of\nthe body and the ambient pressure",
        "choiceone": "It is caused by an increase in the partial pressure of oxygen associated\nwith a decrease in altitude",
        "choicetwo": "It is more likely to occur during ascent then during a rapid descent",
        "choicethree": "It is mainly associated with a sink rate which exceeds the ability of the\nbody to balance its internal pressures",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to decompression sickness associated with flight, we know that:",
        "answer": "age, obesity and scuba diving are risk factors",
        "choiceone": "scuba diving does not pose any problem for a subsequent flight",
        "choicetwo": "gender is the prime risk factor, with two out of every three women being\nsensitive to it",
        "choicethree": "physical activity after decompression reduces the risks of\ndecompression sickness symptoms",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The procedure to be followed in the event of decompression when flying\nabove 10,000 ft must:",
        "answer": "allow for the rapid supply of oxygen in order to prevent hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "allow for a rapid descent independent from sufficient supply of oxygen\nin order to prevent disorders due to hypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "make it possible to prevent hyperventilation owing to the inhalation of\n100 % oxygen",
        "choicethree": "make it possible to eliminate the risk of fogging due to the sudden\npressure changes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the \"Time of Useful Consciousness\" for a rapid decompression at\n25,000 ft ?",
        "answer": "Between 3 and 5 minutes depending on the physical activities of the\nsubjected pilot",
        "choiceone": "About 18 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "Between 25 seconds and 1 minute 30 seconds",
        "choicethree": "About 30 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Time of Useful Consciousness may vary according to:\n1: physical activity of the subjected crew\n2: the experience of the pilot on the type of aircraft in question\n3: the strength and time of decompression\n4: the cabin temperature",
        "answer": "1,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Safety is often improved by applying the principles of CRM, e.g.:",
        "answer": "expression of doubts or of a different opinion",
        "choiceone": "unquestioned obedience to all the Captain's decisions",
        "choicetwo": "abstention from any suggestion which might be untimely",
        "choicethree": "the avoidance of any conflict in order to preserve the crew's synergy",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An efficient flight deck (synergetic cockpit) will be observed when:",
        "answer": "decisions are taken by the Captain with the help and participation of the\nother crew members",
        "choiceone": "the plan of action is defined by the Captain because of his experience\nlevel",
        "choicetwo": "the Captain delegates the decision making process to other crew\nmembers",
        "choicethree": "decisions do not need to be discussed because of a common synergy\nbetween the crew members",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A non synergistic cockpit:",
        "answer": "is characterised by withdrawn crewmembers and unclear\ncommunication",
        "choiceone": "is characterised by a highly efficient crew, communicating appropriately\nwith the outside",
        "choicetwo": "always results from an over-relaxed atmosphere",
        "choicethree": "is not very dangerous as each person checks everything personally",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "CRM (Crew Resource Management) training is:",
        "answer": "intended to develop effectiveness of crew performance by improving\nattitudes towards flight safety and human relationship management",
        "choiceone": "not intended to change the individual's attitude at all",
        "choicetwo": "intended solely to alter an individual's personality;",
        "choicethree": "is mainly of relevance to pilots with personality disorders or\ninappropriate attitudes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The confirmation bias of decision making is",
        "answer": "a tendency to ignore that information which indicates that a hypothesis\nor decision is poor;",
        "choiceone": "a tendency not to seek for information which confirms a judgement",
        "choicetwo": "a tendency not to look for information which would reassure oneself\nabout a decision",
        "choicethree": "a tendency to agree with the decision made by the group",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main problem caused by positive (+Gz) accelerations?",
        "answer": "A pooling of blood in the lower portions of the body, and hence less\nblood available",
        "choiceone": "An improvement of peripheral vision",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in blood pressure in the upper part of the body (above\nheart-level)",
        "choicethree": "Hyperoxygenation of the blood which may lead to sensory disorders",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n1  Hypothermia affects physical and mental abilities.\n2  Man has effective natural protection against intense cold.\n3  Shivering makes it possible to combat the cold to a certain extent, but uses\nup a lot of energy\n4  Disorders associated with hypothermia appear at a body temperature of\nless than 35\u00b0C",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "2,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rods (scotopic visual cells) allow for:",
        "answer": "good night-vision after adaptation to darkness (30 min)",
        "choiceone": "good, virtually instantaneous night-vision (scotopic vision)",
        "choicetwo": "precise vision of contours and colours",
        "choicethree": "red vision, both during the day and at night",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following alternatives, which effects are due to positive acceleration (+\nGz)?\n- 1: Decrease in heart rate\n- 2: Pooling of blood into lower parts of the body\n- 3: Drop in blood pressure above heart-level\n- 4: Downward displacement or deformation of soft or mobile organs",
        "answer": "2,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3",
        "choicetwo": "1",
        "choicethree": "1,3,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is hypoxia ?",
        "answer": "Any condition where the oxygen concentration of the body is below\nnormal limits or where the oxygen available to the body cannot be used\ndue to some pathological condition",
        "choiceone": "The total absence of oxygen in the blood of the body",
        "choicetwo": "The respiratory symptom associated with altitude decompression\nsickness",
        "choicethree": "A state characterised by an excessive supply of oxygen which may be\ndue to maladjustment of the mask",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To optimise one's night-vision performance, it is necessary:\n- 1: to spend some time getting adapted to low levels of illumination\n- 2: to increase the instrument panel lighting by reducing the cockpit lighting\n- 3: not to focus on the point to be observed\n- 4: to avoid blinding sources of light",
        "answer": "1,3,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "2",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual perception of depth at close to medium distance is primarily due to",
        "answer": "binocular vision",
        "choiceone": "interactions between cones and rods",
        "choicetwo": "peripheral vision",
        "choicethree": "the high sensitivity of the retina",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What could be symptoms of hypoxia (when flying without oxygen) above\n12,000 ft?",
        "answer": "Headache, fatigue, dizziness, lack of coordination",
        "choiceone": "Headache, thirst, somnolence, collapse",
        "choicetwo": "Euphoria, headache, improvement in judgement, loss of consciousness",
        "choicethree": "Trembling, increase in body temperature, convulsions, slowing of the\nrate of breathing",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following characteristics apply to short-term memory ?\n- 1: It is limited in time and size\n- 2: It is unlimited in time and limited in size\n- 3: It is stable and insensitive to disturbances\n- 4: It is limited in time and unlimited in size",
        "answer": "1",
        "choiceone": "1,3",
        "choicetwo": "3,4",
        "choicethree": "2,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to short-term memory, we can say that:",
        "answer": "it is made up of everyday information for immediate use, and is limited in\nits capacity for storing and retaining data",
        "choiceone": "it is made up of everyday information for immediate use, and is limited in\nterms of the time for which it retains data but not in its storage capacity",
        "choicetwo": "it is a stable form of working memory, and thus not very sensitive to any\ndisturbance",
        "choicethree": "it stores mainly procedural knowledge (skills)",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Autokinetic illusion is:",
        "answer": "an illusion in which a stationary point of light, if stared at for several\nseconds in the dark, may - without a frame of reference - appear to move",
        "choiceone": "the sensation during a radial acceleration of seeing a fixed reference\npoint moving into the opposite direction of the acceleration",
        "choicetwo": "a conflict between the visual system and bodily sensations",
        "choicethree": "poor interpretation of the surrounding world",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n-1: Modern aircraft allow for 50 - 60% relative humidity in the cabin air under\nany conditions of flight, which is satisfactory for the body\n-2: Thirst is a symptom of dehydration\n-3: Dehydration may lead to clinical manifestations such as dizziness and\nfatigue\n-4: Drinking excessive quantities of water must be avoided since resistance to\nperiods of low hydration will otherwise be lost",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,2,4",
        "choicethree": "1,4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to central vision, which of the following statements are correct ?\n-1: It is due to the functioning of rods\n-2: It enables details, colours and movement to be seen\n-3: Its very active both during the day and at night\n-4: It represents a zone where about 150.000 cones per mm are located to give\nhigh resolution capacity",
        "answer": "2,4",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4",
        "choicetwo": "2,3,4",
        "choicethree": "1,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?",
        "answer": "70% of information processed by man enters via the visual channel",
        "choiceone": "Hearing is the sense which collects most information in man",
        "choicetwo": "40% of information processed by man enters via the visual channel",
        "choicethree": "The kinesthetic channel provides the most important information for\nflying",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the procedure above 10.000 ft altitude when faced with explosive\ndecompression?",
        "answer": "Don an oxygen mask and descend to below 10,000 ft",
        "choiceone": "First inform ATC",
        "choicetwo": "Descend to below 10,000 ft and signal an emergency",
        "choicethree": "Check the cabin altitude, don an oxygen mask and maintain level flight",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the approximate Time of Useful Consciousness for a seated pilot\nfollowing a rapid decompression at 35,000 ft ?",
        "answer": "45 seconds",
        "choiceone": "12 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "5 minutes",
        "choicethree": "3 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Time of Useful Consciousness ?",
        "answer": "The length of time during which an individual can act with both mental\nand physical efficiency, measured from the moment at which he/she\nloses his/her available oxygen supply",
        "choiceone": "The time taken to become aware of hypoxia due to gradual\ndecompression",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot's reaction time when faced with hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "The period of time between the start of hypoxia and the moment that the\npilot becomes aware of it",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the procedure to be followed when symptoms of decompression\nsickness occur?",
        "answer": "Descend to the lowest possible level and land as soon as possible",
        "choiceone": "Descend to the lowest possible level and wait for the symptoms to\ndisappear before climbing again",
        "choicetwo": "Only medical treatment is of use",
        "choicethree": "Only the prompt supply of oxygen is necessary",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is decompression sickness?",
        "answer": "A condition resulting from the formation of nitrogen bubbles in bodily\ntissues and fluids after a cabin pressure loss at high altitude",
        "choiceone": "A frequent disorder in commercial aviation due to the pressurisation\ncurve of modern aircraft",
        "choicetwo": "A disorder which is solely encountered below 18,000 ft",
        "choicethree": "The formation of air bubbles in bodily tissues, with no consequences for\npeople's capabilities",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n-1: Scuba diving may be practiced without restriction\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about long-term memory are correct?\n-1: Information is stored in the Semantic, Episodic and Procedural memories.\n-2: The period of time for which information is retained is limited by the\nfrequency with which this same information is used.\n-3: It processes information quickly and has an effective mode of access in\nreal time.\n-4: Ease and speed of access is dependent upon, to a large extent, the\nfrequency with which the information is recalled.",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information:",
        "answer": "is limited to the foveal area of the retina",
        "choiceone": "is limited to daytime using the rod cells",
        "choicetwo": "is almost equally shared by the entire retina",
        "choicethree": "is governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20\ndegrees of angle",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C\nor more.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The atmospheric pressure at 18,000 feet altitude is half the atmospheric\npressure at sea level.\nIn accordance with this statement,",
        "answer": "the partial oxygen pressure at that altitude will also drop to 1/2 of the\npressure of oxygen at sea level",
        "choiceone": "the oxygen saturation of the blood at that altitude will drop by 50 % too",
        "choicetwo": "the oxygen percentage of the air at that altitude will drop by one half\nalso",
        "choicethree": "the partial oxygen pressure at that altitude will be doubled",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You climb from 0 to 50.000 ft and measure the decrease of the pressure per\n5.000 ft. The absolute difference in barometric pressure is greatest between:",
        "answer": "0 and 5.000 feet",
        "choiceone": "5.000 and 10.000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "10.000 and 15.000 feet",
        "choicethree": "45.000 and 50.000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Physiological problems due to increasing altitude are caused by:",
        "answer": "decreased atmospheric pressure",
        "choiceone": "disorientation",
        "choicetwo": "accelerations",
        "choicethree": "increased atmospheric pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volume percentage of oxygen in the atmosphere at 30.000 feet remains at\n21 %; but the partial pressure of oxygen:",
        "answer": "decreases with decreasing barometric pressure",
        "choiceone": "remains constant, independent from altitude",
        "choicetwo": "increases by expansion",
        "choicethree": "decreases significantly with lower temperatures",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:",
        "answer": "21% oxygen",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dry air is a mixture of gases. Their volume percentage is about:",
        "answer": "21% oxygen,78% nitrogen, 1% other gases",
        "choiceone": "18% oxygen, 80% nitrogen, 2% other gases",
        "choicetwo": "19% oxygen, 80% nitrogen, 1% other gases",
        "choicethree": "25% oxygen, 74% nitrogen, 1% other gases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Boyle's law is directly applicable in case of:",
        "answer": "the expansion of trapped gasses in the human body with increasing\naltitude",
        "choiceone": "the occurrence of decompression sickness at high altitude",
        "choicetwo": "the occurrence of hypoxia with increasing altitude",
        "choicethree": "hyperventilation with increasing altitude",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dalton's law explains the occurrence of:",
        "answer": "altitude hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "bends",
        "choicetwo": "decompression sickness",
        "choicethree": "creeps",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Henry's Law explains the occurrence of:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness",
        "choiceone": "diffusion",
        "choicetwo": "hyperventilation",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Our body takes its energy from:\n1:   minerals\n2:   protein\n3:   carbonhydrates\n4:   vitamins",
        "answer": "2,3",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3,4",
        "choicetwo": "1,4",
        "choicethree": "1,3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by metabolism?",
        "answer": "The generation and utilisation of energy by the body's cells and tissues",
        "choiceone": "Information exchange",
        "choicetwo": "Transfer of chemical messages",
        "choicethree": "Exchange of substances between the lung and the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the waste products of the metabolic process in the cell is:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "protein",
        "choicetwo": "sugar",
        "choicethree": "fat",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The body loses water via:\n1. the skin and the lungs\n2. the kidneys\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct and 2 is not correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is not correct and 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "both are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under normal circumstances, which gas will diffuse from the blood to the\nalveoli:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "carbon monoxide",
        "choicetwo": "nitrogen",
        "choicethree": "oxygen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The blood in the pulmonary artery is:",
        "answer": "lacking in oxygen and rich in carbon dioxide",
        "choiceone": "lacking in both oxygen and carbon dioxide",
        "choicetwo": "rich in oxygen and lacking in carbon dioxide",
        "choicethree": "rich in both oxygen and carbon dioxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The thin walls of capillaries are permeable for:",
        "answer": "",
        "choiceone": "gases",
        "choicetwo": "platelets",
        "choicethree": "protein",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The circulatory system, amongst other things, allows for:\n1. transportation of oxygen and carbon dioxide\n2. transportation of information by chemical substances\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements ?",
        "answer": "",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct and 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 is false and 2 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Oxygen, combined with haemoglobin in blood is transported by",
        "answer": "red blood cells",
        "choiceone": "platelets",
        "choicetwo": "blood plasma",
        "choicethree": "white blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Haemoglobin is:",
        "answer": "in the red blood cells",
        "choiceone": "in the platelets",
        "choicetwo": "dissolved in the plasma",
        "choicethree": "in the white blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia has:",
        "answer": "not enough functional haemoglobin",
        "choiceone": "not enough platelets",
        "choicetwo": "not enough plasma",
        "choicethree": "not enough white blood cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The average pulse of a healthy adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": " 60 to 80 beats/min",
        "choiceone": " 30 to 50 beats/min",
        "choicetwo": " 90 to 100 beats/min",
        "choicethree": "110 to 150 beats/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With a heart rate of 72 beats per minute and a stroke volume of 70 ml the\ncardiac output  is about:",
        "answer": "5 litres/min",
        "choiceone": "6 litres/min",
        "choicetwo": "7 litres/min",
        "choicethree": "8 litres/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "At rest the cardiac output (the quantity of blood the heart pumps in one\nminute) of an adult is approximately:",
        "answer": "5 litres/min",
        "choiceone": "450 ml/min",
        "choicetwo": "45 litres/min",
        "choicethree": "75 litres/min",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The heart muscle is supplied with blood from:",
        "answer": "the coronary arteries",
        "choiceone": "the auricles",
        "choicetwo": "ventricles",
        "choicethree": "the pulmonary veins",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal arterial blood-pressure of a healthy adult is (systolic/diastolic):",
        "answer": "120/80 mm Hg",
        "choiceone": " 80/20 mm Hg",
        "choicetwo": "180/120 mm Hg",
        "choicethree": "220/180 mm Hg",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\nThe blood-pressure which is measured during flight medical checks is the\npressure",
        "answer": "in the artery of the upper arm (representing the pressure at heart level)",
        "choiceone": "in all the blood-vessels of the body (representing the pressure in the\nwhole body)",
        "choicetwo": "in the muscles of the upper arm",
        "choicethree": "in the veins of the upper arm",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Blood-pressure depends on:\n1. the cardiac output\n2. the resistance of the capillaries\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers ?",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The blood-pressure depends on:\n1. the work of the heart\n2. the peripheral resistance\n3. the elasticity of the arterial walls\n4. the blood volume and viscosity",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1,3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in blood-pressure are measured by:",
        "answer": "pressoreceptors",
        "choiceone": "arteriols",
        "choicetwo": "adrenal glands",
        "choicethree": "pacemakers",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The pressoreceptors are located in",
        "answer": "the carotid and aortic arterial vessels",
        "choiceone": "the intestines",
        "choicetwo": "the heart",
        "choicethree": "the lungs",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the pressoreceptors signal a lowering of the blood-pressure there are\nadaptation mechanisms which result in:\n1. an increase of respiratory activity\n2. the arteriols to constrict\n3. an increase of cardiac output\n4. the heart rate to rise",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choiceone": "1,3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological effects of accelerations to the human body depend on:\n1. the duration of the G-forces\n2. the onset rate of the G-forces\n3. the magnitude of the G-forces\n4. the direction of the G-forces.",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicethree": "1and 4 are correct, 3 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive g will cause the blood-pressure in the brain to:",
        "answer": "decrease",
        "choiceone": "remain constant",
        "choicetwo": "increase",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During sustained positive G-forces the order of symptoms you can expect is:",
        "answer": "grey-out, tunnel vision, black-out and unconsciousness.",
        "choiceone": "unconsciousness, black-out, tunnel vision and grey out.",
        "choicetwo": "black-out, grey-out, tunnel vision and unconsciousness.",
        "choicethree": "grey-out, unconsciousness, black-out and tunnel vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal rate of breathing of an adult at rest is about:",
        "answer": "16 cycles per minute",
        "choiceone": "4 cycles per minute",
        "choicetwo": "32 cycles per minute",
        "choicethree": "72 cycles per minute",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The volume of air exchanged during a normal breathing cycle (tidal volume) is\nabout:",
        "answer": "500 ml of air",
        "choiceone": "350 ml of air",
        "choicetwo": "150 ml of air",
        "choicethree": " 75 ml of air",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The primary factor in controlling the rate and depth of breathing is the:",
        "answer": "pressure of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choiceone": "partial pressure of nitrogen",
        "choicetwo": "partial pressure of oxygen in the blood",
        "choicethree": "total air pressure in the blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The transfer of oxygen from the alveoli to the blood can be described by:",
        "answer": "the law of diffusion",
        "choiceone": "Boyle's Law",
        "choicetwo": "Dalton's Law",
        "choicethree": "Henry's Law",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The transfer of carbon dioxide from the blood to the alveoli can be described\nby:",
        "answer": "the law of diffusion",
        "choiceone": "Boyles Law",
        "choicetwo": "Dalton's Law",
        "choicethree": "Henry's Law",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the alveoli is:",
        "answer": "lower than in the blood",
        "choiceone": "the same as in the atmospheric air",
        "choicetwo": "higher than the pressure of carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choicethree": "lower than the pressure of carbon dioxide in the atmospheric air.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli",
        "choicethree": "oxygen in the cells",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pressurized cabin helps to prevent:\n1. decompression sickness\n2 .the problem of expansion of gases in the intestines\n3. hypoxia\n4. coronary disease",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct.",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up\nto:",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:",
        "answer": "the partial oxygen pressure is lower than at sea level.",
        "choiceone": "the composition of the blood changes",
        "choicetwo": "the composition of the air is different from sea level",
        "choicethree": "the percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Saturation of oxygen in the blood at sea level is approximately 98%. This\nsaturation decreases with:\n1. decreasing air pressure\n2. carbon monoxide poisoning\n3. increasing altitude\n4. increasing air pressure",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 4 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is a situation in which the cells",
        "answer": "have a shortage of oxygen",
        "choiceone": "are saturated with nitrogen",
        "choicetwo": "are saturated with oxygen",
        "choicethree": "have a shortage of carbon dioxide",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The severity of hypoxia depends on the:\n1. rate of decompression\n2. physical fitness\n3. flight level\n4. individual tolerance",
        "answer": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 and 4 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning hypoxia is correct?",
        "answer": "It is a potential threat to safety.",
        "choiceone": "It is never a problem at altitudes below 25.000 ft.",
        "choicetwo": "It activates the senses and makes them function better.",
        "choicethree": "It has little effect on the body, because the body can always compensate\nfor it.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Early symptoms of hypoxia could be:\n1. euphoria\n2. decreased rate and depth of breathing\n3. lack of concentration\n4. visual disturbances",
        "answer": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the most dangerous symptoms of hypoxia concerning flight safety is:",
        "answer": "impaired judgement",
        "choiceone": "reduced coordination of limb movements, causing the pilot to spin",
        "choicetwo": "cyanosis, reducing then pilots ability to hear",
        "choicethree": "hyperventilation, causing emotional stress",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following symptoms can indicate hypoxia?\n1. Blue lips and finger nails.\n2. Euphoria.\n3. Flatulence.\n4 .Unconsciousness..",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct.",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct.",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4 are correct.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the functions below, which is the most sensitive to hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Night vision.",
        "choiceone": "Motor coordination.",
        "choicetwo": "Hearing.",
        "choicethree": "Speech.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You are crossing the Alps in a non-pressurised aircraft at an altitude of 15.000\nfeet. You do not use the oxygen mask because you feel fine. This is unsafe,\nbecause:",
        "answer": "your judgement could be impaired",
        "choiceone": "the blood-pressure can get too high",
        "choicetwo": "the blood-pressure can get too low",
        "choicethree": "you will get the bends",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During a night flight at 10,000 feet you notice that your visual acuity has\ndecreased. In this case you can increase your acuity by:",
        "answer": "breathing extra oxygen through the oxygen mask.",
        "choiceone": "closing one eye",
        "choicetwo": "scanning sectors of the field of vision",
        "choicethree": "dim the instrument lights",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During flight all crewmembers have one or more of the following symptoms:\n1. blue lips\n2. mental disturbances\n3. tingling sensations in arms and/or legs\n4. reduction of peripheral vision\nWhich is the possible cause?",
        "answer": "Hypoxia.",
        "choiceone": "Glaucoma.",
        "choicetwo": "Hypothermia.",
        "choicethree": "Hypoglycaemia.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which measure(s) will help to compensate for hypoxia?\n1. Descend below 10 000 FT.\n2. Breathe 100 % oxygen.\n3. Climb to or above 10 000 FT.\n4. Reduce physical activities.",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "only 1 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:",
        "answer": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft",
        "choiceone": "relying on the body's built in warning system recognizing any stage of\nhypoxia",
        "choicetwo": "swallowing, yawing and applying the Valsalva method",
        "choicethree": "not exceeding a cabin pressure altitude of 20000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot should not fly immediately after donating blood because:",
        "answer": "you have an increased susceptibility to fainting",
        "choiceone": "the chance you get the bends is higher after blood-donation",
        "choicetwo": "your blood-pressure is too low after blood-donation",
        "choicethree": "your heart rate is too low after blood-donation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:",
        "answer": "an increased lung ventilation",
        "choiceone": "a too high percentage of nitrogen in the blood",
        "choicetwo": "a decreased lung ventilation",
        "choicethree": "a too high percentage of oxygen in the blood.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial\noxygen pressure (i.e. when climbing a high mountain)",
        "choiceone": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If somebody starts breathing faster and deeper without physiological need",
        "answer": "the blood turns more alkaline",
        "choiceone": "the blood turns more acid",
        "choicetwo": "the acid-base balance of the blood will not change",
        "choicethree": "the blood pressure in the brain will rise significantly",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When hyperventilating you should:",
        "answer": "control your rate and depth of breathing",
        "choiceone": "descend",
        "choicetwo": "apply the Valsalva method",
        "choicethree": "use the oxygen mask",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can overcome hyperventilation by:",
        "answer": "controlling the rate and depth of breathing and/or breathing into a bag",
        "choiceone": "depending on instruments",
        "choicetwo": "increasing the rate and depth of breathing to eliminate harmful carbon\ndioxide",
        "choicethree": "the use of drugs stabilizing blood pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You can overcome hyperventilation by breathing into a plastic or paper bag.\nThe intention is:",
        "answer": "to raise the level of CO2 in the blood as fast as possible",
        "choiceone": "to prevent you from exhaling too much oxygen",
        "choicetwo": "to increase the amount of nitrogen in the lungs",
        "choicethree": "to reduce blood pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rising the perceptual threshold of a sensory organ means:",
        "answer": "a lesser sensitivity",
        "choiceone": "a greater sensitivity",
        "choicetwo": "a greater selectivity",
        "choicethree": "a lesser selectivity",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Subcutaneous pressure receptors are stimulated by:",
        "answer": "the pressure created on the corresponding body parts when sitting,\nstanding or lying down",
        "choiceone": "a touch on the skin indicating the true vertical",
        "choicetwo": "environmental stressors",
        "choicethree": "the condition of the body itself",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The proprioceptors do not orient an individual to his/her surroundings, but\ninforms him/her of",
        "answer": "the relative motion and relative position of his body parts",
        "choiceone": "a touch on the skin",
        "choicetwo": "our surroundings",
        "choicethree": "the condition in the body itself",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype and involuntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of\nreceptors is called:",
        "answer": "reflex",
        "choiceone": "data processing",
        "choicetwo": "control system",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The amount of light which strikes the retina is controlled by:",
        "answer": "the pupil",
        "choiceone": "the ciliary body",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea",
        "choicethree": "the lens",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the lens to change its shape is called:",
        "answer": "accommodation",
        "choiceone": "binocular vision",
        "choicetwo": "depth perception",
        "choicethree": "adaptation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The mechanism of accommodation is caused by:",
        "answer": "the functioning of the ciliary muscle around the lens",
        "choiceone": "the elasticity of the optic nerves",
        "choicetwo": "the functioning of the muscles of the eye",
        "choicethree": "the diameter of the pupil",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia is:",
        "answer": "long sightedness linked with age",
        "choiceone": "short sightedness",
        "choicetwo": "myopia",
        "choicethree": "high intraocular pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual acuity during flight at high altitudes can be affected by:\n1. anaemia\n2. smoking in the cockpit\n3. carbon monoxide poisoning\n4. hypoxia",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Glaucoma\n1. can lead to total blindness\n2. can lead to undetected reduction of the visual field\n3. reduces visual acuity in its final stage",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 is correct, 2 and 3 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Glaucoma is:",
        "answer": "high intra-ocular pressure",
        "choiceone": "disturbed colour vision",
        "choicetwo": "disturbed adaptation",
        "choicethree": "disturbed night vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The peripheral vision is important for:",
        "answer": "detecting moving objects",
        "choiceone": "visual acuity",
        "choicetwo": "binocular vision",
        "choicethree": "colour vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Although we have a field of vision of more than 180\u00b0 it is important during\nflight to use the scanning technique, because",
        "answer": "only in the foveal area resolution is good enough to see an object clearly",
        "choiceone": "it is tiring to look continually in the same direction",
        "choicetwo": "only in the peripheral area of the retina resolution is good enough to see\nan object clearly",
        "choicethree": "the reduction in the field of vision with decreasing altitude is due to a\nlack of vitamin A",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The time an eye needs to adapt fully to the dark is about:",
        "answer": "25 - 30 minutes",
        "choiceone": "5 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "10 minutes",
        "choicethree": "10 seconds",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The photosensitive cells being responsible for night vision are called:",
        "answer": "the rods",
        "choiceone": "the fovea",
        "choicetwo": "the cones",
        "choicethree": "the cones and the rods",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself\nfrom flashblindness by:\na) turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\nb) looking inside the cockpit\nc) wearing sunglasses\nd) using blinds or curtains when installed",
        "answer": "a), b), c) and d) are correct",
        "choiceone": "a), b) and c) are correct, d) is false",
        "choicetwo": "a) and b) are correct, c) and d) are false",
        "choicethree": "c) and d) are correct, a) and b) are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which scanning technique should be used when flying at night?",
        "answer": "Look to the side (10 - 15 deg) of the object.",
        "choiceone": "Look directly at the object.",
        "choicetwo": "Blink your eyes.",
        "choicethree": "Look with one eye.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Eustachian tube connects:",
        "answer": "the middle ear and the throat",
        "choiceone": "the auditory duct and the inner ear",
        "choicetwo": "the semi circular canals",
        "choicethree": "the middle ear and the inner ear",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Conductive hearing loss can be caused by:\n1. damage to the ossicles in the middle ear caused by infection or trauma\n2. a damage of the auditory nerve\n3. an obstruction in the outer ear\n4. a ruptured tympanic membrane",
        "answer": "1, 3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choiceone": "2, 3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicethree": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss (NIHL) is caused by:",
        "answer": "damage to the sensitive membrane in the cochlea due to overexposure\nto noise",
        "choiceone": "a blocked Eustachian tube",
        "choicetwo": "pressure differences on both sides of the eardrum",
        "choicethree": "reduced mobility of the ossicles",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Excessive exposure to noise damages:",
        "answer": "the sensitive membrane in the cochlea",
        "choiceone": "the semi circular canals",
        "choicetwo": "the ossicles",
        "choicethree": "the eardrum",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The inner ear is able to perceive:\n1. angular acceleration\n2. linear acceleration\n3. Noise",
        "answer": "1 and 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicethree": "2 is correct, 1 and 3 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Angular accelerations are perceived by:",
        "answer": "the semi circular canals",
        "choiceone": "the cochlea",
        "choicetwo": "the otholiths",
        "choicethree": "the receptors in the skin and the joints",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The otoliths in the inner ear are sensitive to:",
        "answer": "linear acceleration and gravity",
        "choiceone": "angular acceleration",
        "choicetwo": "angular speed",
        "choicethree": "constant speed only",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Visual disturbances can be caused by:\n1. hyperventilation\n2. hypoxia\n3. hypertension\n4. fatigue",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disorientation is more likely to occur when the pilot is:\n1. flying in IMC\n2. frequently changing between inside and outside references\n3. flying from IMC into VMC\n4. approaching over still water at night",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive linear acceleration when flying in IMC may cause a false sensation of:",
        "answer": "pitching up",
        "choiceone": "pitching down",
        "choicetwo": "apparent sideward movement of objects in the field of vision",
        "choicethree": "vertigo",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Linear acceleration when flying straight and level in IMC may give the illusion\nof:",
        "answer": "climbing",
        "choiceone": "descending",
        "choicetwo": "yawing",
        "choicethree": "spinning",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Coriolis illusion, causing spatial disorientation is the result of:",
        "answer": "simultaneous head movements during aircraft manoeuvres",
        "choiceone": "undergoing positive G",
        "choicetwo": "gazing in the direction of a flashing light",
        "choicethree": "normal deterioration of the semicircular canals with age",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When turning in IMC , head movements should be avoided as much as\npossible. This is a prevention against:",
        "answer": "coriolis illusion",
        "choiceone": "autokinesis",
        "choicetwo": "oculogyral illusion",
        "choicethree": "pressure vertigo",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot, trying to pick up a fallen object from the cockpit floor during a tight\nturn, experiences:",
        "answer": "coriolis illusion",
        "choiceone": "autokinetic illusion",
        "choicetwo": "barotrauma",
        "choicethree": "pressure vertigo",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Empty field myopia is caused by:",
        "answer": "lack of distant focal points",
        "choiceone": "atmospheric perspective",
        "choicetwo": "ozone at altitude",
        "choicethree": "flying over mountainous terrain",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot is starring at an isolated stationary light for several seconds in\nthe dark he might get the illusion that:",
        "answer": "the light is moving",
        "choiceone": "the size of the light is varying",
        "choicetwo": "the intensity of the light is varying",
        "choicethree": "the colour of the light is varying",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When you stare at a single light against the dark (i.e.. an isolated star) you will\nfind the light appears to move after some time. This phenomenon is called:",
        "answer": "autokinetic phenomenon",
        "choiceone": "black hole illusion",
        "choicetwo": "coriolis illusion",
        "choicethree": "leans",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How may haze effect perception?",
        "answer": "Objects seem to be further away than in reality.",
        "choiceone": "Objects will give better contrast.",
        "choicetwo": "Haze makes the eyes to focus at infinity",
        "choicethree": "Objects seem to be closer than in reality.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 'Black hole' phenomenon occurs during approaches at night and over\nwater, jungle or desert. When the pilot is lacking visual cues other than those\nof the aerodrome there is an illusion of",
        "answer": "being too high and too far away, dropping low and landing short",
        "choiceone": "being too close, landing long",
        "choicetwo": "climbing",
        "choicethree": "being too low, flying a steeper approach than normal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You fly VFR from your home base (runway width 27 m), to an international\nairport (runway width 45 m). On reaching your destination there is a risk of\nperforming a:",
        "answer": "high approach with overshoot",
        "choiceone": "high approach with undershoot",
        "choicetwo": "low approach with overshoot",
        "choicethree": "low approach with undershoot",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You fly VFR from your home base (runway width 45 m) to a small airfield\n(runway width 27 m). On reaching your destination there is a risk of\nperforming a:",
        "answer": "low approach with undershoot",
        "choiceone": "high approach with overshoot",
        "choicetwo": "high approach with undershoot",
        "choicethree": "low approach with overshoot",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "1. In case of conflicting information you can always trust your\nSeat-of-the-Pants-Sense.\n2. In case of conflicting information between the sensory organs and the\ninstruments you must believe the instruments.",
        "answer": "1 is false, 2 is correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial\ndisorientation?",
        "answer": "Rely entirely on the indications of the flight instruments.",
        "choiceone": "Tilt your head to the side to get better information from the semicircular\ncanals.",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense.",
        "choicethree": "Get adapted to low levels of illumination before flying and use off-center\nvision all the time.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a pilot prevent spatial disorientation in flight?",
        "answer": "Establish and maintain a good instrument cross check.",
        "choiceone": "Always try to catch outside visual cues.",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on good situational awareness believing your natural senses.",
        "choicethree": "Rely on the \"seat of the pants\" sense.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are subjected to an illusion during night flying you should:",
        "answer": "continue on instruments",
        "choiceone": "dim the cockpit lighting",
        "choicetwo": "scan the surroundings",
        "choicethree": "use your oxygen mask",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are disorientated during night flying you must:",
        "answer": "rely on your instruments",
        "choiceone": "look outside",
        "choicetwo": "descend",
        "choicethree": "check your rate of breathing - do not breathe too fast",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A passenger complains about a painful inflated belly at 8.000 feet. You advise\nhim to:\n1. unbuckle and massage the belly\n2. stand up and let go the gases out of the intestines\n3. eat less gas forming food and avoid carbonhydrated beverages before flight\nin the future\n4. drink a lot of water throughout the flight",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 not advisable",
        "choicethree": "only 4 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "On ascent the gases in the digestive tract will",
        "answer": "expand",
        "choiceone": "stay the same",
        "choicetwo": "shrink",
        "choicethree": "be absorbed by tissues and blood",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having a serious cold it is better not to fly, due to the extra risk of:\n1. flatulence\n2. pain in the ear during descent\n3. vertigo\n4. pain in the nasal sinuses",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1,3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having a serious cold, you are going to fly. What can you expect?",
        "answer": "pain in the sinuses",
        "choiceone": "bends",
        "choicetwo": "chokes",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pain in the middle ear during descent may be eased by:",
        "answer": "levelling off and possibly climbing",
        "choiceone": "blocking the effected ear with the palm of your hand",
        "choicetwo": "increasing the rate of descent",
        "choicethree": "using an oxygen mask",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which symptom does not belong to the following list:",
        "answer": "leans",
        "choiceone": "bends",
        "choicetwo": "chokes",
        "choicethree": "creeps",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The symptoms caused by gas bubbles under the skin following a\ndecompression are called:",
        "answer": "creeps",
        "choiceone": "bends",
        "choicetwo": "chokes",
        "choicethree": "leans",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms caused by gas bubbles in the lungs, following a decompression\nare called:",
        "answer": "chokes",
        "choiceone": "bends",
        "choicetwo": "creeps",
        "choicethree": "leans",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some hours after a rapid decompression at FL 300 you experience pain in the\njoints. Which of following answers is correct?",
        "answer": "You should ask for medical advice (flight surgeon) since this is a\nsymptom of decompression sickness.",
        "choiceone": "This symptom indicates decompression sickness and will disappear\nwhen you take some exercise.",
        "choicetwo": "This phenomenon is treated by physiotherapy.",
        "choicethree": "This phenomenon is treated by breathing 100% nitrogen.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tolerance to decompression sickness is decreased by:\n1. SCUBA diving\n2. Obesity\n3. Age\n4. Body height",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "2 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "only 4 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decompression symptoms are caused by:",
        "answer": "dissolved gases from tissues and fluids of the body",
        "choiceone": "low carbon dioxide pressure of inhaled air",
        "choicetwo": "low oxygen pressure of inhaled air",
        "choicethree": "release of locked gases from joints",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the event of rapid decompression the first action for the flight deck crew is:",
        "answer": "don oxygen masks and ensure oxygen flow",
        "choiceone": "descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA",
        "choicetwo": "transmit mayday call",
        "choicethree": "carry out check for structural damage",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of\ndecompression sickness:\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing",
        "answer": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decompression sickness can normally be prevented by:\n1. avoiding cabin altitudes above 18 000 FT\n2. maintaining cabin pressure below 8 000FT when flying at high altitudes\n3. performing physical exercises before and during the flight\n4. breathing 100 % oxygen for 30 min prior and during the flight",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false",
        "choicethree": "only 3 is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Following a rapid decompression at 30.000 feet, the time of useful\nconsciousness would be about:",
        "answer": "between 45 seconds and 1 minute 30 seconds",
        "choiceone": "3 to 5 minutes",
        "choicetwo": "5 to 10 minutes",
        "choicethree": "10 to 12 minutes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After a rapid decompression at 35 000 feet, the time of useful consciousness\nis about:",
        "answer": "30 to 60 seconds",
        "choiceone": "15 seconds or less",
        "choicetwo": "5 minutes.",
        "choicethree": "10 minutes.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of\ntime before flying again. This period is at least:",
        "answer": "24 hours",
        "choiceone": " 6 hours",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours",
        "choicethree": "48 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:",
        "answer": "decompression sickness without having a decompression",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "stress",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding alcohol in the human body?",
        "answer": "Judgement and decision making can be affected even by a small amount\nof alcohol.",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases visual acuity.",
        "choicetwo": "An increase of altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.",
        "choicethree": "When drinking coffee, the human body metabolizes alcohol at a faster\nrate than normal.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during\nflight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Smoking cigarettes reduces the capability of the blood to carry oxygen. This\nis because:",
        "answer": "haemoglobin has a greater affinity for carbon monoxide than it has for\noxygen",
        "choiceone": "carbon monoxide in the smoke of cigarettes assists diffusion of oxygen\nin the alveoli",
        "choicetwo": "carbon monoxide increases the partial pressure of oxygen in the alveoli",
        "choicethree": "the smoke of one cigarette can cause an obstruction in the respiratory\ntract",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "CO (carbon monoxide) present in the smoke of cigarettes can lead to:\n1. reduction of time of useful consciousness\n2. hypoxia at a lower altitude than normal",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide in the human body can lead to:\n1. loss of muscular power\n2. headache\n3. impaired judgement\n4. pain in the joints\n5. loss of consciousness",
        "answer": "1, 2 , 3 and 5 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 4 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "choicethree": "1, 2, 3, 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Adverse effects of carbon monoxide increase as:",
        "answer": "altitude increases",
        "choiceone": "altitude decreases",
        "choicetwo": "air pressure increases",
        "choicethree": "relative humidity decreases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The human circadian rhythm is based on a cycle of about:",
        "answer": "25 hours",
        "choiceone": "1.5 hours",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours",
        "choicethree": "48 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disturbance of the biological clock appears after a:\n1. bad night's sleep\n2. day flight Amsterdam - New York\n3. day flight Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The effects of sleep deprivation on performance:\n1. increase with altitude\n2. decrease with altitude\n3. increase with higher workload\n4. decrease with higher workload\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements ?",
        "answer": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sleeplessness or the disruption of sleeping patterns\n1. can lead to symptoms of drowsiness, irritability and lack of concentration\n2. will make an individual more prone to make errors",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is not correct, 2 is correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct, 2 is not correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both not correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n1. A person experiencing sleep loss is unlikely to be aware of personal\nperformance degradation\n2. Performance loss may be present up to 20 minutes after awaking from a\nshort sleep (nap)",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sleep cycles repeat during the course of a night's sleep.\n1. Each succeeding cycle contains a greater amount of REM-sleep.\n2. Frequent interruption of the REM-sleep may be harmful.",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 isfalse, 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n1. REM-sleep becomes shorter with any repeated sleep cycle during the night.\n2. REM-sleep is more important for the regeneration of mental functions than\nall the other sleep stages are.",
        "answer": "1 is false, 2 is correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is correct, 2 is false",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stress reaction is:",
        "answer": "the non-specific response of the body to demands placed on a person",
        "choiceone": "the specific response of the body to demands placed on a person",
        "choicetwo": "the non-specific stimuli causing a human body to respond",
        "choicethree": "the specific stimuli causing a human body to respond",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:",
        "answer": "distress",
        "choiceone": "coping stress",
        "choicetwo": "eustress",
        "choicethree": "stressors",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stress will effect:\n1. attention\n2. concentration\n3. memory\n4. judgment",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The biological reaction to stress is identical regardless of the cause of stress.\nThis mechanism occurs in three phases and is referred to, by Selye, as the\n\"General Adaptation Syndrome\".\nThe sequence is:",
        "answer": "alarm phase - resistance phase - exhaustion phase",
        "choiceone": "alarm phase - denial phase - exhaustion phase",
        "choicetwo": "exhaustion phase - resistance phase - adaptation phase",
        "choicethree": "resistance phase - exhaustion phase - recovery phase",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the different phases of the \"General Adaptation Syndrome\"\nwhich of the following statement/s is/are correct?\n1. During the alarm phase stress hormones (i.e. adrenalin) will cause a\nmassive release of glucose into the blood, an acceleration of pulse and blood\npressure as well as an increase in the rate and depth of breathing\n2. During the resistance phase the parasympathetic system uses a different\ntype of hormone (cortisol) assisting for the conversion of fat into sugar.\n3. During the exhaustion phase the body has to be given time to eliminate the\nwaste products which have been generated excessively during the two\npreceding phases.",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false",
        "choicetwo": "only 1 is correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If coping with a stress situation is impossible, one will remain in the state of:",
        "answer": "distress",
        "choiceone": "adaptation",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia",
        "choicethree": "eustress",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements concerning stress are true ?\n1. Adaptation is a new state of equilibrium after having coped with a stressful\nsituation.\n2. An individual's anticipation of the situation and his/her perceived abilities\nto cope with it will determine the type and strength of stress.",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both true",
        "choiceone": "1 is true, 2 is false",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, 2 is true",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The level at which a pilot will experience a situation as stressful",
        "answer": "depends on the individual's perception of available abilities in\ncomparison to the perceived demands",
        "choiceone": "does not depend on his capacity to absorb information",
        "choicetwo": "depends on the level of demand but not on individual interpretation of\nthe situational demands",
        "choicethree": "depends on self-confidence alone",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive\nsense and by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot\nlooking forward to what may happen",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n1. Psychosomatic means that mental and/or emotional stressors can be\nmanifested in physical reactions.\n2. Psychosomatic means that a physical problem is always followed by\npsychological stress.",
        "answer": "1 is correct, 2 is false",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is false, 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whilst flying a coordinated turn, most of your activity is",
        "answer": "skill based behaviour",
        "choiceone": "coping behaviour",
        "choicetwo": "knowledge based behaviour",
        "choicethree": "rule based behaviour",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The choice of the moment you select flaps depending on situation and\nconditions of the landing is:",
        "answer": "skill and/or rule based behaviour",
        "choiceone": "knowledge based behaviour",
        "choicetwo": "pressure based behaviour",
        "choicethree": "automated behaviour",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a\ncritical situation",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is\nlimited anyway",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will\nbe evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one's mind, contradictory information may not get the\nattention it really needs.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of\ninformation to the central decision maker.",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 are correct",
        "choiceone": "1and 3 are correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In an abnormal situation the pilot has an apparently correct explanation for\nthe problem. The chance that he/she now ignores or devalues other relevant\ninformation, not fitting into his/her mental picture is:",
        "answer": "not usual",
        "choiceone": "very rare",
        "choicetwo": "not applicable with old and experienced pilots",
        "choicethree": "not possible since correct training should have eliminated this problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n1. Interesting information is easier to take into consideration for creating a\nmental picture than boring information.\n2.The sequence in which information is presented is also important for the\nuse the pilot makes of it.",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is not correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is not correct, 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both not correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If someone hyperventilates due to stress his/her blood will become:",
        "answer": "more alkaline",
        "choiceone": "less saturated with oxygen",
        "choicetwo": "more saturated with carbon dioxide",
        "choicethree": "more acid",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "1. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is not correct",
        "choicetwo": "1 is not correct, 2 is correct",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both not correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide poisoning can be treated by:",
        "answer": "increasing the amount of oxygen being physically dissolved in the blood",
        "choiceone": "decreasing the amount of oxygen being combined with the hemoglobin\nin the blood",
        "choicetwo": "increasing the amount of nitrogen being physically dissolved in the\nblood",
        "choicethree": "breathing into a paper bag",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ozone in the air of a pressurized cabin can be eliminated by:",
        "answer": "ozone-converters",
        "choiceone": "avoiding flights along the equator",
        "choicetwo": "climbing to altitudes above 45,000 ft",
        "choicethree": "spraying detergents",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The exchange of gases between the alveoli and the blood is due to:",
        "answer": "diffusion",
        "choiceone": "changes in atmospheric pressure",
        "choicetwo": "inspiration",
        "choicethree": "physical exercise",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The circulation of blood:\n1. transports oxygen to the body cells\n2. withdraws waste products from the cells\n3. conveys nutrients to the cells\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1, 2 and 3",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During hyperventilation:",
        "answer": "acidity level of the blood is reduced",
        "choiceone": "alkalinity level of the blood is reduced",
        "choicetwo": "oxygen concentration of the blood is below normal",
        "choicethree": "nitrogen concentration of the blood is above normal",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxic hypoxia may be caused by:\n1. climbing to a high altitude without using additional oxygen\n2. malfunction in the oxygen supply system\n3. loss of cabin pressurization at high altitude\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following gases is fundamentally responsible for decompression\nsickness?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen.",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen.",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide.",
        "choicethree": "Sodium.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the functional connection between neurones?",
        "answer": "Synapse.",
        "choiceone": "By-pass.",
        "choicetwo": "Interconnnection.",
        "choicethree": "Occlusion.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Glaucoma is due to:",
        "answer": "Increase in pressure of the liquid within the eye",
        "choiceone": "Drop in pressure of the liquid around the eye",
        "choicetwo": "Damage to the eyeball due to high altitude",
        "choicethree": "Excess light on the eyeball",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can cause spatial disorientation?",
        "answer": "False perception of orientation of the aircraft with respect to spatial\nreferences.",
        "choiceone": "Damage to the receptor cells in the eyes.",
        "choicetwo": "Reference to well-defined external visual references, such as the\nhorizon.",
        "choicethree": "Flying in clear daylight conditions.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by presbycusis?",
        "answer": "Gradual loss of hearing with age.",
        "choiceone": "Total loss of hearing in one ear due to use of a headset in the cockpit.",
        "choicetwo": "Total loss of hearing in both ears due to disease.",
        "choicethree": "Gradual onset of long-sightedness with age.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When might a pilot have the sensation of a nose-low attitude?",
        "answer": "When decelerating in straight, horizontal flight.",
        "choiceone": "During linear acceleration.",
        "choicetwo": "When turning (angular acceleration).",
        "choicethree": "When climbing at greater than 2000 FT / min",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The unique organisation of characteristics which determine the typical or\nstandard behaviour of an individual is known as:",
        "answer": "personality",
        "choiceone": "development",
        "choicetwo": "heredity",
        "choicethree": "learning",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The causes of human error can be abundant and complex. Which of the\nfollowing factors could contribute to human error?\n1. Personality.\n2. Motivation and attitudes.\n3. Emotional state.\n4. External environmental factors.\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the external factors that may contribute to an error, cockpit noise and\nthe restriction of the field of view due to windscreen design correspond to:",
        "answer": "ergonomic factors.",
        "choiceone": "organisational factors.",
        "choicetwo": "psychobiological factors.",
        "choicethree": "social factors.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Organisational factors which affect or may have some influence on human\nerror are:\n1. malfunction of technical systems.\n2. fuel-saving policies.\n3. rostering.\n4. weather phenomena.\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "2 and 3",
        "choiceone": "1 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The autocratic leadership style is synonymous with:",
        "answer": "an authoritarian style",
        "choiceone": "a democratic style",
        "choicetwo": "an anarchic style",
        "choicethree": "a \"laissez-faire\" style",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What human function is most sensitive to lack of oxygen?",
        "answer": "Night vision.",
        "choiceone": "Motor co-ordination.",
        "choicetwo": "Hearing.",
        "choicethree": "Touch.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To avoid incapacity due to gastro-intestinal problems, it is recommended that\na simple, easily digested meal before boarding the aircraft should be\naccompanied by:",
        "answer": "non-carbonated water",
        "choiceone": "wine or beer",
        "choicetwo": "carbonated water.",
        "choicethree": "no drinks, as fluids are not important",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The dry atmosphere of the flight deck may cause dehydration, which may lead\nto a reduction in the ability to pay attention. To prevent this, it is appropriate\nto:",
        "answer": "drink sufficient non-carbonated liquids",
        "choiceone": "drink plenty of coffee",
        "choicetwo": "drink cool cola drinks",
        "choicethree": "drink tea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Caffeine may cause an increase in cardiac rate, restlessness/nervousness,\ninsomnia, anxiety and intestinal irritability. Excessive consumption is\nconsidered to be in excess of:",
        "answer": "250 mg/day",
        "choiceone": "3 mg/day",
        "choicetwo": "40-65 mg/day",
        "choicethree": "150 mg/day",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the case of changes to circadian rhythms, the readjustment to a new time\nzone:",
        "answer": "is most rapid when flying westbound",
        "choiceone": "is most rapid when flying eastbound",
        "choicetwo": "is the same in both westbound and eastbound flights",
        "choicethree": "occurs immediately, as circadian rhythms do not change depending on\ndirection of flying",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about acute or chronic fatigue is INCORRECT?",
        "answer": "Acute fatigue generally has psychological roots.",
        "choiceone": "Chronic fatigue may be caused by inadequate recuperation from periods\nof acute fatigue.",
        "choicetwo": "Chronic fatigue may lead to a person being totally apathetic and\nindifferent to what goes on around them.",
        "choicethree": "Acute fatigue is felt after a period of significant exertion or emotional\nexcitement.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following statements regarding stress, which is correct?",
        "answer": "Stress may be positive, fatigue is always negative.",
        "choiceone": "Stress and fatigue are synonymous.",
        "choicetwo": "Stress and anxiety are the same in every sense.",
        "choicethree": "Stress always has a negative effect on performance.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Physical exercise in high temperatures (tropical climates) may:",
        "answer": "cause painful muscle and abdominal cramps",
        "choiceone": "cause the pilot to collapse, due to an excess of fluid in the body",
        "choicetwo": "increase a pilot's resistance to decompression sickness",
        "choicethree": "cause dysentery",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Medical conditions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and\ndiabetes are associated with:",
        "answer": "obesity",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa",
        "choicetwo": "cholera",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To resynchronize a circadian rhythm, it takes more time after:",
        "answer": "eastbound flights",
        "choiceone": "westbound flights",
        "choicetwo": "north-south flights",
        "choicethree": "south-north flights",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Environmental sources of stress in the cockpit could be:\n1. noise and vibration\n2. acceleration\n3. radiation\n4. extreme temperatures\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "1 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n1. not eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. always peel fruit\n3. only eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2",
        "choicetwo": "1, 2 and 3",
        "choicethree": "2 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "By 'long duration acceleration', we mean that it lasts more than:",
        "answer": "1 second",
        "choiceone": "20 seconds",
        "choicetwo": "1 minute",
        "choicethree": "5 minutes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Night vision is significantly reduced (i.e. a loss of more than 25%) at 15,000 FT\nin which stage of hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Compensatory",
        "choiceone": "Indifferent",
        "choicetwo": "Clinical manifestation phase",
        "choicethree": "Anaemic phase",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this\nphysical stress?",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Up to what altitude is blood oxygen saturation reduction unlikely to affect a\npilot's judgement?",
        "answer": "10,000 FT",
        "choiceone": "20,000 FT",
        "choicetwo": "25,000 FT",
        "choicethree": "30,000 FT",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "By what action could the pressure gradient between the middle and the outer\near be balanced?",
        "answer": "By swallowing.",
        "choiceone": "By breathing in.",
        "choicetwo": "By breathing out.",
        "choicethree": "By coughing.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Barotrauma is caused by an increase or decrease in the volume of the gases\ncontained in the body's cavities. Which, in practice, are the most frequent\nlocations of such problems?",
        "answer": "Facial sinuses, middle ear and dental cavities",
        "choiceone": "Inner ear, facial sinuses and stomach",
        "choicetwo": "Facial sinuses, outer ear and stomach",
        "choicethree": "Dental cavities, outer ear and eyes",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The system which controls breathing, digestion, heart rate, etc., over which\nthere is no voluntary control, is:",
        "answer": "the autonomic nervous system",
        "choiceone": "the local nervous system",
        "choicetwo": "the critical nervous system",
        "choicethree": "non-existent, as all these functions are under conscious control",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs in:",
        "answer": "presbyopia",
        "choiceone": "myopia",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia",
        "choicethree": "astigmatism",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What factors can lead to a deterioration in vision?\n1.  Hypoxia\n2.  Smoking\n3.  Poor diet, lacking Vitamin A\n4.  Exposure to bright lights\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "1 and 3",
        "choicetwo": "2 and 4",
        "choicethree": "1, 3 and 4",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The damaging effects of noise on the pilot depends on:\n1.  The intensity of the noise\n2.  The frequency of the noise\n3.  The exposure time to noise\n4.  Proper use of the headset in the cockpit\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements?",
        "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
        "choiceone": "2, 3 and 4",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4",
        "choicethree": "3 only",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can vertigo be prevented in conditions of good visibility?",
        "answer": "By looking at the horizon",
        "choiceone": "By closing the eyes momentarily",
        "choicetwo": "By looking approximately 5\u00b0 to one side of an object",
        "choicethree": "By avoiding blinking",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent empty field myopia at higher altitudes:",
        "answer": "it is recommended that a pilot uses short sharp scans, or periodically\nfocuses on a distant object such as a wingtip or cloud edge",
        "choiceone": "it is recommended that a pilot focuses on an object known to be\napproximately one metre away",
        "choicetwo": "one should concentrate only on instruments",
        "choicethree": "one should book an appointment with an opthalmologist as soon as\npossible",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Waiting for takeoff on the runway, a pilot is informed by the tower that the tail\nwind component is 12 kt. According to the manual, the limitation is 10 kt max.\nThe pilot makes a decision to take-off anyway, as the runway is long.",
        "answer": "This is a violation.",
        "choiceone": "This is an error of reasoning.",
        "choicetwo": "This is a decision error.",
        "choicethree": "This is neither an error or a violation - the pilot is using his initiative.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "On approach, by day, in snowy conditions, without reference to glideslope\ninformation:",
        "answer": "judgement of height is extremely difficult",
        "choiceone": "there is a risk of you underestimating your speed",
        "choicetwo": "estimation of height and distance is not a problem for a well-trained pilot",
        "choicethree": "there is a risk of you entering a spin",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to avoid hypoglycaemia:",
        "answer": "a pilot should eat regularly and ensure he/she has a balanced diet",
        "choiceone": "a pilot should never eat sugar or sweets",
        "choicetwo": "peanuts are recommended because of their high energy value",
        "choicethree": "a pilot should not take snacks between meals",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Night vision:",
        "answer": "requires up to 30 minutes to reach its best performance",
        "choiceone": "requires 5 minutes to reach its best performance",
        "choicetwo": "is insensitive to short duration light sources",
        "choicethree": "is insensitive to lightning flashes in storms",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot experiences difficulties in the control of his aircraft and consequently\nomits to monitor the fuel level. This is caused by:",
        "answer": "a lack of attention due to distraction",
        "choiceone": "a lack of alertness",
        "choicetwo": "both a lack of attention and a lack of alertness",
        "choicethree": "This pilot manages his attention well.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In tropical zones, it is recommended that:",
        "answer": "cold drinks be taken from sealed containers",
        "choiceone": "one uses ice cubes in cold drinks",
        "choicetwo": "one eats raw vegetables",
        "choicethree": "one eats fruit without peeling them, to ensure a supply of vitamins",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot meets the ground engineer in charge on the apron. Although the pilot\nhas not been through flight preparation yet, he nevertheless instructs the\nengineer as to the amount of fuel to be loaded, since he is used to flying this\nroute. This behaviour results from:",
        "answer": "a decision bias due to habits (frequency bias)",
        "choiceone": "a bias in selecting data",
        "choicetwo": "a confirmation bias",
        "choicethree": "a decision bias due to group (social) pressure",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before takeoff, a briefing:",
        "answer": "must be done systematically in order to refresh the memory of the crew\nmembers and to co-ordinate actions",
        "choiceone": "is not necessary when departing from home base because this is routine",
        "choicetwo": "is not required unless both crew members agree it is essential",
        "choicethree": "is not necessary if the crew members know each other",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In-flight incapacitation of a pilot is most frequently caused by:",
        "answer": "acute gastrointestinal disorders",
        "choiceone": "chronic pulmonary disorders",
        "choicetwo": "cardio-vascular disorders",
        "choicethree": "behavioural disorders",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When considering the eating-habits of pilots:",
        "answer": "breakfast should bring about 25% of the daily calorie intake",
        "choiceone": "low fibre and low protein/carbohydratediet is ideal",
        "choicetwo": "a heavy supper is best",
        "choicethree": "high intake of chocolate is recommended before flight to prevent\nreactional hypoglycemia",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "On experiencing a vestibular illusion in straight and level flight, it is\nrecommended that:",
        "answer": "you avoid head movements and rely on your instruments",
        "choiceone": "you tilt your head to the side opposite to the turn to nullify the stimulus\ncausing the illusion",
        "choicetwo": "you close your eyes for a moment so that the oculo-vestibular conflict\ndisappears",
        "choicethree": "you rely on your sensations only, as humans are much more reliable\nthan flight instruments",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person's attitudes define a set of learned dispositions (likes and dislikes)\nwhich:",
        "answer": "influence a person's reaction and response to people, situations, etc.",
        "choiceone": "is exactly the same as a person's personality",
        "choicetwo": "cannot be modified through training",
        "choicethree": "do not depend on a person's past experiences",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The low level of humidity found in a pressurised aircraft cabin:",
        "answer": "must be compensated for by drinking water before one gets thirsty",
        "choiceone": "must be compensated for by breathing in to a paper bag",
        "choicetwo": "requires a regular supply of water only for those who are in poor health.\nHealthy people compensate for this naturally.",
        "choicethree": "must be compensated for by a regular supply of coffee or tea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Planning:",
        "answer": "allows crew members to anticipate potential risky situations and decide\non possible responses",
        "choiceone": "is unnecessary in the cockpit, as crew members are so highly trained,\nthey will always know what to do in unusual situations",
        "choicetwo": "in the cockpit typically results in plans that are always easy to modify\nwhen things are not as anticipated",
        "choicethree": "is dangerous in the cockpit, as it interrupts flight crew creativity",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The resistance phase of stress:",
        "answer": "allows fats to be transformed into sugars, thereby prolonging the\nmobilization of energy in the body",
        "choiceone": "is characterised by the secretion of adrenalin, increased heart rate and\nblood pressure",
        "choicetwo": "may cause a person to die by stopping the defence mechanisms of the\nbody",
        "choicethree": "is very short duration and is unlikely to give a pilot the opportunity to\nresolve a problem",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The cornea and the crystalline lens of the eye:",
        "answer": "cause the convergence of light rays onto the retina",
        "choiceone": "keep the retina clean and healthy",
        "choicetwo": "allow for the regulation of the amount of light admitted into the eye",
        "choicethree": "permit the reception and conversion of visual stimuli to images\ninterpreted by the brain",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Free running circadian rhythms normally have a cycle of approximately:",
        "answer": "25 hours",
        "choiceone": "6 hours",
        "choicetwo": "8 hours",
        "choicethree": "36 hours",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is",
        "choiceone": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)",
        "choicetwo": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the decision-making process, confirmation bias results in:",
        "answer": "a tendency to look for information which confirms the validity of the\ndecision",
        "choiceone": "choosing familiar solutions, even if they are not the best ones",
        "choicetwo": "overestimating the frequency of some events",
        "choicethree": "a tendency to look for approval by other crew-members, or by the ATC",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An experienced pilot:",
        "answer": "prepares thoroughly for a flight and is able to anticipate the majority of\npossible problems",
        "choiceone": "functions exclusively in a reactive manner, as it is not\nresource-consuming",
        "choicetwo": "seeks complex solutions to problems, thus using his capacities up to\n100%",
        "choicethree": "avoids using automated systems as his experience allows him to\nperform all tasks manually",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to limit stress when flying, a pilot should:",
        "answer": "maintain his competence by practicing his professional skills and\nlearning from past experiences",
        "choiceone": "forget about bad past experiences",
        "choicetwo": "avoid anticipating events during a flight to manage his workload",
        "choicethree": "drop activities outside work so as to focus on his work better",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot may get the illusion of low altitude on approach although the aircraft is\non the correct glidepath:",
        "answer": "when the runway is wider than he is used to",
        "choiceone": "when the runway is unusually narrow",
        "choicetwo": "on night approaches only",
        "choicethree": "depending on the approach speed of the aircraft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet aircraft\ncommercial fleet shows that human error is involved in:",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases",
        "choiceone": "about 90% of cases",
        "choicetwo": "about 55% of cases",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the cruise, at night, when the workload is low, it is recommended that:",
        "answer": "the lighting in the cockpit be increased in order to prevent low vigilance",
        "choiceone": "the lighting in the cockpit be dimmed in order to reduce visual fatigue",
        "choicetwo": "the lighting in the cockpit be dimmed in order to prevent low vigilance",
        "choicethree": "only those instruments that are vital to flying the aircraft be lit in order to\navoid dividing one's attention",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Vision of terrain relief (e.g. hills, valleys, etc.):",
        "answer": "is based on binocular vision at short distances and the rules of\nproportion and perspective for objects that are further away",
        "choiceone": "is impossible with only one eye",
        "choicetwo": "is possible at only at distances over 200 m due to binocular vision",
        "choicethree": "is impossible if a pilot wears sunglasses",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Decisions made by pilots in a cockpit:",
        "answer": "remain valid for a limited time only",
        "choiceone": "are always irreversible",
        "choicetwo": "should always be made as quickly as possible",
        "choicethree": "are automatic when pilots are experts",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When suffering from Hypoxia short-term memory impairment starts at\napproximately at:",
        "answer": "12,000 ft",
        "choiceone": "10,000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "18,000 ft",
        "choicethree": "25,000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Haemoglobin has an affinity for carbon monoxide of ...............times over\noxygen",
        "answer": "210 - 250",
        "choiceone": "50 - 75",
        "choicetwo": "5 - 10",
        "choicethree": "500 - 1,000",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Peripheral Nervous System passes information from the:",
        "answer": "sensory inputs to the CNS through sensory and motor nerves",
        "choiceone": "brain to the sensory stores through sensory nerves",
        "choicetwo": "brain to all parts of the body through sensory and autonomic nerves",
        "choicethree": "brain to all parts of the body through sensory nerves",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Vestibular Apparatus consists of the:",
        "answer": "Semi-circular canals and the otoliths",
        "choiceone": "Eustachian tube and the semi-circular canals",
        "choicetwo": "Cochlea and the auditory nerve",
        "choicethree": "Eustachian tube and the pinna",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"Leans\" or Somatogyral illusion can be caused by:",
        "answer": "Reducing bank following a prolonged turn",
        "choiceone": "Bunting the aircraft",
        "choicetwo": "Going into a turn too quickly",
        "choicethree": "A carrier take-off",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the factors which affect visual acuity are:",
        "answer": "Hypoxia, age and angular distance from the fovea",
        "choiceone": "Smoking, colour blindness and angular distance from the fovea",
        "choicetwo": "Colour blindness, alcohol and amount of light available",
        "choicethree": "Colour blindness, visibility and angular distance from the fovea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia results in:",
        "answer": "a decrease of accommodation",
        "choiceone": "a lack of vitamin A",
        "choicetwo": "a lack of empty field",
        "choicethree": "a mis-shapened cornea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Astigmatism is caused by:",
        "answer": "A mis-shapened cornea",
        "choiceone": "A lack of vitamin A",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of empty field",
        "choicethree": "A lack of accommodation",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the factors that increase tolerance to long-duration g forces are:",
        "answer": "Bending forward or supine body position and tensing of the abdominal\nmuscles",
        "choiceone": "Correct use of pilot's harness and tensing of the abdominal muscles",
        "choicetwo": "Anti-g suits and correct use of pilot's harness",
        "choicethree": "Tensing the leg muscles and correct use of pilot's harness",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to withstand g forces is reduced by a number of factors, among\nthese factors are:",
        "answer": "Low blood sugar, obesity and hypoxia",
        "choiceone": "Hypoxia, fatigue and vibrations",
        "choicetwo": "Smoking, obesity and vibrations",
        "choicethree": "Physical fitness, heat and hypotension",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the two types of attention ?",
        "answer": "Selective and divided",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Trace elements should be obtained through:",
        "answer": "A balanced diet",
        "choiceone": "Vitamin pills",
        "choicetwo": "Eating plenty of meat and vegetables",
        "choicethree": "Dairy products and vegetables",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the symptoms of hypoglycaemia are:",
        "answer": "Headache and lack of concentration",
        "choiceone": "Double vision and puffiness around the eyes",
        "choicetwo": "Severe eye and head aches",
        "choicethree": "Difficulty in focussing on near-by objects",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Approximately how long will a blood/alcohol level of 60 mgm/100ml take to\nreturn to normal ?",
        "answer": "4 hours",
        "choiceone": "20 hours",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours",
        "choicethree": "1 hour",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Phobic states or obsessional disorders will :",
        "answer": "may require successful treatment before flying may be permitted",
        "choiceone": "always result in permanent loss of a flying licence",
        "choicetwo": "result in the loss of a Class I medical classification after successful\ntreatment",
        "choicethree": "require immediate termination of all flying duties",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cholera can be transmitted through:",
        "answer": "Food or water which has been contaminated",
        "choiceone": "Droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person",
        "choicetwo": "Insect bites",
        "choicethree": "Bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tetanus is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "Bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin",
        "choiceone": "Droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person",
        "choicetwo": "Insect bites",
        "choicethree": "Food or water which has been contaminated",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hepatitis 'A' is transmitted through:",
        "answer": "food or water which has been contaminated.",
        "choiceone": "droplets in the air cause by the breath of an infected person.",
        "choicetwo": "insect bites.",
        "choicethree": "bacteria in the form of spores via a puncture in the skin.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Records of radiation are normally kept for flights above:",
        "answer": "49,000 ft",
        "choiceone": "45,000 ft",
        "choicetwo": "40,000 ft",
        "choicethree": "55,000 ft",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Galactic Radiation is:",
        "answer": "Steady and reasonably predictable",
        "choiceone": "Unsteady and reasonably predictable",
        "choicetwo": "Steady but unpredictable",
        "choicethree": "Unsteady and unpredictable",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The effects of Galactic radiation:",
        "answer": "Increases with altitude",
        "choiceone": "Decreases with altitude",
        "choicetwo": "Is unaffected by altitude",
        "choicethree": "Remains steady up to 49,000 ft and thereafter increases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Excessive intake of aspirin can cause:",
        "answer": "Gastric bleeding",
        "choiceone": "Sensory loss",
        "choicetwo": "Fits",
        "choicethree": "Memory impairment",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the factors which can cause illusions while taxiing are:",
        "answer": "relative movement and cockpit height above the ground.",
        "choiceone": "visibility and distance.",
        "choicetwo": "distance from the edge of the taxiway and taxi lighting.",
        "choicethree": "distance from the edge of the taxiway and cockpit lighting.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Somatogravic illusion gives the pilot a false impression of:",
        "answer": "climbing or descending.",
        "choiceone": "descending and turning to the left.",
        "choicetwo": "climbing and turning to the right.",
        "choicethree": "descending and turning to the right.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Autokinesis can give the pilot the impression that:",
        "answer": "a star is another aircraft",
        "choiceone": "the aircraft is climbing",
        "choicetwo": "lights from ships are stars",
        "choicethree": "lights are further away than in fact they are.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the major protective measures against illusions is:",
        "answer": "comprehensive briefing and de-briefing",
        "choiceone": "regular eye tests",
        "choicetwo": "wearing of good quality sun glasses",
        "choicethree": "wearing of polaroid sun glasses",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sleep pattern is closely associated with:",
        "answer": "Body temperature",
        "choiceone": "Glucose level",
        "choicetwo": "Blood pressure",
        "choicethree": "Heart rate",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The normal sleep cycle is approximately every ................minutes",
        "answer": "90",
        "choiceone": "60",
        "choicetwo": "120",
        "choicethree": "180",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If a stop-over is more than 24 hours, the correct action is to:",
        "answer": "Move to the new time as soon as possible",
        "choiceone": "Stay on home time and, on arrival, move to the new time",
        "choicetwo": "Stay on home time",
        "choicethree": "No adjustment is necessary",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mode Error is associated with:",
        "answer": "Automation",
        "choiceone": "Hardware",
        "choicetwo": "Check lists",
        "choicethree": "Vertigo",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The two types of fatigue are:",
        "answer": "Chronic short-term and acute",
        "choiceone": "Short-term and oppressive",
        "choicetwo": "Oppressive and negative",
        "choicethree": "Heavy and light",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main purpose of lumbar support is to:",
        "answer": "produce an even pressure of the discs by allowing the lower spine to\ncurve naturally.",
        "choiceone": "allow the most comfortable position for the spine and shoulder bones",
        "choicetwo": "allow the most comfortable position for the upper spine",
        "choicethree": "allow the most comfortable position for the spine and higher neck bones",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following answers is correct?",
        "answer": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is\nadaptable.",
        "choiceone": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is\nadaptable.",
        "choicetwo": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is not\nadaptable.",
        "choicethree": "Personality is the outward result of behaviour and attitude and is not\nadaptable.",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With too much cohesion, Groupthink can be:",
        "answer": "negative",
        "choiceone": "positive and far-reaching",
        "choicetwo": "popular and positive",
        "choicethree": "positive",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cohesion is a major advantage in times of:",
        "answer": "Difficulty",
        "choiceone": "Achievement",
        "choicetwo": "Personal advancement",
        "choicethree": "Success",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Differences of opinion should be regarded as ....................\u2013",
        "answer": "Helpful",
        "choiceone": "Confrontational",
        "choicetwo": "Having negative influence on the group and are not to be encouraged",
        "choicethree": "Stressful",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "CRM and MCC training are designed to improve:",
        "answer": "The quality of crew performance",
        "choiceone": "Individual achievement",
        "choicetwo": "Individual efficiency and contribution",
        "choicethree": "The quality and a number of individuals' performance",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having made an important decision, a Commander of an aircraft should:",
        "answer": "Always try to make time to explain the reasons for the decision even if it\nis after landing",
        "choiceone": "Explain the reasons for the decision only if time permits in the air",
        "choicetwo": "As the leader of the crew, never need explain the reasons behind the\ndecision",
        "choicethree": "Explain the reasons for the decision only if asked",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The three types of Authority Gradient Cockpits are:",
        "answer": "Autocratic, Laisser-Faire and Synergistic",
        "choiceone": "Authoritative, Laisser-Faire and Synergistic",
        "choicetwo": "Autocratic, Followership and Synergistic",
        "choicethree": "Authoritative, Followership and Synergistic",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A Captain running an Autocratic cockpit is normally:",
        "answer": "Over-loaded",
        "choiceone": "Under-worked",
        "choicetwo": "Efficient",
        "choicethree": "A good leader",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"ideal\" cockpit can be termed as:",
        "answer": "Synergistic",
        "choiceone": "Cohesive",
        "choicetwo": "Communicative",
        "choicethree": "Co-operative",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL\nConcept of:",
        "answer": "L and S",
        "choiceone": "L and L",
        "choicetwo": "L and H",
        "choicethree": "L and E",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The choice of words and their packaging become more important in the\ncockpit of an aircraft because:",
        "answer": "Loss of body language",
        "choiceone": "Loss of hypertext",
        "choicetwo": "Loss of situational awareness",
        "choicethree": "Loss of perception",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Communication efficiency is most sensitive to:",
        "answer": "Workload and interruptions",
        "choiceone": "Packaging of words",
        "choicetwo": "Packaging of phrases",
        "choicethree": "Packaging of sentences",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Internal conflict within oneself is termed as:",
        "answer": "Intra-personal conflict",
        "choiceone": "Intro-personal conflict",
        "choicetwo": "Inter-personal conflict",
        "choicethree": "Intermediate-personal conflict",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The use of professional languages offers:",
        "answer": "quick comprehension and simplified grammar",
        "choiceone": "longer attention span",
        "choicetwo": "more precise grammar",
        "choicethree": "better communication even if professionals are not from the same field",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Approximately ................... of all communication is achieved by factors other\nthan words (metacommunications)",
        "answer": "80%",
        "choiceone": "30%",
        "choicetwo": "50%",
        "choicethree": "10%",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Expressed as a simple mathematical statement when considering a crew of\ntwo, good synergy is:",
        "answer": "1 + 1 =   >  2",
        "choiceone": "1 + 1 =   <  2",
        "choicetwo": "1 +/- 1 =   <  2",
        "choicethree": "1 - 1 =   >  2",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With reference to the SHELL Model, S represents:",
        "answer": "Software (which includes check lists)",
        "choiceone": "Security (which includes Safety)",
        "choicetwo": "Self-awareness (which includes Safety)",
        "choicethree": "Symbology (which includes safety)",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Below 70,000 ft., what gas makes up the major part of the atmosphere ?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide",
        "choicethree": "Ozone",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot successfully completes a difficult and stressful landing at an\naerodrome. The next time a landing is attempted under the same conditions\nand at the same aerodrome, is the pilot likely to experience:",
        "answer": "a lower level of stress",
        "choiceone": "a higher level of stress",
        "choicetwo": "the same stress level as the first landing",
        "choicethree": "the pilot should only attempt a landing at the same aerodrome if the\nconditions are improved",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An important aspect of Situational Awareness is:",
        "answer": "When a pilot's perception equals reality",
        "choiceone": "When the pilot perceives the situation both inside and outside the\naircraft",
        "choicetwo": "When the pilot perceives the instant and immediate situation both inside\nand outside the cockpit",
        "choicethree": "When a pilot is sure that the situation both inside and outside the\naircraft is correct",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Having interrupted the Captain for a sound reason, the co-pilot should:",
        "answer": "Remind him/her of his/.her last action before the interruption",
        "choiceone": "Ensure there is no ATC traffic on the radio that may be causing a\npossible distraction before continuing",
        "choicetwo": "Repeat the interruption twice so that the Captain's attention is focussed\non the new information",
        "choicethree": "Never interrupt his/her Captain at a critical stage of flight",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An unnoticed way-point error entered in an aircraft data base is an example\nof:",
        "answer": "Latent failure/error",
        "choiceone": "Pro-active failure/error",
        "choicetwo": "Re-active failure/error",
        "choicethree": "Active failure/error",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "If one error is allowed to effect a whole system, the system is described as:",
        "answer": "Vulnerable",
        "choiceone": "Error-prone",
        "choicetwo": "Error tolerant",
        "choicethree": "Corrupted",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Active errors/failures are committed at:",
        "answer": "the human/system interface and have an immediate effect",
        "choiceone": "the human/system interface and have a delayed effect",
        "choicetwo": "the system/system interface and have an immediate effect",
        "choicethree": "the system/system interface and have a delayed effect",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ergonomics are associated with:",
        "answer": "the human/workplace interface",
        "choiceone": "cognition",
        "choicetwo": "communications",
        "choicethree": "information processing",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first cockpit tool that tends to suffer as a result of stress:",
        "answer": "Cockpit communications",
        "choiceone": "Cockpit synergy",
        "choicetwo": "Cockpit cohesion",
        "choicethree": "Cockpit entity",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The best method to avoid Confirmation Bias is to:",
        "answer": "Search for information that will falsify the hypothesis",
        "choiceone": "Deliberately confirm that the receiver has understood the information\nthat has been passed to him/her",
        "choicetwo": "Double-check that you have not fitted the ground over which you are\npassing to your map",
        "choicethree": "Precise and careful pre-flight briefings",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The phases of learning a Motor Programme are:",
        "answer": "Cognitive, Associative and Automatic phases",
        "choiceone": "Initial, Interim and Final phases",
        "choicetwo": "1st, 2nd and 3rd phases",
        "choicethree": "Induction, Simulation and Practice phases",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stimuli must be of a certain strength for the receptors to pick them up. This is\ncalled:",
        "answer": "Sensory threshold",
        "choiceone": "Sensory filter",
        "choicetwo": "Sensory strength",
        "choicethree": "Sensory volume",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "We generate Mental Models on:",
        "answer": "Past experience and learning",
        "choiceone": "Stereopsis",
        "choicetwo": "Imagination",
        "choicethree": "3-D vision",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The errors of a motor programme are:",
        "answer": "Action Slip and Environmental Capture (Habituation)",
        "choiceone": "Habituation and Error of Commission",
        "choicetwo": "Action Slip and Confirmation Bias",
        "choicethree": "Confirmation error and Error of Commission",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1972, a psychologist named Edwards presented a concept of the interface\nbetween flight crew and other parts of the airspace environment. What is this\nconcept called and the names of those elements involved ?",
        "answer": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment, and liveware",
        "choiceone": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, economy and liveware",
        "choicetwo": "The SHELL Concept. Software, harmony, environment, and location",
        "choicethree": "The SHELL Concept. Software, hardware, environment and location",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who in the Aviation Industry is responsible for flight safety ?",
        "answer": "Everyone involved",
        "choiceone": "Aircrew",
        "choicetwo": "Aircrew and GroundCrew",
        "choicethree": "Management, Aircrew, Groundcrew and ATC",
        "source": "pdf/Type2/hp\\HP.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "some of the hazardous attitudes which may occur to every pilot to some degree at some\ntime are....\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, macho, resignation, and invulnerability.\n",
        "choiceone": "Poor situational awareness, snap judgments, and lack of a decision making process.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor risk management and lack of stress management.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:\n",
        "answer": "Lands\n",
        "choiceone": "LandL\n",
        "choicetwo": "LandH\n",
        "choicethree": "LandE\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When suffering from Hypoxia short-term memory impairment starts at approximately ....\n",
        "answer": "12,000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "10,000 ft\n",
        "choicetwo": "18,000 ft\n",
        "choicethree": "25,000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You climb from 0 to 50,000 ft and measure the decrease of the pressure per 5.000 ft.\nThe absolute difference in barometric pressure is greatest between:\n",
        "answer": "0 and 5.000 feet\n",
        "choiceone": "5.000 and 10.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "10.000 and 15.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "45.000 and 50.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot and friends are going to fly to an out-of-town football game. When the\npassengers arrive, the pilot determines that they will be over the maximum gross weight\nfor takeoff with the existing fuel load. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates\nthe RESIGNATION reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Well, nobody told him about the extra weight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Weight and balance is a formality forced on pilots by the FAA.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He can't wait around to de-fuel, they have to get there on time.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Atwoki Kaija_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:\n",
        "answer": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "relying on the body's built in warning system recognizing any stage of hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "swallowing, yawing and applying the Valsalva method\n",
        "choicethree": "not exceeding a cabin pressure altitude of 20000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Perceptional illusions are:\n",
        "answer": "normal and can be prevented by trusting instrument read-out.\n",
        "choiceone": "usually not serious except in bad weather.\n",
        "choicetwo": "abnormal and indicate weakness in one or more of the senses.\n",
        "choicethree": "never caused by the brain's ability to distort normal sense inputs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype ant\ncalled:\n\nwoluntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\n",
        "answer": "reflex\n",
        "choiceone": "data processing\n",
        "choicetwo": "control system\n",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:\n",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part\n",
        "choiceone": "rods located in its central part\n",
        "choicetwo": "crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its peripheral zone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a student can concentrate on learning, which of these human needs must be\nsatisfied first?\n",
        "answer": "Physical needs.\n",
        "choiceone": "Social needs.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Safety needs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is more subject to spatial disorientation if\n",
        "answer": "body signals are used to interpret flight attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "kinesthetic senses are ignored.\n",
        "choicetwo": "eyes are moved often in the process of cross-checking the flight instruments.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the use of cockpit lighting for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reducing the lighting intensity to a minimum level will eliminate blind spots.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensations which lead to spatial disorientation during instrument flight conditions\n",
        "answer": "must be suppressed and complete reliance placed on the indications of the flight\ninstruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "are frequently encountered by beginning instrument pilots, but never by pilots with\nmoderate instrument experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "occur, in most instances, during the initial period of transition from visual to\ninstrument flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a student can concentrate on learning, which of these human needs must be\nsatisfied first?\n",
        "answer": "Physical needs.\n",
        "choiceone": "Social needs.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Safety needs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Albert Kaija_20-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name some hazardous attitudes that can affect your judgment during the aeronautical\ndecision making (ADM) process.\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, and resignation.\n",
        "choiceone": "impulsivity, antiestablishment, and reevaluation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Peer pressure and stress levels.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:\n",
        "answer": "Lands\n",
        "choiceone": "LandL\n",
        "choicetwo": "LandH\n",
        "choicethree": "LandE\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n\n-4: SCUBA diving may be practiced without restriction\n\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.\n",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Perceptional illusions are:\n",
        "answer": "normal and can be prevented by trusting instrument read-out.\n",
        "choiceone": "usually not serious except in bad weather.\n",
        "choicetwo": "abnormal and indicate weakness in one or more of the senses.\n",
        "choicethree": "never caused by the brain's ability to distort normal sense inputs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype ant\ncalled:\n\nwoluntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\n",
        "answer": "reflex\n",
        "choiceone": "data processing\n",
        "choicetwo": "control system\n",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina of the eye\n",
        "answer": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the photoreceptors essential\nfor vision\n",
        "choiceone": "filters the UV-light\n",
        "choicetwo": "is the muscle, changing the size of the crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "only regulates the light that falls into the eye\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Probably the greatest single barrier to effective communication is the\n",
        "answer": "lack of a common core of experience between communicator and receiver.\n",
        "choiceone": "use of inaccurate statements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "use of abstractions by the communicator.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot and friends are going to fly to an out-of-town football game. When the\npassengers arrive, the pilot determines that they will be over the maximum gross weight\nfor takeoff with the existing fuel load. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates\nthe RESIGNATION reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Well, nobody told him about the extra weight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Weight and balance is a formality forced on pilots by the FAA.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He can't wait around to de-fuel, they have to get there on time.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Allan Muhanguzi_12-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can smoking affect a pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Reduces the oxygen-carrying capability of the blood.\n",
        "choiceone": "Can decrease night vision by up to 50 percent.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Creates additional carbon dioxide gases in the body which often leads to\nhyperventilation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:\n",
        "answer": "Lands\n",
        "choiceone": "LandL\n",
        "choicetwo": "LandH\n",
        "choicethree": "LandE\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype ant\ncalled:\n\nwoluntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\n",
        "answer": "reflex\n",
        "choiceone": "data processing\n",
        "choicetwo": "control system\n",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia:\n",
        "answer": "is common over the age of 50.\n",
        "choiceone": "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90dB.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.\n",
        "choicethree": "surgical replacement of the lens the usual treatment and is compatible with flying.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "State the conditions which cause the \"black hole effect\" and the danger to flight safety.\n",
        "answer": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach\nto an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than\nitis, leading to a low approach being flown.\n",
        "choiceone": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over featureless terrain on the\napproach to an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher\naltitude than itis, leading to a high approach being flown.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach\nto an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than\nitis, leading to a high approach being flown.\n",
        "choicethree": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying under instruments with poor cockpit\nlighting and can lead to disorientation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is true with reference to semantic memory?\n",
        "answer": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a longer\nperiod of time and tends to be more accurate than episodic memory.\n",
        "choiceone": "It is the memory of events; it lasts for a longer period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be more accurate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a shorter\nperiod of time than episodic memory and tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "choicethree": "Itis the memory of events; it lasts for a shorter period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving cont\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2, 3 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3,4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "1, 2,4 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot recognizes a hazardous thought, he or she then should correct it by\napplying the corresponding antidote. Which of the following is the antidote for\nANTIAUTHORITY/DON'T TELL ME hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Don't tell me. Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "choiceone": "Not so fast. Think first.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It won't happen to me. It could happen to me.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fal\ntrying to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and demonstrate\nthe \u2018right stuff.\u201d\n",
        "choiceone": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "choicetwo": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Benjamin Ojule_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is more subject to spatial disorientation if\n",
        "answer": "body signals are used to interpret flight attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "kinesthetic senses are ignored.\n",
        "choicetwo": "eyes are moved often in the process of cross-checking the flight instruments.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\dated.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can smoking affect a pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Reduces the oxygen-carrying capability of the blood.\n",
        "choiceone": "Can decrease night vision by up to 50 percent.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Creates additional carbon dioxide gases in the body which often leads to\nhyperventilation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which use of cockpit lighting is correct for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "Reducing the interior lighting intensity to a minimum level.\n",
        "choiceone": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will not impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Perceptional illusions are:\n",
        "answer": "normal and can be prevented by trusting instrument read-out.\n",
        "choiceone": "usually not serious except in bad weather.\n",
        "choicetwo": "abnormal and indicate weakness in one or more of the senses.\n",
        "choicethree": "never caused by the brain's ability to distort normal sense inputs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:\n",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part\n",
        "choiceone": "rods located in its central part\n",
        "choicetwo": "crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its peripheral zone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:\n",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep\n",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep\n",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep\n",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While material is being taught, students may be learning other things as well. What\nadditional learning called?\n\n",
        "answer": "Incidental learning.\n",
        "choiceone": "Residual learning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Conceptual learning.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya 2_AB178560_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n\n-4: SCUBA diving may be practiced without restriction\n\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.\n",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:\n",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure\n(i.e. when climbing a high mountain)\n",
        "choiceone": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure\n",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving cont\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2, 3 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3,4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "1, 2,4 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Denis Mbuya_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Abrupt head movement during a prolonged constant rate turn in IMC or\ninstrument conditions can cause\n",
        "answer": "pilot disorientation.\n",
        "choiceone": "false horizon.\n",
        "choicetwo": "elevator illusion.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name some hazardous attitudes that can affect your judgment during the aeronautical\ndecision making (ADM) process.\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, and resignation.\n",
        "choiceone": "impulsivity, antiestablishment, and reevaluation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Peer pressure and stress levels.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the first step of the Decide Model for effective risk management\nand Aeronautical Decision Making?\n",
        "answer": "Detect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Identify.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina of the eye\n",
        "answer": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the photoreceptors essential\nfor vision\n",
        "choiceone": "filters the UV-light\n",
        "choicetwo": "is the muscle, changing the size of the crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "only regulates the light that falls into the eye\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:\n",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep\n",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep\n",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep\n",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is true with reference to semantic memory?\n",
        "answer": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a longer\nperiod of time and tends to be more accurate than episodic memory.\n",
        "choiceone": "It is the memory of events; it lasts for a longer period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be more accurate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a shorter\nperiod of time than episodic memory and tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "choicethree": "Itis the memory of events; it lasts for a shorter period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\document.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia:\n",
        "answer": "is common over the age of 50.\n",
        "choiceone": "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90dB.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.\n",
        "choicethree": "surgical replacement of the lens the usual treatment and is compatible with flying.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a student can concentrate on learning, which of these human needs must be\nsatisfied first?\n",
        "answer": "Physical needs.\n",
        "choiceone": "Social needs.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Safety needs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving cont\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2, 3 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3,4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "1, 2,4 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot and friends are going to fly to an out-of-town football game. When the\npassengers arrive, the pilot determines that they will be over the maximum gross weight\nfor takeoff with the existing fuel load. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates\nthe RESIGNATION reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Well, nobody told him about the extra weight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Weight and balance is a formality forced on pilots by the FAA.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He can't wait around to de-fuel, they have to get there on time.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\el berry.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can smoking affect a pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Reduces the oxygen-carrying capability of the blood.\n",
        "choiceone": "Can decrease night vision by up to 50 percent.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Creates additional carbon dioxide gases in the body which often leads to\nhyperventilation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Elvis Kibuuka_22-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "some of the hazardous attitudes which may occur to every pilot to some degree at some\ntime are....\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, macho, resignation, and invulnerability.\n",
        "choiceone": "Poor situational awareness, snap judgments, and lack of a decision making process.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor risk management and lack of stress management.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensations which lead to spatial disorientation during instrument flight conditions\n",
        "answer": "must be suppressed and complete reliance placed on the indications of the flight\ninstruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "are frequently encountered by beginning instrument pilots, but never by pilots with\nmoderate instrument experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "occur, in most instances, during the initial period of transition from visual to\ninstrument flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When suffering from Hypoxia short-term memory impairment starts at approximately ....\n",
        "answer": "12,000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "10,000 ft\n",
        "choicetwo": "18,000 ft\n",
        "choicethree": "25,000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype ant\ncalled:\n\nwoluntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\n",
        "answer": "reflex\n",
        "choiceone": "data processing\n",
        "choicetwo": "control system\n",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "State the conditions which cause the \"black hole effect\" and the danger to flight safety.\n",
        "answer": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach\nto an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than\nitis, leading to a low approach being flown.\n",
        "choiceone": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over featureless terrain on the\napproach to an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher\naltitude than itis, leading to a high approach being flown.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach\nto an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than\nitis, leading to a high approach being flown.\n",
        "choicethree": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying under instruments with poor cockpit\nlighting and can lead to disorientation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\football.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:\n",
        "answer": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "relying on the body's built in warning system recognizing any stage of hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "swallowing, yawing and applying the Valsalva method\n",
        "choicethree": "not exceeding a cabin pressure altitude of 20000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:\n",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure\n(i.e. when climbing a high mountain)\n",
        "choiceone": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure\n",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:\n",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is\n",
        "choiceone": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)\n",
        "choicetwo": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity\n",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fal\ntrying to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and demonstrate\nthe \u2018right stuff.\u201d\n",
        "choiceone": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "choicetwo": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\hard disk.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name some hazardous attitudes that can affect your judgment during the aeronautical\ndecision making (ADM) process.\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, and resignation.\n",
        "choiceone": "impulsivity, antiestablishment, and reevaluation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Peer pressure and stress levels.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the first step of the Decide Model for effective risk management\nand Aeronautical Decision Making?\n",
        "answer": "Detect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Identify.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the use of cockpit lighting for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reducing the lighting intensity to a minimum level will eliminate blind spots.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:\n",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is\n",
        "choiceone": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)\n",
        "choicetwo": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity\n",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While material is being taught, students may be learning other things as well. What\nadditional learning called?\n\n",
        "answer": "Incidental learning.\n",
        "choiceone": "Residual learning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Conceptual learning.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Japheth Okabo Okeng_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:\n",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure\n(i.e. when climbing a high mountain)\n",
        "choiceone": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure\n",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia:\n",
        "answer": "is common over the age of 50.\n",
        "choiceone": "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90dB.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.\n",
        "choicethree": "surgical replacement of the lens the usual treatment and is compatible with flying.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving cont\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2, 3 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3,4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "1, 2,4 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joel Kanghuli_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is more subject to spatial disorientation if\n",
        "answer": "body signals are used to interpret flight attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "kinesthetic senses are ignored.\n",
        "choicetwo": "eyes are moved often in the process of cross-checking the flight instruments.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joseph ATIALUK_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can smoking affect a pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Reduces the oxygen-carrying capability of the blood.\n",
        "choiceone": "Can decrease night vision by up to 50 percent.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Creates additional carbon dioxide gases in the body which often leads to\nhyperventilation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:\n",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure\n(i.e. when climbing a high mountain)\n",
        "choiceone": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure\n",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:\n",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is\n",
        "choiceone": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)\n",
        "choicetwo": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity\n",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Joshua Asaba_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to gain a realistic perspective on one's attitude toward flying, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "take a Self-Assessment Hazardous Attitude Inventory Test.\n",
        "choiceone": "understand the need to complete the flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "obtain both realistic and thorough flight instruction during training.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Abrupt head movement during a prolonged constant rate turn in IMC or\ninstrument conditions can cause\n",
        "answer": "pilot disorientation.\n",
        "choiceone": "false horizon.\n",
        "choicetwo": "elevator illusion.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can smoking affect a pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Reduces the oxygen-carrying capability of the blood.\n",
        "choiceone": "Can decrease night vision by up to 50 percent.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Creates additional carbon dioxide gases in the body which often leads to\nhyperventilation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype ant\ncalled:\n\nwoluntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\n",
        "answer": "reflex\n",
        "choiceone": "data processing\n",
        "choicetwo": "control system\n",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina of the eye\n",
        "answer": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the photoreceptors essential\nfor vision\n",
        "choiceone": "filters the UV-light\n",
        "choicetwo": "is the muscle, changing the size of the crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "only regulates the light that falls into the eye\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a student can concentrate on learning, which of these human needs must be\nsatisfied first?\n",
        "answer": "Physical needs.\n",
        "choiceone": "Social needs.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Safety needs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot and friends are going to fly to an out-of-town football game. When the\npassengers arrive, the pilot determines that they will be over the maximum gross weight\nfor takeoff with the existing fuel load. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates\nthe RESIGNATION reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Well, nobody told him about the extra weight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Weight and balance is a formality forced on pilots by the FAA.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He can't wait around to de-fuel, they have to get there on time.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Lilian Namukwaya_22-08-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:\n",
        "answer": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "relying on the body's built in warning system recognizing any stage of hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "swallowing, yawing and applying the Valsalva method\n",
        "choicethree": "not exceeding a cabin pressure altitude of 20000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Mathew Sekalo_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is more subject to spatial disorientation if\n",
        "answer": "body signals are used to interpret flight attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "kinesthetic senses are ignored.\n",
        "choicetwo": "eyes are moved often in the process of cross-checking the flight instruments.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to gain a realistic perspective on one's attitude toward flying, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "take a Self-Assessment Hazardous Attitude Inventory Test.\n",
        "choiceone": "understand the need to complete the flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "obtain both realistic and thorough flight instruction during training.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Abrupt head movement during a prolonged constant rate turn in IMC or\ninstrument conditions can cause\n",
        "answer": "pilot disorientation.\n",
        "choiceone": "false horizon.\n",
        "choicetwo": "elevator illusion.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hyperventilation is:\n",
        "answer": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure\n(i.e. when climbing a high mountain)\n",
        "choiceone": "an increased heart rate caused by an increasing blood pressure\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased heart rate caused by a decreasing blood-pressure\n",
        "choicethree": "a reduction of partial oxygen pressure in the brain\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:\n",
        "answer": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "relying on the body's built in warning system recognizing any stage of hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "swallowing, yawing and applying the Valsalva method\n",
        "choicethree": "not exceeding a cabin pressure altitude of 20000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?\n",
        "answer": "Complete adaptation to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Vasodilatation is the only mechanism which is capable of reducing body\ntemperature.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaporation is more effective when ambient humidity is high.\n",
        "choicethree": "Performance is not impaired by an increase in body temperature to 40\u00b0C or more.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving cont\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2, 3 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3,4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "1, 2,4 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Paul Ayul_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name some hazardous attitudes that can affect your judgment during the aeronautical\ndecision making (ADM) process.\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, and resignation.\n",
        "choiceone": "impulsivity, antiestablishment, and reevaluation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Peer pressure and stress levels.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensations which lead to spatial disorientation during instrument flight conditions\n",
        "answer": "must be suppressed and complete reliance placed on the indications of the flight\ninstruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "are frequently encountered by beginning instrument pilots, but never by pilots with\nmoderate instrument experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "occur, in most instances, during the initial period of transition from visual to\ninstrument flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can smoking affect a pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Reduces the oxygen-carrying capability of the blood.\n",
        "choiceone": "Can decrease night vision by up to 50 percent.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Creates additional carbon dioxide gases in the body which often leads to\nhyperventilation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Abrupt head movement during a prolonged constant rate turn in IMC or\ninstrument conditions can cause\n",
        "answer": "pilot disorientation.\n",
        "choiceone": "false horizon.\n",
        "choicetwo": "elevator illusion.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n\n-4: SCUBA diving may be practiced without restriction\n\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.\n",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information is:\n",
        "answer": "limited to the foveal area of the retina\n",
        "choiceone": "limited to daytime using the rod cells\n",
        "choicetwo": "almost equally shared by the entire retina\n",
        "choicethree": "governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20 degrees of angle\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:\n",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep\n",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep\n",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep\n",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While material is being taught, students may be learning other things as well. What\nadditional learning called?\n\n",
        "answer": "Incidental learning.\n",
        "choiceone": "Residual learning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Conceptual learning.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\property.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensations which lead to spatial disorientation during instrument flight conditions\n",
        "answer": "must be suppressed and complete reliance placed on the indications of the flight\ninstruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "are frequently encountered by beginning instrument pilots, but never by pilots with\nmoderate instrument experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "occur, in most instances, during the initial period of transition from visual to\ninstrument flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the first step of the Decide Model for effective risk management\nand Aeronautical Decision Making?\n",
        "answer": "Detect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Identify.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which use of cockpit lighting is correct for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "Reducing the interior lighting intensity to a minimum level.\n",
        "choiceone": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will not impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Read and interpret the flight instruments, and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Rely on kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "some of the hazardous attitudes which may occur to every pilot to some degree at some\ntime are....\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, macho, resignation, and invulnerability.\n",
        "choiceone": "Poor situational awareness, snap judgments, and lack of a decision making process.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor risk management and lack of stress management.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:\n",
        "answer": "Lands\n",
        "choiceone": "LandL\n",
        "choicetwo": "LandH\n",
        "choicethree": "LandE\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information is:\n",
        "answer": "limited to the foveal area of the retina\n",
        "choiceone": "limited to daytime using the rod cells\n",
        "choicetwo": "almost equally shared by the entire retina\n",
        "choicethree": "governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20 degrees of angle\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fal\ntrying to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and demonstrate\nthe \u2018right stuff.\u201d\n",
        "choiceone": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "choicetwo": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:\n",
        "answer": "stable.\n",
        "choiceone": "unstable.\n",
        "choicetwo": "easy changeable.\n",
        "choicethree": "easy changed by an outside influence.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\refund.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to gain a realistic perspective on one's attitude toward flying, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "take a Self-Assessment Hazardous Attitude Inventory Test.\n",
        "choiceone": "understand the need to complete the flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "obtain both realistic and thorough flight instruction during training.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the use of cockpit lighting for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reducing the lighting intensity to a minimum level will eliminate blind spots.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most effective technique to use for detecting other aircraft at night is to\n",
        "answer": "avoid staring directly at the point where another aircraft is suspected to be flying.\n",
        "choiceone": "turn the head and sweep the eyes rapidly over the entire visible region.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid scanning the region below the horizon so as to avoid the effect of ground\nlights on the eyes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Expressed as a simple mathematical statement when considering a crew of two, good\nsynergy is:\n",
        "answer": "1+1=>2\n",
        "choiceone": "1+1= <2\n",
        "choicetwo": "14+#-1= <2\n",
        "choicethree": "1-1\n\n>2\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ritah Nasirumbi_Rnasirumbi_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the use of cockpit lighting for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reducing the lighting intensity to a minimum level will eliminate blind spots.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which use of cockpit lighting is correct for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "Reducing the interior lighting intensity to a minimum level.\n",
        "choiceone": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will not impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the first step of the Decide Model for effective risk management\nand Aeronautical Decision Making?\n",
        "answer": "Detect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Identify.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When suffering from Hypoxia short-term memory impairment starts at approximately ....\n",
        "answer": "12,000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "10,000 ft\n",
        "choicetwo": "18,000 ft\n",
        "choicethree": "25,000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Perceptional illusions are:\n",
        "answer": "normal and can be prevented by trusting instrument read-out.\n",
        "choiceone": "usually not serious except in bad weather.\n",
        "choicetwo": "abnormal and indicate weakness in one or more of the senses.\n",
        "choicethree": "never caused by the brain's ability to distort normal sense inputs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "State the conditions which cause the \"black hole effect\" and the danger to flight safety.\n",
        "answer": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach\nto an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than\nitis, leading to a low approach being flown.\n",
        "choiceone": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over featureless terrain on the\napproach to an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher\naltitude than itis, leading to a high approach being flown.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach\nto an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than\nitis, leading to a high approach being flown.\n",
        "choicethree": "The \u201cblack hole effect\" can be caused by flying under instruments with poor cockpit\nlighting and can lead to disorientation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does good cockpit stress management begin with?\n",
        "answer": "Good life stress management.\n",
        "choiceone": "Knowing what causes stress.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Eliminating life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a student can concentrate on learning, which of these human needs must be\nsatisfied first?\n",
        "answer": "Physical needs.\n",
        "choiceone": "Social needs.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Safety needs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Robert Eguny_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most effective technique to use for detecting other aircraft at night is to\n",
        "answer": "avoid staring directly at the point where another aircraft is suspected to be flying.\n",
        "choiceone": "turn the head and sweep the eyes rapidly over the entire visible region.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid scanning the region below the horizon so as to avoid the effect of ground\nlights on the eyes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name some hazardous attitudes that can affect your judgment during the aeronautical\ndecision making (ADM) process.\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, and resignation.\n",
        "choiceone": "impulsivity, antiestablishment, and reevaluation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Peer pressure and stress levels.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensations which lead to spatial disorientation during instrument flight conditions\n",
        "answer": "must be suppressed and complete reliance placed on the indications of the flight\ninstruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "are frequently encountered by beginning instrument pilots, but never by pilots with\nmoderate instrument experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "occur, in most instances, during the initial period of transition from visual to\ninstrument flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:\n",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep\n",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep\n",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep\n",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot recognizes a hazardous thought, he or she then should correct it by\napplying the corresponding antidote. Which of the following is the antidote for\nANTIAUTHORITY/DON'T TELL ME hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Don't tell me. Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "choiceone": "Not so fast. Think first.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It won't happen to me. It could happen to me.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot and friends are going to fly to an out-of-town football game. When the\npassengers arrive, the pilot determines that they will be over the maximum gross weight\nfor takeoff with the existing fuel load. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates\nthe RESIGNATION reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Well, nobody told him about the extra weight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Weight and balance is a formality forced on pilots by the FAA.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He can't wait around to de-fuel, they have to get there on time.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Ruth Menya Komyhendo_24-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "some of the hazardous attitudes which may occur to every pilot to some degree at some\ntime are....\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, macho, resignation, and invulnerability.\n",
        "choiceone": "Poor situational awareness, snap judgments, and lack of a decision making process.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor risk management and lack of stress management.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "in a 2 crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes\nincapacitated, your first action is to:\n",
        "answer": "don your own oxygen mask.\n",
        "choiceone": "call for immediate assistance from cabin crew.\n",
        "choicetwo": "commence an emergency descent.\n",
        "choicethree": "administer oxygen to the other pilot.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Perceptional illusions are:\n",
        "answer": "normal and can be prevented by trusting instrument read-out.\n",
        "choiceone": "usually not serious except in bad weather.\n",
        "choicetwo": "abnormal and indicate weakness in one or more of the senses.\n",
        "choicethree": "never caused by the brain's ability to distort normal sense inputs.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To enhance a student's acceptance of further instruction, the instructor should\n",
        "answer": "keep the student informed of his/her progress.\n",
        "choiceone": "continually prod the student to maintain motivational levels.\n",
        "choicetwo": "establish performance standards a little above the student's actual ability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Evaluation of student performance and accomplishment during a lesson should be\nbased on the\n",
        "answer": "objectives and goals that were established in the lesson plan.\n",
        "choiceone": "student's background and past experiences.\n",
        "choicetwo": "student's actual performance as compared to an arbitrary standard.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Taking physical or mental fight is a defense mechanism that students use when they\n",
        "answer": "want to escape from frustrating situations.\n",
        "choiceone": "become bewildered and lost in the advanced phase of training.\n",
        "choicetwo": "attempt to justify actions that otherwise would be unacceptable.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which should be the first step in preparing a lecture?\n",
        "answer": "Establishing the objective and desired outcome.\n",
        "choiceone": "Organizing the material.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Researching the subject.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a student asks irrelevant questions or refuses to participate in class activities, it\nusually is an indication of the defense mechanism known as\n",
        "answer": "aggression.\n",
        "choiceone": "resignation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "substitution.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The method of arranging lesson material from the\nand known to unknown, is one that\n\nple to complex, past to present,\n",
        "answer": "indicates the relationship of the main points of the lesson.\n",
        "choiceone": "the instructor should avoid.\n",
        "choicetwo": "creates student thought pattern departures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The level of learning at which a person can repeat something without understanding\ncalled\n\n",
        "answer": "rote learning.\n",
        "choiceone": "basic learning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "random learning.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In levels of learning, what are the steps of progression?\n",
        "answer": "Rote, understanding, application, and correlation.\n",
        "choiceone": "Application, understanding, rote, and correlation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Correlation, rote, understanding, and application.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When problem-solving, what determines the transition from rule-based activities to\nknowledge-based activities?\n",
        "answer": "Unsuitability of known rules for the problem posed.\n",
        "choiceone": "Unsuitability of automated actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Knowledge of rules that apply for the problem.\n",
        "choicethree": "There is never a transition from Rule-based and Knowledge-based behaviour.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Expressed as a simple mathematical statement when considering a crew of two, good\nsynergy is:\n",
        "answer": "1+1=>2\n",
        "choiceone": "1+1= <2\n",
        "choicetwo": "14+#-1= <2\n",
        "choicethree": "1-1\n\n>2\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While on an IFR flight, a pilot emerges from a cloud to find himself within 300 feet of a\nhelicopter. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the \u2018MACHO' reaction?\n",
        "answer": "He flies a little closer, just to show him.\n",
        "choiceone": "He is not too concerned; everything will be alright.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He quickly turns away and dives, to avoid collision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a student uses excuses to justify inadequate performance, it is an indication of\n\nthe defense mechanism known as\n\n",
        "answer": "rationalization.\n",
        "choiceone": "aggression.\n",
        "choicetwo": "resignation.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Samuel Okirol_20-08-2014_ATPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Someone who has anaemia does not have\n",
        "answer": "enough functional haemoglobin\n",
        "choiceone": "enough platelets\n",
        "choicetwo": "enough plasma\n",
        "choicethree": "enough white blood cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "You climb from 0 to 50,000 ft and measure the decrease of the pressure per 5.000 ft.\nThe absolute difference in barometric pressure is greatest between:\n",
        "answer": "0 and 5.000 feet\n",
        "choiceone": "5.000 and 10.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "10.000 and 15.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "45.000 and 50.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:\n",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part\n",
        "choiceone": "rods located in its central part\n",
        "choicetwo": "crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its peripheral zone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:\n",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep\n",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep\n",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep\n",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Expressed as a simple mathematical statement when considering a crew of two, good\nsynergy is:\n",
        "answer": "1+1=>2\n",
        "choiceone": "1+1= <2\n",
        "choicetwo": "14+#-1= <2\n",
        "choicethree": "1-1\n\n>2\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When a pilot recognizes a hazardous thought, he or she then should correct it by\napplying the corresponding antidote. Which of the following is the antidote for\nANTIAUTHORITY/DON'T TELL ME hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Don't tell me. Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "choiceone": "Not so fast. Think first.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It won't happen to me. It could happen to me.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\scanned.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is more subject to spatial disorientation if\n",
        "answer": "body signals are used to interpret flight attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "kinesthetic senses are ignored.\n",
        "choicetwo": "eyes are moved often in the process of cross-checking the flight instruments.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 90 db can result\n",
        "answer": "noise induced hearing loss\n",
        "choiceone": "conductive hearing loss\n",
        "choicetwo": "presbycusis (effects of aging)\n",
        "choicethree": "a ruptured ear drum\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:\n",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is\n",
        "choiceone": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)\n",
        "choicetwo": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity\n",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving cont\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2, 3 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3,4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "1, 2,4 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n-3: a willingness for group cohesion.\n-4: a tendency to withdrawal.\n\nThe combination of correct statements i:\n\n",
        "answer": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Seith RWASHANDE_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fall into are to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and \u2018get the job\ndone.\"\n",
        "choiceone": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "choicetwo": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Abrupt head movement during a prolonged constant rate turn in IMC or\ninstrument conditions can cause\n",
        "answer": "pilot disorientation.\n",
        "choiceone": "false horizon.\n",
        "choicetwo": "elevator illusion.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from\nflashblindness by:\n\n1 - turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\n\n2 - looking inside the cockpit\n\n3 - wearing sunglasses\n\n4 - using blinds or curtains when installed\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false\n",
        "choicethree": "3 and 4 are correct, 1 and 2 are false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia:\n",
        "answer": "is common over the age of 50.\n",
        "choiceone": "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90dB.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.\n",
        "choicethree": "surgical replacement of the lens the usual treatment and is compatible with flying.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "For a pilot who is used to land on small and narrow runways only, approaching a larger\nand wider runway can lead to:\n",
        "answer": "early or high \u201cround out\"\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018steeper than normal approach dropping low\n",
        "choicetwo": "flatter than normal approach with the risk of \"ducking under\"\n",
        "choicethree": "risk to land short of the overrun\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally\nbe expected to be approximately:\n",
        "answer": "1in 100\n",
        "choiceone": "1in 200\n",
        "choicetwo": "1in 500\n",
        "choicethree": "1in 2000\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\shortcut.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most effective technique to use for detecting other aircraft at night is to\n",
        "answer": "avoid staring directly at the point where another aircraft is suspected to be flying.\n",
        "choiceone": "turn the head and sweep the eyes rapidly over the entire visible region.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid scanning the region below the horizon so as to avoid the effect of ground\nlights on the eyes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to gain a realistic perspective on one's attitude toward flying, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "take a Self-Assessment Hazardous Attitude Inventory Test.\n",
        "choiceone": "understand the need to complete the flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "obtain both realistic and thorough flight instruction during training.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During a stall recovery, the instructor allows the student to exceed maneuvering speed.\nWhich best illustrates an \u2018antiauthority\u2019 reaction by the instructor?\n",
        "answer": "The aircraft can handle a lot more than the maneuvering speed.\n",
        "choiceone": "The student should know how to recover from a stall by this time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "There hasn't been a problem doing this in the past.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a common symptom of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "Decreased breathing rate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A sense of well-being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of these conditions results in hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient oxygen reaching the brain.\n",
        "choiceone": "xcessive oxygen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": ":xcessive carbon dioxide in the bloodstream.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1. tidal volume\n2. inspiratory reserve volume\n3. expiratory reserve volume\n4. residual volume\n\nWhich of the following lists the correct combination?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2and3\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina of the eye\n",
        "answer": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the photoreceptors essential\nfor vision\n",
        "choiceone": "filters the UV-light\n",
        "choicetwo": "is the muscle, changing the size of the crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "only regulates the light that falls into the eye\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is true regarding the presence of alcohol within the human body?\n",
        "answer": "Judgment and decision-making abilities can be adversely affected by even small\namounts of alcohol.\n",
        "choiceone": "A small amount of alcohol increases vision acuity.\n",
        "choicetwo": "An increase in altitude decreases the adverse effect of alcohol.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol, when taken simultaneously with drugs, may\n",
        "answer": "intensify the side effects of the drugs\n",
        "choiceone": "compensate for side effects of drugs\n",
        "choicetwo": "lead to undesired effects only during night flights\n",
        "choicethree": "increase the rate of drug elimination from the blood\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n4. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease\n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individuals physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance of contracting lung cancer\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct, 1 is false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon 2 Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The most effective technique to use for detecting other aircraft at night is to\n",
        "answer": "avoid staring directly at the point where another aircraft is suspected to be flying.\n",
        "choiceone": "turn the head and sweep the eyes rapidly over the entire visible region.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid scanning the region below the horizon so as to avoid the effect of ground\nlights on the eyes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensations which lead to spatial disorientation during instrument flight conditions\n",
        "answer": "must be suppressed and complete reliance placed on the indications of the flight\ninstruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "are frequently encountered by beginning instrument pilots, but never by pilots with\nmoderate instrument experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "occur, in most instances, during the initial period of transition from visual to\ninstrument flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among these is a result of hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "a lack of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "a need to increase the flow of supplemental oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "breathing too rapidly causing a lack of oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What suggestion could you make to people who are experiencing motion sickness?\n",
        "answer": "Avoid unnecessary head movement and focus sight on a point outside the aircraft.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recommend taking medication to prevent motion sickness.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Have the students lower their head, shut their eyes, and take deep breaths.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During trai\na student can\n\nig flights, an instructor should interject realistic distractions to determine if\n",
        "answer": "maintain aircraft control while his/her attention is diverted.\n",
        "choiceone": "learn despite stressful conditions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "perform maneuvers using the integrated method of flight instruction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the first step of the Decide Model for effective risk management\nand Aeronautical Decision Making?\n",
        "answer": "Detect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Identify.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:\n",
        "answer": "Lands\n",
        "choiceone": "LandL\n",
        "choicetwo": "LandH\n",
        "choicethree": "LandE\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following actions are appropriate when faced with symptoms of decompression\nsickness:\n\n1. climb to higher level\n2. descent to the higher of 10000 ft or MSA and land as soon as possible\n3. breathe 100 % oxygen\n\n4. obtain medical advice about recompression after landing\n",
        "answer": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability of the human eye to read alphanumeric information is:\n",
        "answer": "limited to the foveal area of the retina\n",
        "choiceone": "limited to daytime using the rod cells\n",
        "choicetwo": "almost equally shared by the entire retina\n",
        "choicethree": "governed by peripheral vision over an area of approximately 20 degrees of angle\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:\n",
        "answer": "the airfield being further away than actually is\n",
        "choiceone": "his/her visual field shrinking (i.e. tunnel vision)\n",
        "choicetwo": "his/her eyes focusing on infinity\n",
        "choicethree": "aircraft altitude being lower than it actually is\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alcohol degrades:\n",
        "answer": "Paradoxical sleep\n",
        "choiceone": "Slow wave sleep\n",
        "choicetwo": "Stage 2 sleep\n",
        "choicethree": "Stage 3 and 4 sleep\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is true with reference to semantic memory?\n",
        "answer": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a longer\nperiod of time and tends to be more accurate than episodic memory.\n",
        "choiceone": "It is the memory of events; it lasts for a longer period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be more accurate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a shorter\nperiod of time than episodic memory and tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "choicethree": "Itis the memory of events; it lasts for a shorter period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of classic behavioral traps that experienced pilots may fal\ntrying to\n",
        "answer": "complete a flight as planned, please passengers, meet schedules, and demonstrate\nthe \u2018right stuff.\u201d\n",
        "choiceone": "assume additional responsibilities and assert PIC authority.\n",
        "choicetwo": "promote situational awareness and then necessary changes in behavior.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\Simon Ekwee_17-07-2014_CPL(A)_040-Human performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot is more subject to spatial disorientation if\n",
        "answer": "body signals are used to interpret flight attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "kinesthetic senses are ignored.\n",
        "choicetwo": "eyes are moved often in the process of cross-checking the flight instruments.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Without visual aid, a pilot often interprets centrifugal force as a sensation of\n",
        "answer": "rising or falling.\n",
        "choiceone": "turning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "motion reversal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "some of the hazardous attitudes which may occur to every pilot to some degree at some\ntime are....\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, macho, resignation, and invulnerability.\n",
        "choiceone": "Poor situational awareness, snap judgments, and lack of a decision making process.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor risk management and lack of stress management.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During a stall recovery, the instructor allows the student to exceed maneuvering speed.\nWhich best illustrates an \u2018antiauthority\u2019 reaction by the instructor?\n",
        "answer": "The aircraft can handle a lot more than the maneuvering speed.\n",
        "choiceone": "The student should know how to recover from a stall by this time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "There hasn't been a problem doing this in the past.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The DECIDE process consists of six elements to help provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching aeronautical decision making. These elements are to\n",
        "answer": "detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "estimate, determine, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL Concept of:\n",
        "answer": "Lands\n",
        "choiceone": "LandL\n",
        "choicetwo": "LandH\n",
        "choicethree": "LandE\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which gas below 70,000 ft., above ground gas makes up the major part of the\natmosphere ?\n",
        "answer": "Nitrogen\n",
        "choiceone": "Oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "Carbon dioxide\n",
        "choicethree": "Ozone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When suffering from Hypoxia short-term memory impairment starts at approximately ....\n",
        "answer": "12,000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "10,000 ft\n",
        "choicetwo": "18,000 ft\n",
        "choicethree": "25,000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia:\n",
        "answer": "is common over the age of 50.\n",
        "choiceone": "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90dB.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.\n",
        "choicethree": "surgical replacement of the lens the usual treatment and is compatible with flying.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference t\nbecause:\n\n",
        "answer": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast\n",
        "choiceone": "his attention will be distracted automatically under these conditions\n",
        "choicetwo": "the danger of a \u201cgreying out\" will make it impossible to determine the height above\nthe terrain\n",
        "choicethree": "pressure differences can cause the altimeter to give wrong information\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?\n",
        "answer": "The cochlea\n",
        "choiceone": "The semicircular canals\n",
        "choicetwo": "The sacculus and utriculus\n",
        "choicethree": "The Eustachian tube\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon Monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1. Its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2. Itis colourless\n\n3. Its is odourless\n\n4. Itis highly toxic\n\n5. Its effects are cumulative\n\n",
        "answer": "all of the above\n",
        "choiceone": "1, 2,3 and 5 only\n",
        "choicetwo": "2, 3, and 4 only\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3,4 and 5 only\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While material is being taught, students may be learning other things as well. What\nadditional learning called?\n\n",
        "answer": "Incidental learning.\n",
        "choiceone": "Residual learning.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Conceptual learning.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated.\n2. If one has made up one\u2019s mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it\nreally\nneeds.\n3. With increasing stress, attention is limited thereby reducing the flow of information to the\ncentral decision maker.\n",
        "answer": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 2 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are some of the hazardous attitudes dealt with in Aeronautical Decision Making\n(ADM)?\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority (don't tell me), impulsivity (do something quickly without thinking),\nmacho (I can do it).\n",
        "choiceone": "Risk management, stress management, and risk elements.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Poor decision making, situational awareness, and judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best characterises a self-centered cockpit ?\n",
        "answer": "Each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of\nwhat is being done or what is going on\n",
        "choiceone": "The egoistic and self-centered personality of the captain often leads to a synergetic\ncockpit\n",
        "choicetwo": "The communication between crew members always increases when the captain takes\ncharge of a situation\n",
        "choicethree": "While decreasing communication, the independence of each member bolsters the\ncrew's synergy\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "All pilots should have a sound understanding of English because itis safer to\nadhere to the common language chosen by the aeronautical world.\n",
        "choiceone": "Be familiar with normal procedures in English since only this allows for effective\nmanagement of any flight's communication.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Itis necessary and sufficient to have a command of any of the official languages of\nthe ICAO.\n",
        "choicethree": "The composition of every crew should be geared to a command of the official\naeronautical language of the destination country.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of these dangerous tendencies or behavior patterns which must be identified\nand eliminated include:\n",
        "answer": "Peer pressure, get-there-itis, loss of positional or situation awareness, and operating\nwithout adequate fuel reserves.\n",
        "choiceone": "Deficiencies in instrument skills and knowledge of aircraft systems or limitations.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Performance deficiencies from human factors such as, fatigue, illness or emotional\nproblems.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The passengers for a charter flight have arrived almost an hour late for a flight that\nrequires a reservation. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates the\nANTIAUTHORITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Those reservation rules do not apply to this flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "If the pilot hurries, he or she may still make it on time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot can't help it that the passengers are late.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\spacing.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When should a flight instructor begin teact\nstudent?\n\n1g aeronautical decision making (ADM) to a\n",
        "answer": "As soon as the student is able to control the aircraft during basic maneuvers.\n",
        "choiceone": "Beginning with the first lesson.\n",
        "choicetwo": "After the student has completed the initial solo flight but before conducting cross\ncountry flights.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name some hazardous attitudes that can affect your judgment during the aeronautical\ndecision making (ADM) process.\n",
        "answer": "Antiauthority, impulsivity, and resignation.\n",
        "choiceone": "impulsivity, antiestablishment, and reevaluation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Peer pressure and stress levels.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which use of cockpit lighting is correct for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "Reducing the interior lighting intensity to a minimum level.\n",
        "choiceone": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will not impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Motion sickness is caused by\n",
        "answer": "continued stimulation of the tiny portion of the inner ear which controls sense of\nbalance.\n",
        "choiceone": "an instability in the brain cells which affects balance and will generally be overcome\nwith experience.\n",
        "choicetwo": "the movement of an aircraft causing the stomach to create an acid substance which\ncauses the stomach lining to contract.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is hypoxia particularly dangerous during flights with one pilot?\n",
        "answer": "Symptoms of hypoxia may be difficult to recognize before the pilot's reactions are\naffected.\n",
        "choiceone": "Night vision may be so impaired that the pilot cannot see other aircraft.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pilot may not be able to control the aircraft even if using oxygen.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During a stall recovery, the instructor allows the student to exceed maneuvering speed.\nWhich best illustrates an \u2018antiauthority\u2019 reaction by the instructor?\n",
        "answer": "The aircraft can handle a lot more than the maneuvering speed.\n",
        "choiceone": "The student should know how to recover from a stall by this time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "There hasn't been a problem doing this in the past.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can an instrument pilot best overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Properly interpret the flight instruments and act accordingly.\n",
        "choiceone": "Use a very rapid cross-check.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Avoid banking in excess of 30 degrees.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the worldwide jet raft commercial\n\nfleet shows that human error is involved in:\n",
        "answer": "about 70% of cases\n",
        "choiceone": "about90% of cases\n",
        "choicetwo": "70% of cases\n",
        "choicethree": "all cases, one way or another\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia susceptibility due to inhalation of carbon monoxide increases as\n",
        "answer": "altitude increases.\n",
        "choiceone": "humidity decreases.\n",
        "choicetwo": "xygen demand increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment to a depth greater\nthan 10 metres ....\n",
        "answer": "can cause decompression sickness even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18\n000 FT\n",
        "choiceone": "presents any dangers caused by DCS (decompression sickness) when climbing to\naltitudes not exceeding 30 000 FT\n",
        "choicetwo": "has no influence on altitude flights\n",
        "choicethree": "will always lead to hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct:\n\n-4: SCUBA diving may be practiced without restriction\n\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear.\n",
        "answer": "2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Positive G will cause the blood flow to the brain to:\n",
        "answer": "decrease\n",
        "choiceone": "remain constant\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase\n",
        "choicethree": "first increase, then decrease\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To scan properly for traffic, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "use a series of short, regularly spaced eye movements that bring successive areas\nof the sky into the central visual field.\n",
        "choiceone": "slowly sweep the field of vision from one side to the other at intervals.\n",
        "choicetwo": "concentrate on any peripheral movement detected.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stereotype ant\ncalled:\n\nwoluntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is\n",
        "answer": "reflex\n",
        "choiceone": "data processing\n",
        "choicetwo": "control system\n",
        "choicethree": "change of stimulation level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina of the eye\n",
        "answer": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the photoreceptors essential\nfor vision\n",
        "choiceone": "filters the UV-light\n",
        "choicetwo": "is the muscle, changing the size of the crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "only regulates the light that falls into the eye\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The retina allows for colour perception as a result of the:\n",
        "answer": "cones located in its central part\n",
        "choiceone": "rods located in its central part\n",
        "choicetwo": "crystalline lens\n",
        "choicethree": "rods located in its peripheral zone\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchrot\ntime zone at a rate of about\n",
        "answer": "1-1.5 hours a day\n",
        "choiceone": "2 - 2.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 - 3.5 hours a day\n",
        "choicethree": "4-45 hours a day\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the follwoing best discribes disturbance of the biological clock?\n\n1. bad night's sleep\nht Amsterdam - New York\n\nht Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam\n\n",
        "answer": "2 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1 and 3 are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Loss of elasticity of the crystalline lens due to ageing occurs i\n",
        "answer": "presbyopia\n",
        "choiceone": "myopia\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypermetropia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "While conducting an operational check of the cabin pressurization system, the pilot\ndiscovers that the rate control feature is inoperative. He knows that he can manually\ncontrol the cabin pressure, so he elects to disregard the discrepancy. Which of the\nfollowing alternatives best illustrates the INVULNERABILITY reaction?\n",
        "answer": "What is the worst that could happen.\n",
        "choiceone": "He can handle a little problem like this.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It's too late to fix it now.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To communicate effectively, instructors must\n",
        "answer": "display a positive, confident attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "utilize highly organized notes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "display an authoritarian attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,\n",
        "answer": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down\n",
        "choiceone": "to store a large amount of visual information for about 0.5 seconds\n",
        "choicetwo": "to ignore messages for other aircraft\n",
        "choicethree": "to remember our own name\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is true with reference to semantic memory?\n",
        "answer": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a longer\nperiod of time and tends to be more accurate than episodic memory.\n",
        "choiceone": "It is the memory of events; it lasts for a longer period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be more accurate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a shorter\nperiod of time than episodic memory and tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "choicethree": "Itis the memory of events; it lasts for a shorter period of time than episodic memory\nand tends to be less accurate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "on which features does risk management, as part of the Aeronautical Deci:\n(ADM) process, rely?\n",
        "answer": "Situational awareness, problem recognition, and good judgment.\n",
        "choiceone": "The mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making\na timely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Application of stress management and risk element procedures.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot and friends are going to fly to an out-of-town football game. When the\npassengers arrive, the pilot determines that they will be over the maximum gross weight\nfor takeoff with the existing fuel load. Which of the following alternatives best illustrates\nthe RESIGNATION reaction?\n",
        "answer": "Well, nobody told him about the extra weight.\n",
        "choiceone": "Weight and balance is a formality forced on pilots by the FAA.\n",
        "choicetwo": "He can't wait around to de-fuel, they have to get there on time.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the General Adaption Syndrome(GAS) activate?\n",
        "answer": "Responding to an imaginary threat.\n",
        "choiceone": "Responding to Circadian Disrhythmia.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Responding to boredom.\n",
        "choicethree": "Rresponding to Hypovigilance.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\standard.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to gain a realistic perspective on one's attitude toward flying, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "take a Self-Assessment Hazardous Attitude Inventory Test.\n",
        "choiceone": "understand the need to complete the flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "obtain both realistic and thorough flight instruction during training.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the steps in the aeronautical deci:\ndecision making is\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing a \u2018can do\u2019 attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia is caused by\n",
        "answer": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung\n",
        "choiceone": "reduced partial pressure of nitrogen in the lung\n",
        "choicetwo": "an increased number of red blood cells\n",
        "choicethree": "a higher affinity of the red blood cells (haemoglobin) to oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:\n",
        "answer": "more carbon dioxide than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choiceone": "more nitrogen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicetwo": "less water vapour than in the inhaled air\n",
        "choicethree": "more oxygen than in the inhaled air\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:\n",
        "answer": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "the amount of carbon monoxide in the blood\n",
        "choicetwo": "the amount of nitrogen in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "the total atmospheric pressure\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be the effect if, in a tight turn, one bends down to pick up a pencil?\n",
        "answer": "Coriolis effect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Barotrauma.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Vertigo.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 35\u00b0C:\n",
        "answer": "shivering, will tend to cease, and be followed by the onset of apathy\n",
        "choiceone": "the appearance of intense shivering\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental disorders, and even coma\n",
        "choicethree": "profuse sweating\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "ions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are\nassociated with:\n",
        "answer": "obesity\n",
        "choiceone": "anorexia nervosa\n",
        "choicetwo": "cholera\n",
        "choicethree": "hypoxia\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "As hyperventilation progresses, a pilot can experience\n",
        "answer": "symptoms of suffocation and drowsiness.\n",
        "choiceone": "decreased breathing rate and depth.\n",
        "choicetwo": "heightened awareness and feeling of well being.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is condidered as a step involved in good Aeronautical Deci:\nMaking (ADM) process?\n\n",
        "answer": "identifying personal attitudes hazardous to safe flight.\n",
        "choiceone": "making a rational evaluation of the required actions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "developing the \u2018right stuff attitude.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judgement is based upon:\n",
        "answer": "a process involving a pilot's attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the\nsituation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience\n",
        "choiceone": "a decision-making process involving the 5 physical senses and their use to\nmanually operate the aircraft controls\n",
        "choicetwo": "the development of skills through constant practice of flight manoeuvres\n",
        "choicethree": "the ability to interpret the flight instruments\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense\nand by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:\n",
        "answer": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised\n",
        "choiceone": "both pilots will loose their motor-coordination\n",
        "choicetwo": "both pilots will experience the same amount of stress\n",
        "choicethree": "the pilot feeling threatened, will be much more relaxed, than the pilot looking forward\nto what may happen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anxiety can affect:\n\n4. Judgement\n2. Attention\n\n3. Memory\n\n4. Concentration\n",
        "answer": "All are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 only is correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\tuition.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Decide Model is comprised of a 6-step process to provide a pilot a logical way of\napproaching Aeronautical Decision Making. These steps are:\n",
        "answer": "Detect, estimate, choose, identify, do, and evaluate.\n",
        "choiceone": "Determine, evaluate, choose, identify, do, and eliminate.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Determine, eliminate, choose, identify, detect, and evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "which of the following may more likely result into hypoxia?\n",
        "answer": "reduced barometric pressures at altitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "\u2018cessive nitrogen in the bloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "decreasing amount of oxygen as your altitude increases.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What visual illusion creates the same effect as a narrower-than-usual runway?\n",
        "answer": "An upsloping runway.\n",
        "choiceone": "A wider-than-usual runway.\n",
        "choicetwo": "A downsloping runway.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "During a stall recovery, the instructor allows the student to exceed maneuvering speed.\nWhich best illustrates an \u2018antiauthority\u2019 reaction by the instructor?\n",
        "answer": "The aircraft can handle a lot more than the maneuvering speed.\n",
        "choiceone": "The student should know how to recover from a stall by this time.\n",
        "choicetwo": "There hasn't been a problem doing this in the past.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What physical change would most likely occur to occupants of an unpressurized\naircraft flying above 15,000 feet without supplemental oxygen?\n",
        "answer": "A blue coloration of the lips and fingernails develop along with tunnel vision.\n",
        "choiceone": "Gases trapped in the body contract and prevent nitrogen from escaping the\nbloodstream.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The pressure in the middle ear becomes less than the atmospheric pressure in the\ncabin.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person should be able to overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation by\n",
        "answer": "slowing the breathing rate\n",
        "choiceone": "increasing the breathing rate\n",
        "choicetwo": "refraining from the use of alcohol\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the use of cockpit lighting for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reducing the lighting intensity to a minimum level will eliminate blind spots.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which use of cockpit lighting is correct for night flight?\n",
        "answer": "Reducing the interior lighting intensity to a minimum level.\n",
        "choiceone": "The use of regular white light, such as a flashlight, will not impair night adaptation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Coloration shown on maps is least affected by the use of direct red lighting.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the first step of the Decide Model for effective risk management\nand Aeronautical Decision Making?\n",
        "answer": "Detect.\n",
        "choiceone": "Identify.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Evaluate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aeronautical decision making (ADM) process, what is the first step in neutralizing\na hazardous attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Recognizing hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognizing the invulnerability of the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Making a rational judgement.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To overcome the symptoms of hyperventilation, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "slow the breathing rate.\n",
        "choiceone": "swallow or yawn.\n",
        "choicetwo": "increase the breathing rate.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately:\n",
        "answer": "21% oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "5% oxygen\n",
        "choicetwo": "15% oxygen\n",
        "choicethree": "10% oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "After SCUBA diving (more than 30 feet of depth) you have to wait a period of time before\nflying again. This period is at least:\n",
        "answer": "24 hours\n",
        "choiceone": "6 hours\n",
        "choicetwo": "12 hours\n",
        "choicethree": "48 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n4. Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia.\n2. Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error.\n",
        "answer": "1 and 2 are both correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1 is correct, 2 is false\n",
        "choicetwo": "1is false, 2 is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "1 and 2 are both false\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When suffering from Hypoxia short-term memory impairment starts at approximately ....\n",
        "answer": "12,000 ft\n",
        "choiceone": "10,000 ft\n",
        "choicetwo": "18,000 ft\n",
        "choicethree": "25,000 ft\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of\n",
        "answer": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood,\ntransportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from\nthe body\n",
        "choiceone": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of carbon monoxide\n",
        "choicetwo": "the transportation of oxygen to the cells and the elimination of nitrogen\n",
        "choicethree": "the transportation of carbon dioxide to the cells and elimination of oxygen\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When focussing on near objects:\n",
        "answer": "the shape of lens gets more spherical\n",
        "choiceone": "the shape of lens gets flatter\n",
        "choicetwo": "the cornea gets smaller\n",
        "choicethree": "the pupil gets larger\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods.\n",
        "choiceone": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Cones.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Scotopic Vision is the same as Photopic Vision.\n",
        "choicethree": "Photopic Vision is the same as Peripheral Vision.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Noise induced hearing loss:\n",
        "answer": "is a condition resulting in permanent hearing loss of selected frequencies.\n",
        "choiceone": "is not a permanent hearing loss, the nerve cells frequently recover.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is also known as presbyacusis and is associated with pressure damage to the\nmiddle ear.\n",
        "choicethree": "causes Eustationary Tube dysfunction.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n\n1. eat salad or raw vegetables\n2. peel fruit when neccesary\n\n3. eat food that has been properly cooked\n4. avoid ice-cream\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct answers?\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3and4\n",
        "choiceone": "1and2\n",
        "choicetwo": "1,2and3\n",
        "choicethree": "2and4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "How is Yellow fever contracted?\n",
        "answer": "A virus transmitted by an infected mosquito.\n",
        "choiceone": "Excessive use of alcohol.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Contaminated food or water.\n",
        "choicethree": "By contact with the saliva of infected animals.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two types of attention ?\n",
        "answer": "Selective and divided\n",
        "choiceone": "Intuitive and behavioural\n",
        "choicetwo": "Divided and behavioural\n",
        "choicethree": "Cognitive and intuitive\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ability to monitor information which could indicate the development of a critical\nsituation\n",
        "answer": "is necessary to maintain good situational awareness\n",
        "choiceone": "is dangerous, because it distracts attention from flying the aircraft\n",
        "choicetwo": "makes no sense because the human information processing system is limited\nanyway\n",
        "choicethree": "is responsible for the development of inadequate mental models\nof the real world\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Define Aeronautical Decision Making(ADM)\n",
        "answer": "systematic approach to the mental process used by pilots to consistently determine\nthe best course of action for a given set of circumstances.\n",
        "choiceone": "decision making process which relies on good judgment to reduce risks associated\nwith each flight.\n",
        "choicetwo": "mental process of analyzing all information in a particular situation and making a\ntimely decision on what action to take.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What should a pilot do when recognizing a thought as hazardous?\n",
        "answer": "Label that thought as hazardous, then correct that thought by stating the\ncorresponding learned antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "Avoid developing this hazardous thought.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Develop this hazardous thought and follow through with modified action.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "redirecting that hazardous attitude so that appropriate action can be taken.\n",
        "choiceone": "early recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choicetwo": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Upbringing\n3. Experience\n4. Childhood\n",
        "answer": "1,2, 3 and 4 are correct\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "choicetwo": "None of the listed answers is correct\n",
        "choicethree": "2, 3 and 4 only are correct\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements make up the personality of an individual?\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n\n4. Past experience\n",
        "answer": "1,2,3,4\n",
        "choiceone": "1,2,4\n",
        "choicetwo": "2,3\n",
        "choicethree": "2,3,4\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:\n",
        "answer": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference to an\nobject or a situation\n",
        "choiceone": "form part of personality and, as a result, cannot be changed in an adult\n",
        "choicetwo": "are non-evolutive adaptation procedures regardless of the result of the actions\nassociated with them\n",
        "choicethree": "are essentially driving forces behind changes in personality\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\urban hype.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?\n",
        "answer": "Rely on the indications of the flight instruments.\n",
        "choiceone": "Reduce head and eye movements to the extent possible.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Rely on the kinesthetic sense.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "lusion, when landing on a narrower-than-usual runway, the aircraft will\n\n",
        "answer": "higher than actual, leading to a lower-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "lower than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "choicetwo": "higher than actual, leading to a higher-than-normal approach.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Success in reducing stress associated with a crisis in the cockpit begins with\n",
        "answer": "assessing stress areas in one's personal life.\n",
        "choiceone": "eliminating the more serious life and cockpit stress issues.\n",
        "choicetwo": "knowing the exact cause of the stress.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What effect does haze have on the ability to see traffic or terrain features during flight?\n",
        "answer": "Haze creates the illusion of being a greater distance than actual from the runway,\nand causes pilots to fly a lower approach.\n",
        "choiceone": "Haze causes the eyes to focus at infinity, making terrain features harder to see.\n",
        "choicetwo": "The eyes tend to overwork in haze and do not detect relative movement easily.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rapid or extra deep breathing while using oxygen can cause\n",
        "answer": "hyperventilation.\n",
        "choiceone": "cyanosis.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a build-up of carbon dioxide in the body.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, a pilot should\n",
        "answer": "try to relax and think rationally at the first sign of stress.\n",
        "choiceone": "think of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will degrade the ability to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A rapid acceleration during takeoff can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "being in a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choiceone": "spinning in the opposite direction.\n",
        "choicetwo": "diving into the ground.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and left during straight-\nand-level flight?\n",
        "answer": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals.\n",
        "choiceone": "Concentrate on relative movement detected in the peripheral vision area.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Continuous sweeping of the windshield from right to left.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "An abrupt change from climb to straight-and-level flight can create the illusion of\n",
        "answer": "tumbling backwards.\n",
        "choiceone": "a noseup attitude.\n",
        "choicetwo": "a descent with the wings level.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon, and a dark scene spread with ground\nlights and stars can create an illusion known as\n",
        "answer": "false horizons.\n",
        "choiceone": "elevator illusions.\n",
        "choicetwo": "autokinesis.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What action should be taken if hyperventilation is suspected?\n",
        "answer": "Consciously breathe at a slower rate than normal.\n",
        "choiceone": "Breathe at a slower rate by taking very deep breaths.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Consciously force yourself to take deep breaths and breathe at a faster rate than\nnormal.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the antidote for a pilot with a \u2018macho\u2019 attitude?\n",
        "answer": "Taking chances is foolish.\n",
        "choiceone": "I'm not helpless. | can make a difference.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Follow the rules. They are usually right.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hazardous attitudes which contribute to poor pilot judgment can be effectively\ncounteracted by\n",
        "answer": "an appropriate antidote.\n",
        "choiceone": "taking meaningful steps to be more assertive with attitudes.\n",
        "choicetwo": "early recognition of these hazardous attitudes.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these would most likely result in hyperventilation?\n",
        "answer": "Insufficient carbon dioxide.\n",
        "choiceone": "Insufficient oxygen.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Excessive carbon monoxide.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fatigue and stress\n",
        "answer": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choiceone": "increase the tolerance to hypoxia\n",
        "choicetwo": "do not affect hypoxia at all\n",
        "choicethree": "will increase the tolerance to hypoxia when flying below 15 000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:\n",
        "answer": "partial oxygen pressure is below the critical value of 55mm/Hg\n",
        "choiceone": "composition of the blood changes\n",
        "choicetwo": "composition of the air is different from sea level\n",
        "choicethree": "percentage of oxygen is lower than at sea level\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily regulated by the concentration of:\n",
        "answer": "carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choiceone": "nitrogen in the air\n",
        "choicetwo": "water vapour in the alveoli\n",
        "choicethree": "\u00bbxygen in the cells\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying a non-pressurized light aircraft at 9 000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:\n",
        "answer": "you reduce altitude and supply him/her with oxygen.\n",
        "choiceone": "you supply him/her with extra oxygen, but do not reduce altitude .\n",
        "choicetwo": "you supply additional oxygen but controlled.\n",
        "choicethree": "calm him/her and occupy him with suitable tasks.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:\n",
        "answer": "decompression sickness\n",
        "choiceone": "hyperventilation\n",
        "choicetwo": "hypoxia\n",
        "choicethree": "stress\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Healthy people are usually capable of compensating for a lack of oxygen up to:\n",
        "answer": "10.000 - 12.000feet\n",
        "choiceone": "15.000 feet\n",
        "choicetwo": "20.000 feet\n",
        "choicethree": "25.000 feet\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by\n",
        "answer": "decreased ability of the haemoglobin to transport oxygen\n",
        "choiceone": "lack of nitrogen in ambient air\n",
        "choicetwo": "too much carbon dioxide in the blood\n",
        "choicethree": "increasing oxygen partial pressure used for the exchange of gases\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness\n",
        "answer": "are bends, chokes, creeps and neurological symptoms\n",
        "choiceone": "are only relevant when diving\n",
        "choicetwo": "can only develop at altitudes of more than 40000 FT\n",
        "choicethree": "are flatulence and pain in the middle ear\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this phys\nstress?\n",
        "answer": "By intense vasoconstriction.\n",
        "choiceone": "By vasodilatation which permits a greater flow of blood to the periphery.\n",
        "choicetwo": "By speeding up the metabolic rate in the Autonomic Nervous System.\n",
        "choicethree": "By increasing cardiac frequency.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Illuminated anti-collision lights in IMC\n",
        "answer": "can cause disorientation\n",
        "choiceone": "can cause colour-illusions\n",
        "choicetwo": "will improve the pilots depth perception\n",
        "choicethree": "will effect the pilots binocular vision\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cataract is caused by:\n",
        "answer": "A clouding of the lens\n",
        "choiceone": "Lack of mobility of the cornea\n",
        "choicetwo": "A lack of accommodation at the cornea\n",
        "choicethree": "A mis-shapened cornea\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presbyopia:\n",
        "answer": "is common over the age of 50.\n",
        "choiceone": "is caused by long-termed exposure to stimuli over 90dB.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is partial visual loss due to pressure changes in the eye.\n",
        "choicethree": "surgical replacement of the lens the usual treatment and is compatible with flying.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equ:\naltitude is changed?\n\nition of pressure take place, when\n",
        "answer": "Eustachian tube\n",
        "choiceone": "Cochlea\n",
        "choicetwo": "Tympanic membrane\n",
        "choicethree": "External auditory canal\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?\n",
        "answer": "Turning in the opposite direction\n",
        "choiceone": "Flying straight and level\n",
        "choicetwo": "Climbing\n",
        "choicethree": "Turning into the original direction\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Flying with a \u201ccommon cold\":\n",
        "answer": "may lead to incapacitation due to severe sinus or ear pain.\n",
        "choiceone": "is permitted as long as you are on treatment with antibiotics.\n",
        "choicetwo": "will cause infection in other crew members if you are flying in a pressurised aircraft.\n",
        "choicethree": "increases the risk of hypertension.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning in flig|\n",
        "answer": "presents an extremely dangerous situation as the blood may not be able carry\nsufficient amounts of oxygen to vital cells and tissues of the body.\n",
        "choiceone": "can be cured by breathing into a plastic bag to retain the carbon monoxide.\n",
        "choicetwo": "is usually harmless because oxygen is more easily attached to haemoglobin than\ncarbon monoxide to a magnitude of 200 times.\n",
        "choicethree": "is a complication when hyperventilating and requires its own special and individual\ntreatment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "To help manage cockpit stress, pilots must\n",
        "answer": "condition themselves to relax and think rationally when stress appears.\n",
        "choiceone": "be aware of life stress situations that are similar to those in flying.\n",
        "choicetwo": "avoid situations that will improve their abilities to handle cockpit responsibilities.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory\n",
        "answer": "about 20 seconds\n",
        "choiceone": "less than 1 second\n",
        "choicetwo": "from 5 to 10 minutes\n",
        "choicethree": "around 24 hours\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \u201creversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\u201d are:\n\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when lations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress\n\n",
        "answer": "1. and 3.\n",
        "choiceone": "1. and 2.\n",
        "choicetwo": "3 only.\n",
        "choicethree": "2. and 3.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whatis the current approach to human error?\n",
        "answer": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choiceone": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system/procedural errors.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Realisation that humans are infallible and that systems/procedures should be\ndesigned to minimise human error.\n",
        "choicethree": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be\nbrought into line to prevent system, latent and procedural errors.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stereotypes\u201d are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:\n",
        "answer": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them.\n",
        "choiceone": "develop better teamwork by standardizing procedures.\n",
        "choicetwo": "communicate non-verbally with a stranger.\n",
        "choicethree": "act in the same manner in all situations and thus assuring stability.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct?\n",
        "answer": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper\nthe communication process.\n",
        "choiceone": "There is no relation between inadequate communication and incidents or accidents.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Inconsistent communication improves flight safety.\n",
        "choicethree": "Personal conflict that takes place prior to take-off should wait to be addressed until\nthe end of the flight.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the first step in neutralizing a hazardous attitude in the ADM process?\n",
        "answer": "Recognition of hazardous thoughts.\n",
        "choiceone": "Recognition of invulnerability in the situation.\n",
        "choicetwo": "Dealing with improper judgment.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "The basic drive for a pilot to demonstrate the \u2018right stuff can have an adverse effect on\nsafety, by\n",
        "answer": "generating tendencies that lead to practices that are dangerous, often illegal, and\nmay lead to a mishap.\n",
        "choiceone": "a total disregard for any alternative course of action.\n",
        "choicetwo": "imposing a realistic assessment of piloting skills under stressful conditions.\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "Attitudes are defined as:\n",
        "answer": "tendencies to respond to people, things or events in a particular manner\n",
        "choiceone": "the conditions necessary for carrying out an activity\n",
        "choicetwo": "the genetic predispositions for thinking and acting\n",
        "choicethree": "a synonym for behaviour\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:\n",
        "answer": "distress\n",
        "choiceone": "coping stress\n",
        "choicetwo": "eustress\n",
        "choicethree": "stressors\n",
        "source": "pdf/Type3/hp\\William Ariho_21-07-2014_PPL(A)_040-Human Performance.pdf"
    }
]